DAHLIA MALKI: All right, good morning, everybody.
AUDIENCE: Good morning!
>> Oh, yeah, nothing like 200 geeks awake
at 9 in the morning.
What a sight.
So this talk can be one sentence.
In every round, every node picks a random
target, exchanges some information, and waits
for the next round.
This is what I like about gossip algorithm,
they're simple, they're really literally one
line.
Because they're so simple, they're robust
to implement and simple and yet they're remarkably
efficient and fault toll rant.
Today I'm going to talk about three protocols
of this family, and go down to the basics.
And we'll go right away.
So the story actually begins with a company
that introduced and commercialized this technology.
How many people recognize the technology and
the company?
Not a single one.
Laugh.
OK.
This is the company that also introduced the
first PC.
The object-oriented programming languages,
the mouse, the ethernet, the first laser printer.
How many people know what I am tea talking
about now?
All right.
So this is a xerox.
It took it 20 years to take this first successful
paper to paper copy.
This was the first successful copy of one
paper to another.
It took it 20 years to commercialize this
and become, you know, a commercial product.
And then they realized that the office of
tomorrow is going to be at least partially
digital, so they founded Xerox Park and they
started this amazing group of researchers
to help bring Xerox to the digital age, and
this is where this amazing group of scientists
encountered the problem that led to the birth
of these gossip-based protocols.
So what was the problem that they were grappling
with?
So in the grapevine system, which was also
one of the first if not the first distributed
network system, they needed to keep copies
of data consistent, and they came up with
this randomized protocol for doing this, which
later received rigorous analysis, first in
a POTC87 paper, and then further even more
strict and some variations of analysis in
a wonderful FOX2000 paper.
So what are we talking about?
So the problem, the basic problem in grapevine
was initially to keep copies of mail synchronized
throughout the cluster.
So mail would arrive at one of the nodes and
from here, I'm going to talk about a network
of nodes, and refer to all the players or
participants or processes or pieces simply
as nodes.
So mail arrives at one of the nodes, and the
obvious first solution that they came up with
was direct mail.
As soon as the mail arrives, the node multi-casts
the mail to all of the nodes in the network
such that users can access their mail from
any node in this network.
Problem?
First of all, multi-cast is somewhat expensive.
Networks did not necessarily support it, so
the node had to contact one at a time.
Each one of the nodes in the network, which
was already getting very, very scalable at
a time.
We're talking about 8 to 16 nodes.
That was a heavy burden.
And it was difficult, because there were also
failures, so at the time when the mail arrived,
and the node was trying to contact one of
the nodes, it may be down or there may be
message omissions so it had to remember to
contact later, and then maybe when later the
node that used to be down is up, now the origin
would then fail, and so they ran into a lot
of difficulties of keeping this direct mail
method working.
So their second attempt was what they called
anti-entropy.
So anti- entropy worked by occasionally having
nodes contact one another and compare their
database of mails, and later they used the
same thing for something like DNS, for network
addresses directory, so they would just compare
their entire database and see what's missing
and then send each other the missing information.
So that actually worked, and converged, and
any information in the network would eventually
reach everybody.
So already there was some randomization here,
so by occasionally picking a random communication
partner, every period of time, and synchronizing
with them, there was already this phenomenon
that over time all necessary information got
everywhere.
But it also fundamentally relied on synchronizing
databases, comparing them and sending what's
missing, keeping information essentially forever,
even deletions had to be kept around for quite
a long time in order for synchronization to
work.
It was quite expensive and quite slow to operate.
So finally this led to the first actual gossip
protocol, which from here on I will refer
to as randomized gossip, and that was the
rumormongering protocol.
So here the idea is to totally rely on gossip
to spread information, so mail or any kind
of update more generally arrives at a node,
the node keeps it for a certain duration,
during this duration, every once in a while
every period wakes up, sends a copy to a random
partner and then after a duration, if you
believe that the gossip worked, it marks these
information as no longer hot and stops gossiping
about it.
All other nodes do the same thing.
Every once in a while, wake up, send a copy
of their information, do that for a few rounds,
exactly the duration that the gossip proceed
ducts that's needed, and then mark this information
as OK, completely synchronized, gossip has
completed, and stop gossiping about it.
So complete reliance on the gossip protocol
to disseminate the information throughout
the network, completely, and reliably.
So now let's move away from grapevine and
look at this more foundationally.
I know it's early in the morning, but my hope
it to look at the foundations, look at the
analysis of this without scaring you and to
actually make it more accessible, not less,
if I can understand it, I think anybody can.
So in order to do this, we do need to look
at, you know, the precise definitions and
assumptions made in this algorithm.
It's a really simple, one-line algorithm.
So all we need is to say the following: We
assume -- or we ask the protocol to work in
logically synchronous rounds.
We're not going to mix and match messages
from different rounds.
So logically all the nodes in the network
go through rounds one at a time where they
do their operations, process and continue
to the next round.
So logically it's a wave of actions one by
one.
So that's what we mean when we say by synchronous
rounds.
We're going to implement it this way and we
also need this for the analysis.
As we said, the algorithm is just one line.
In each one of these rounds, a node picks
a random target, and exchanges information
with it.
For this to actually be meaningful, for this
to be well defined, implicitly we assume that
every node knows all the other nodes in the
network and from here, we're going to use
n to denote the obligatory number of nodes
in the network.
But implicitly notice that the assumption
here is that there's full information and
full connectivity in this net work, so every
node can pick another node perfectly uniformly
at random.
This will not work if there's any kind of
skew or information is lacking.
And this assumption does not hold.
And the assumption about the network is that
every node can in fact form an interaction
with every other node in the network.
So in this framework, there are many, many
protocols and many variants.
I'm going to look at three today.
The first one is the analysis of this rumor-mongering
that I just talked about, just a simple synthesis
of information that.
This was the system that was developed at
Xerox PARC.
The second is method detailed at Cornell University.
And the third one with will be network discovery
where the information we send is used to build
the network itself.
And this is a method and work that was developed
by the Akamai engineers when they faced scalable
networking.
OK, so let me start with a simple information
dissemination, rumor-mongering.
So we'll do that first by demonstration, so
here we have a network, it's a full network,
everybody is connected to everybody else.
We will call the node that first holds a copy
of the message informed in the literature
sometimes it's infected or you know, many
other terms.
Here I will call every node that holds a copy
of the information that we want to spread informed
All right, so we have the first node that's
informed and what's used to spread the message
using randomized gossip.
So first for clarity of the slides get rid
of the network and we're going to assume this
implicitly from now on.
It's going to pick a random parter and send
information to it.
So here I want to give you a point of view
which you won't actually find in the literature,
and it's not actually really precise or correct,
but just mind intuition the way I think about
it.
So the way I think about it is the original
node had the responsibility to send a copy
of the original gossip message to n recipients.
It's going to recruit help and say look, why
don't you be responsible for half of it and
I'll still be responsible for half of it.
OK, so now in the next round, we have another
node which is informed, and in the next round,
they're both going to proceed autonomously
and concurrently.
So now two nodes are actually gossiping and
they're each doing the same thing.
They're each picking another node to help
them, not just to inform them but also to
become active gossipers of the message.
So it's as if they say in the next round,
OK, we had responsibility each for half of
the dissemination, and now each one of us
is going to choose a partner and ask for help
in a quarter.
So now we have four nodes, each one of them
responsible for further spreading the message
to a quarter.
And this continues in the next round, it's
n over 8.
Now, I only have 8 nodes on this slide, so
in principle, we should have completed, if
this was precise, but we know that actually
what happens is that there's certain inefficiency.
Nodes will collide and send the same information
to the same target, so actually we didn't
finish and another round is needed in this
example to finish.
Let me actually scroll back and look at the
process again, a little bit slowly.
So what really happens is that first, most
of the nodes that are chosen as gossip partners
are not informed.
So with very good efficiency, every gossip
message reaches an uninformed node, and turns
it into informed.
And this happens so long as about half of
the network is still uninformed.
We have the probability of at least a half
of reaching an uninformed nodes, so really
every round is very effective.
It grows the number of informed nodes by a
constant factor, almost doubles the number
of informed nodes.
At some point the network starts becoming
mostly informed, and here we start wasting
communication just to reach the few unlucky
nodes that are still uninformed.
So here there's only one uninformed node and
everybody is trying to target it, hopefully
within a few rounds somebody will actually
pick this unlucky node and complete the process.
So this intuition is in fact what we can use
for formal analysis.
So to look at the formal analysis, we're looking
at the number of aspects of the process.
So first of all, again, we have n nodes and
we're going to look at the gossip process
and its complexity, focusing on gossip of
one message only.
There may be a lot of messages and in fact
in most systems, there may be multiple messages,
simultaneously being gossiped and we're going
to piggyback on the same connections and potentially
transfer many messages but for the analysis
it's enough to follow what's happening for
one message only.
And then it turns out that the basic framework
that I gave still there's a lot of flexibility.
So the framework says in every round a node
picks a random partner for interaction, but
it doesn't really say then how do they exchange
information, and in fact, it turns out that
very different behavior occurs if the information
is pushed to the partner, if the information
is pulled from it, or if it's pushed and pulled.
And I think that that understanding it gives
a lot of insight on this process and I'm going
to do this in the next few minutes.
It's going to be a little bit of math.
If you really, really dread it, this is the
time to go on your Twitter and come back in
about 20 minutes.
So in about 10 minutes I'll get back to failure
detection or if you're really waiting for
it this is the 10 minutes that you could take
a little bit of math but really just a little
bit.
I'll try to be precise and at the same time,
gloss over some details.
So let's first look and say something obvious.
It's sort of obvious that if at every round
every node has -- is allowed only one interaction,
one connection with one other node.
The best we could do is spread the message
in log n number of rounds.
Let's look at the graph of all of connections
which are formed during this process.
OK, this is a graph where each node has out
degree, has a logarithmic log n number of
corrections that it chooses to other nodes
and it's well known in the theory of random
graphs that this graph will have log n diameter,
with high probability in expectation and also
with very high probability.
So if the graph has log n diameter and we're
starting with a examination on one node, it
will take log n even with the best structure
of algorithm to cross the graph.
If you're looking at what I'm saying in the
slide it's not the same.
This is saying the same thing, but actually
proving it.
But if you just think of this as a random
graph with log n edges, you immediately see
that it will take, you know, logarithmic number
of steps for the message to move from one
end of the graph to another.
OK, now let's look.
So this is the lower bound.
There's nothing you can do better with so
few connection.
Let's look actually at an upper bound, so
how long does it take to actually complete.
And we're going to split the analysis into
push and pull.
We'll start with the push analysis.
And we're going to split the push analysis
into two parts.
The first part is when less than half of the
network is informed, so the message has reached,
less than half of the network.
What we can say then is that every push by
an informed node has a pretty good chance
of succeeding, at least half.
And in expectation, all together, the set
of informed nodes have an expected half, you
know, is expected to grow by a factor of at
least half of them.
So at least half of them actually get to uninformed
nodes.
So this is an expectation.
There are two things that we need to do in
order to move this into a high probability,
high assurance result.
And in this talk and in most of the papers
we will consider something that happens with
probability at least 1n 1/n.
We'll consider that small enough probability.
It's really easy to get this to 1 over n squared
or any probability that you want.
Any polynomial probability that you want.
So in order to move this to high probability
behavior, we need to consider two things.
The one is even if informed nodes get to uninformed
nodes there's some collision, so there's some
loss of efficiency there.
And secondly, you know, these -- even though
the selection of partners is completely independent,
the actual sum of uninformed nodes that become
informed, that's not an independent sum.
But the dependency is small enough, every
two nodes can affect each other by at most
1 if they collide and the collisions are rare
enough that you can rigorously show that the
actual progress of the process is very close
to the expectation.
So our intuition and actual rigorous analysis
are completely perfectly aligned in this case.
Until you know half of -- or any constant
fraction of the network are informed, every
round increases the set of informed nodes
by a constant factor.
It's not exactly double, but it's close to
it.
I can definitely say that it's at least grows
by a third.
So this is the first half of the process.
The second half of the process is when already
a significant fraction of the network, let's
say a half, are informed.
What happens then?
So this is the part where we are losing a
lot of inefficiency just to get to the last
remaining nodes.
And those of you who are familiar with coupon-collector
analysis, this is exactly what's going on.
We're going to throw a lot, a lot of messages,
n log n messages just to make sure that every
single note is not missed.
And so now, in each round, at least half of
the network is informed, so in each round,
we are in fact throwing a linear number-messages,
n/2 at least, and so if we looked at the probability
of an uninformed node to actually receive
any one of these messages, there's a little
formula there.
It's really a trivial formula.
If I'm an uninformed node, the probability
that somebody, you know, one other node chooses
me, is pretty small.
It's 1/n, the probability that I'm not chosen
by that one other player is 1-1/n, but the
probability that all of them don't choose
me, that's 1-1/n raised to the power of the
number of uninformed nodes.
At least 1/2.
And if you look at this formula it converts
very easily to e to the-1/2.
So the actual number doesn't really matter
whether it's a third or one other square root
of 3.
It's a constant number, non-negligible one,
that if I'm uninformed in around 1/2 random
messages are send, I will receive it.
So that's the probability.
In order for this to happen with high probability,
I can raise this to log n and after log n
rounds, then with high probability, I will
not be missed and all of the nodes will not
be missed.
And this is again why I need the high probability
to be at least 1/n so that in all nodes this
will actually happen.
So a very simple analysis actually shows this
powerful result that says that this actually
happens.
This is a randomized protocol, but with very
good strict guarantees of convergence.
So this was the push protocol.
I think it's actually remarkably illuminating
to also look at the pull protocol.
I'll do it very quickly.
In the pull protocol I'm using the basic same
framework.
Every node chooses a partner at random in
a round.
But now whenever a node chooses another node
to interact with, it pulls information from
it.
Whatever it has, it pulls from it.
What happens in this protocol is that a very,
very same analysis to what we just had says
that the one, you know, when we start, the
one node that actually has the message will
be selected by one other node with constant
probability, exactly the same probability
as in the opposite direction.
So that's good.
So this will look a little bit like gossip,
so one node pulls from the informed node,
looks a little bit like the informed node
pushes to one other node.
Except that with non-negligible probability,
this will also not happen in the first round
or the second round or ten rounds and in fact,
it's not unlikely at all that for logarithmic
number of rounds, no pulls will be successful.
Only log n rounds can I guarantee that even
a single pool succeeds, and the same thing
happens if you know, one or two pulls succeed
and we have a small constant number of informed
nodes, we can still, you know, not very unlikely
that we'll miss them or definitely not grow
the set of informed nodes by a constant factor.
So there's a long startup of the pull process
until we reach a logarithmic size of informed
set.
Once we cross that threshold, then the rest
of the first part of the process behaves exactly
like push.
So the set of informed nodes will increase
by a constant factor in every round.
The second half of the pull process, once
a significant part of the network, half of
the network is informed, that's actually considerably
different and remarkably, you know, insightful,
to what goes on in the gossip process.
So now we have, you know, some fraction, let's
say half of the network, which are informed.
And the other half is uninformed.
So let's say that we have some fraction which
are uninformed.
I'll.
You can immediately say that an uninformed
node stays uninformed with probability C.
So we have C times n uninformed nodes and
uninformed nodes picks a node at random.
It picks an uninformed node.
Probability 1 picks an uninformed node.
So the expected number of uninformed nodes
goes from CXn to C squared Xn, but this is
very, very different from 2 times C. So now
we're squaring the fraction of uninformed
nodes in every round.
So if we start with half of n uninformed in
one round we go to a quarter.
In the next round we grow to?
AUDIENCE: 8.
No, good, that's what I was ready for.
So not to an eighth, but to 1/4 squared, which
is?
16.
>> Not to put you on the spot.
This really takes a moment to stop and think.
This is a really much much faster process.
This is not an exponential process, this is
super-exponential, so again, very trivial
math, nothing complicated, sorry.
[laughter]
But what it means is that in the pull process
now, the part of the gossip process kiss heavy,
which is really sending a lot of messages,
converges much much more quickly and if you
do the math, it's log log n rounds and log
log n rounds to this audience, to me, that's
as good as a constant.
That is a really, really small number.
So pull and push are very, very different,
and this led to a beautiful result in the
2000 paper, by Karp et al., where they've
combined push and push, they say, well, pull
has this long warmup, startup phase, but then
after it reaches a certain fraction of the
network, it converges much much more quickly,
much more efficiently and with much fewer
rounds, but not just rounds, messages.
If we could only identify when to transition,
then we're good, and so they've developed
a simple protocol that carries information
with it, and identifies when to switch over,
and so then the first part of gossip, where
the first informed nodes sends to others,
then two others send to four, and then all
of this initial phase we're only sending linear
number of messages.
And then in the second half, if we switch
to pull, we're sending almost linear.
We're send N times log log n, which for all
practical purposes is almost linear.
So to wrap up the first protocol in this family,
and really the one that started the interest
in randomized gossip protocol, the basic rumor-mongering,
basic information dissemination by gossip
protocol, we didn't talk at all about this,
but it's inherently fault tolerant.
If we choose a random partner that's faulty
at any point in the protocol, it's remarkably
resilient to that.
It's very simple.
We talked about it being one line.
And when you understand the round and the
message complexity, you can see that first
of all the round complexity is as optimal
as it can be.
The message plexity, well, there is a cost.
Naively, you -- so you say slightly more than
some deterministic multi-cast regime, but
still, you main, you know, amazing simplicity
and fault tolerance.
At the same time, I also emphasize that all
of this works, and we can analyze it in a
full network with perfect knowledge of the
network.
We don't know anything if any process has
only partial knowledge.
Some selections, some random subset of the
network to talk to, you we don't know anything
about the convergence of this protocol.
Any questions before we move to, you know,
interesting use cases?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Is it possible in the push protocol
to make sure a node doesn't push to the same
node as --
>> No.
>> Is there any way to guarantee that the
same node is not picked twice as a gossip
target, either by the same node or even from
two?
I mean, you can patch -- you can patch the
protocol, the basic framework did not preclude
this and does not need this.
So ... that didn't answer your question?
I was talking the same node.
The same node as pushing, it wouldn't push
the same node twice, would it?
>> So you can definitely add to your algorithm
some, you know, simple test that removes this
duplicity, it's not going to change the -- you
know, most of the complexity and the analysis
remains exactly the same, but you could definitely
avoid this as really unnecessary.
Not much efficiency is lost there.
That's not a common event.
AUDIENCE: OK.
OK, yeah?
>> (We have a microphone.)
>> I was just curious, do you happen to have,
for example, a number for some, you know,
in an example system where this has been deployed,
a number for what the probability actually
is after the log n number of rounds that we
got very unlikely and didn't reach them all?
Because it seems like we don't really know
if we did or not.
So it seems interesting to know.
>> So these numbers can be easily computed
and they are in the papers.
I can't give you a number off the top of my
head.
It's also not a number.
It's a function of n.
But I can tell you it goes very quickly.
This is an exponential process, so it goes
down very, very quickly polynomially.
If you do 2 log n rounds, the probability
is 1 over n squared.
If you do 3, it will be 1/n cubed.
So you can definitely pinpoint the probability
very easily, and very precisely.
Yeah.
Yeah, one more question here and then maybe
I'll continue and defer questions to the end.
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, when you switch to the pull
protocol, how do the nodes that don't know
that they need to know something, know that
it's time to pull?
>> Yeah, so that's a perfect question and
I'll refer you to the paper, because -- uh,
uh, I don't have time to go over it.
It's not a trivial protocol.
It's a really, really nice protocol.
It's also not a complicated one.
Really beautiful protocol.
I recommend that you read the Fox paper.
Now maybe it will look a little more accessible.
Fox is a very scary conference in general,
but yeah.
[laughter]
>> All right.
So now let's switch gears and talk about one
of the most exciting use cases that I see
in practice these days and that's failure
detection.
>> So the work actually started by some early
paper on gossip-style failure detectors by
... which simply used gossip to replace the
multi-cast of heartbeats in a network.
That did not actually work too well and that
led to an improved attempt in the SWIM protocol.
So the SWIM protocol is what I'm going to
talk about today.
So in a nutshell, what SWIM does is two components
for maintaining failure detection in a scalable
network.
The first one is to say, we don't want everybody
to monitor everybody else.
We don't want this, you know, quadratic behavior.
We also don't want a centralized monitoring
service to have to monitor a very large and
scalable network.
So what we're going to do is we're going to
use this randomized regime, randomized framework,
for monitoring.
So in every round we're going to pick -- we're
going to let each node pick a node at random
and test its health, send in a message and
wait for a reply.
And because this somewhat ad hoc testing is
less stable, less predictable than actually
having a heartbeat monitoring service implemented
over, you know, some reliable transport, like
TCP/IP, because of this ad hoc wake up, send
a message, and wait for a reply, that has
some stability concerns.
The second idea in SWIM is that when a response
does not arrive, we elicit help from peers
and ask them to also try to ping a node that's
not responsive.
We only actually detect or suspect a failure
if all of the group of peers jointly do not
receive a response from this node.
So this is the first part.
This is a randomized failure probing or health
probing.
The second part is, what do we do when a problem
is detected or some change is detected?
And here again, the idea is to use gossip
to disseminate only these changes alerts:
Only these rare alerts and notifications,
we use gossip for them.
So some of the nice ideas and properties that
are promised by this paradigm is, OK, we don't
have a centralized monitoring service and
we don't have all to all, but because of the
nice properties of gossip, we know that every
node has a pretty good chance, has a constant
probability, of being selected by one other
node in a round.
And also has a constant probability of actually
being selected.
So if there is a failure with constant probability,
some node will detect it.
So this is, you know, this is a completeness
property, and at the same time, because everything
is built on top of the gossip framework, the
fundamental overhead appears to be constant
in every round, essentially we're forming
a constant number of interactions, so no matter
what we do, we send information, we expect
responses back, it fundamentally scales.
>> And also, this idea that we separate the
monitoring and the actual dissemination of
alerts, that's also a really nice property
and a really nice idea of this framework.
Monitoring is something that you need to do
periodically and there's no way around it
and we use randomization to drive the cost
low.
Alerts and notification on the other hand,
they should be pretty rare.
So we don't want to conflate these two, and
have to exchange information about the status
of the network in each and every round.
Only when actually something occur, then we
actually need to send alerts.
So this is the basic idea in SWIM and let's
again see the protocol by example.
So here's a case where we have a network,
you know, for the purposes of SWIM, I needed
some more nodes to fill up the slide.
We're not going to be able to do it with 8
nodes.
And potentially one node, A, here is faulty.
So with constant probability, some other node,
B, will actually choose it as a random partner
and within a few rounds this will hopefully
happen.
We'll send a message, we'll not get a response.
So it will elicit help from peers so now there's
a peer group, they're all sending messages
to A, all of these messages are not being
answered and then there will be a failure
detection.
And so this will lead to a normal gossip protocol.
So now B wants to gossip to the network information
about the failure detection.
So it's going to spread around this rumor,
A is faulty.
And this will work.
First there's only one source, second round
there are already two sources and we expect
this exponential behavior where nodes are
spreading this information and very quickly
within logarithmic number of rounds, the network
knows about it.
OK, but wait, wait.
Let's actually go back to the first time that
this gossip is sent.
At this point, we already know from before
very, very few nodes know about this.
At this point it was the origin and now it's
you know, selecting one more random partner,
so the rest of the network doesn't know about
the failure and we're going to take our time
and gossip about it slowly.
But remember, meanwhile we're continuing,
you know, the normal operation of the SWIM
protocol.
So in the next round, with good probability,
another node will pick A as the target for
monitoring, so this is the node C. Node C
pings to A, doesn't get a response, what's
it going to do it's going to elicit help from
peers.
So now there's a group of peers that are also
swarming A with probes and the same thing
happens in the next round, so now two nodes
are gossiping A's failure to four nodes but
still most of the network doesn't know about
it, so there's a node D now that also probes
A and there's a group of peers that will come
around to help and this will actually continue
as we know until about half of the network
already learns about the failure.
Everybody in every round will continue probing
the same process A, and this will result in
an inflation of probes all targeted at A because
we're now eliciting peers to help and so if
there's a node that is having any kind of
transient network problems or any slowdown
what will happen is that after once it's detected
to have a problem, actually the next rounds
will only exacerbate it.
It doesn't have any steady monitoring relationship
with any, you know, centralize had had monitoring
in every round, again and again, you know,
a group of messages will actually target it.
Also, if there is in fact a failure, if A
was faulty, it may take quite a while.
So in a large network, you know, people are
talking about 1,000 or 10,000 nodes, order
log n rounds to spread this information is
quite a while.
So we saw that until actually information
about, you know, the failed response spreads
in the network, that could take quite a long
time, and remember, we don't want to, you
know, this is a failure detection, we don't
want to send these probes too frequently,
so the gap, the period between rounds is pretty
sizable.
So it takes quite a long time for this information
to actually spread.
And during this time, as we saw, all of the
probes will continue.
So one might ask, I don't know, and I invite
to discussion and I'll be happy to hear some
of the experiences you have, but one might
ask could some of the alternatives actually
help here.
So some of the alternatives is to actually
leverage and use the transport protocol, you
know, strong properties, whether it's TCP/IP
or something else.
Whether it's a ring or some other hierarchical
structure and perhaps even have a heartbeat
monitoring relationship when a failure is
detected, then it's forced on the other side,
who knows, that might actually get over some
of these difficulties.
But we're not even done.
Let's continue looking at the SWIM process,
and now let's look at a slightly different
scenario.
So here, A was not actually faulty.
So either we missed, you know, some response
from it, or maybe even A was the one that
was faulty.
Maybe it slept for a while, came back and
missed all of the responses that A sent it
and also the peers that it recorded sent it.
So there's this faulty notification which
is, which we start to gossip, and immediately
another node, you know, in the next round
probes A and actually discovers that A is
healthy.
So this is the green probing.
But it's not going to do anything about it,
because nobody reported that A is faulty yet.
Gossip takes a long time to actually propagate.
So this could happen to C and can happen to
D and in fact again, we know that up until
almost the end of the gossip process, most
of the network doesn't know about it.
Only after a logarithmic number of rounds,
when we reach let's say half of the network
and half of them know that A is faulty, only
then do we expect some node to emerge that
both heard that, you for example A is being
suspected, and goes and probes A in that round
as the random partner and sees that oh, no,
A is alive.
So here we're starting to see that additional
enhancements to the protocol were needed,
so SWIM introduced this model that it's just
a suspicion, everybody holds onto it for a
while and don't really remove the node from
the membership and see whether there's any
conflicting information.
If anybody actually probes the node and finds
that it's healthy it's going to start a conflicting
rumor.
So now we have one rumor about the failure
and another conflicting rumor saying the node
is alive.
And we know that rumors are completely randomized.
Some of them hear about the health of the
node first before they here about the suspicion
and all of them are around and all of this
is going on for a pretty prolonged period
of time because we're talking about a logarithmic
process where each probing period is itself
non-negligible.
So let's start a confirmation that's again
a third rumor.
Now I'm going to confirm this.
But now you need to get the rest of the network
to converge.
So here's a third rumor that confirms the
suspicion.
So this works great in the case where, you
know, there was a failed suspicion, you know,
a false suspicion by B, so B was out for a
while, suspected A, tried to spread a rumor
that A was faulty, and then immediately everybody
corrected it.
This could work great.
Except that wait, what if A really was faulty,
but the last message from A actually did reach
C?
So C has heard that there's a suspicion about
A and tried to probe it, coincidentally in
that round and was actually able to get some
responses due to some timing and ordering
problem.
Well, what happens now is that everybody in
proceeding rounds will again and again probe
A, and this could be C and D and E, and you
know, for logarithmic number of rounds.
Everybody will probe A, will find out that
it's faulty, will reinforce the gossip that
A is faulty, but that there was this one message,
one node that received the last response from
A saying no, A is alive, and it's going to
supersede all of them.
OK because this is gossip, everything arrives
out of order.
So in summary, if you look at some of the
enhancements that needed to make SWIM operate,
there are quite a few of them.
So we talked about the basic difficulty of
asynchronously probing, we don't actually
have full trust in this probing mechanism
because it's so ad hoc, so we're fixing it
by having suspicions instead of detection,
and then we have false suspicions with alive
messages, we have confirmations of non-false
suspicions with confirmation messages, all
of these gossips are occurring in parallel.
When there's a single very clear failure crash,
yes it will be detected, yes it will be spread
in the network quite efficiently.
You know, it will take a while, but eventually
with some gap everything will converge.
When there are multiple occurrences in the
network, not clear.
So some of the additional enhancements that
were needed in SWIM, because of these behaviors
were, OK, so we don't really trust this randomized
probing to actually reach all nodes, you know,
in time, so they've actually switched to deterministic
probing, so they go around round robbing and
each has a round robinning regime to make
sure that no node is missed and the gossip
itself piggybacks on the probing in order
to not create too many connections.
So actually the gossip itself is not randomized.
At the end of all of this, very importantly
what you get is a failure detection.
In the paper it's called weak membership service.
If you look at this it's a tiny little footnote
on the second page, footnote No. 2, that says
that everything from now on has the adjective
weak added to it but we're not going to do
it in this paper.
So this is what you get at the end of all
of these patches.
I'm going to stop here, because I don't want
to turn this into a papers we hate conference.
[laughter]
I also hear that you know, some people are
actually enhancing SWIM and trying to address
some of these difficulties that they're actually
experiencing in real deployed systems, so
this is what it is.
So I think I'm out of time.
Where is Zeeshan?
Should I stop for questions?
Five minutes for questions, yeah.
>> OK, I have a third part, but you're going
to have to invite me again to hear about it.
That's fine.
Network discovery, great.
ZEESHAN: We'll give you about 10 minutes.
>> You know what I'm going to flash something
about network discovery and leave you to it.
So one thing to realize is that all of this
was in a full network.
What happens in, you know, arbitrary graphs?
Well, clearly in some graphs this process
is going to take a long time.
So if the graph is aligned, it's going to
take linear number of steps for a message
to get from one side to another.
There may even be graphs where it will be
super-linear, so this single barbell graph
is a classic example where there's one node
connected to a dense clique and it may take
a number of rounds until this one node is
picked by its single neighbor.
So the question is what can you do in arbitrary
networks in general to disseminate information
more quickly and I just want to flash a result.
So there's a really -- a really beautiful
paper by the engineers at Akamai from 1999
where they introduced the name-dropper algorithm.
Allegedly it was used in some versions of
Akamai, I don't think it is any more.
But very, very quickly, just to say what it
gives you, lots of demonstrations, so what
it gives you is for any draff, even nondirected
graph.
So if you think about the TCP/IP it doesn't
mean that that other node means my IP address,
so even if the graph is only connect in a
directed way and not completely connected,
the name dropper algorithm will collapse the
entire graph into a clique where everybody
knows everybody in essentially log squared
n rounds.
Even less, it's log n times log the diameter
of the graph, which is of course at most n,
and that result has already been improved
somewhat with a deterministic protocol that
actually brings it down to log n, so really
beautiful and powerful result tells that you
even if your network is not a clique, you
can't talk to everybody at the same time,
you can very quickly build the network through
this gossip protocol.
Again, in essentially logarithmic process,
and within this logarithmic time everybody
will know everybody else.
And so with this, I will actually conclude.
And open for questions.
[applause]
>> What are the properties of the network
that make this applicable or not applicable?
Are there cases where you wouldn't want to
use gossip?
Is it like the latency of the links or the
topology, that kind of thing or the total
number of nodes versus bandwidth?
>> So that's a good question.
Probably people here have more experience.
From a theoretical point of view, all of this
assumed, you know, very basic uniformity.
So if there's really huge skews between latencies,
between nodes, some of them are really close
by, others are, you know, off in the cloud
or away, gossip doesn't seem like a good choice,
or at least straight gossip doesn't seem like
a good choose, because you have to tune these
rounds to the slowest link.
So gossip is fundamentally, you know, this
very uniform process, full knowledge, perfect
knowledge, perfect ability to pick a partner
and you know, to succeed in directing with
it.
I actually don't know of many, many cases
where gossip in practice gives you a very,
very good solution.
This is why I wanted to speak about SWIM today,
because this is one of the very few emerging
cases where people use gossip semi-successfully,
but stim with a lot of problems.
Hope that answers.
>> I just have a quick question.
At the very beginning, you mentioned that
everyone has to know a priori, all of the
other nodes that are in the network.
I was wondering maybe you covered this and
I just missed it, how to step back other nodes
leaving and joining the network on the gossiping
or is this handled outside of the gossip itself
or --
>> Yeah, so the question is, if I can rephrase
it, how can you use gossip to maintain membership
when you need membership to make gossip operate?
And I'm asking myself the same question.
Yes, the only analysis that we have is when
you have full and perfect ability to sample
the network.
What happens if you have partial sample that's
not really uniform?
We don't know.
(Shrugs).
[laughter]
>> With the SWIM protocol on large networks
has it ever been a concern that when you're
trying to reconfirm a failure that you're
actually going to do like some kind of denial
of service against that node and then have
a certain ratio of failures that just kind
of never goes away?
>> I haven't seen such a concern.
I don't think security was at all a consideration
in any of these protocols.
I'll take this opportunity to say a comment
that may or may not stem from what you're
asking, so Byzantine failures or malicious
intrusions, these protocols are not built
to tolerate.
But let me also say fundamentally it seems
to me that when failures occur, there are
essentially two classes of scenarios.
One is when there's single failure or, you
know, very few nodes fail, and fail in kind
of a black or white way.
They crash and that's it.
The other is when there's some transient partition,
half the network is partitioned away from
you maybe permanently, maybe it is black and
white or there is some transient fail ore
where messages are dropped excessively but
not completely, the first type, I think almost
any mechanism that you implement will work
with, you could do just a group of monitors,
you could do all to all, you could do almost
anything and probably also SWIM will converge
very quickly in that setting.
The second type of scenario, that's where
you know, the mechanism really is put to a
test and it's not exactly Byzantine so it's
not exactly what you're asking, but it will
cause removal of nonfaulty nodes and errors
and false failure detections and all of that.
So I think that the effort in tuning a system
and engineering it correctly should be on
the second case and that's what should be
test and optimized for.
Does that address at all?
Yeah, I don't seem to have a good luck with
you --
[laughter]
>> I mean the strict answer is, no, I haven't
seen any.
>> I wasn't really getting into the security
part.
Just the protocol itself.
Where they're being reflooded with reconfirmations.
>> Yeah, so I mean this confirmations in a
nonsteady state could cause removal of a perfectly
OK node, yes.
>> Certain percentage saying, OK, it is alive,
and a certain percentage saying it's OK, and
constantly -- maybe we should talk about this
later.
>> Sure.
>> Last question.
>> I noticed in the example that it was primarily
binary, healthy, not healthy.
Is there the option of accommodating something
more like a nice factor where it's like I've
had trouble against that particular node 30%
of the time because in a degrading state,
something will often go from full up time
to 50% to 15%, so I'm just wondering if the
gossip protocol could accommodate matching
that range.
>> I think gossip spreads that information.
What you do with it, I think yes.
Or how you interpret it.
Whichever way you want.
Right, thank you very much.
Been a great audience.
[applause]