So I've decided to speak about decoding the
sensuality in music, because I work in music
information research, and part of the reason
that we spend so much time thinking about
music is because it moves people, and it affects
us emotionally, and it's part of the reason
why we come and listen to music over and over
again, the same piece of music, being performed
by different people or maybe a same recording
which is the same person playing the same
piece in a particular way.
And part of the reason that I am one of the
lucky people who's able to spend all my time
thinking about music and how it affects us
is because of the explosion digital music
information, and also because of that, a rise
in music information research, sometimes called
music information retrieval.
And just to give you a sense of the figures,
the global -- this is from the IFPI Report
from this year: The global recorded music
revenue is on the order of 15.7 billion USD.
And the share of digital revenues is 50% of
that.
And it's growing at a very fast pace and there's
numerous industries that make this possible
on a very large scale, and I've just listed
some of them there.
None of them are funding me.
[laughter]
So there's no reason why I'm putting up these
companies rather than others, but these are
just representative companies that work in
music, digital music, and you can look at
the numbers and see that there's huge numbers
of people interacting with music through these
digital interfaces.
And for example, shazam, there's been over
30 billion shazams since they started and
it's growing by 20 million per day, so people
are shazamming every day.
Spotify has over 140 million users every month,
so we're talking about large numbers of people
who need to be able to access and care for their digital music collections and
therefore we also need to have computer systems that understand how people interact with their music.
How human brains, humans minds, process music and we need to
also be able to appreciate how humans experience
music.
And in this case, how they engage with their
OK, so with that introduction, I'm going to
move into today's topic, which is to talk
about the experience of music.
And we all know that music moves us, which
is why we listen to music.
They evoke strong emotion, such as goose bumps,
laughter and awe, and part of the reason why
it -- music does this to us and because it
evokes expectations, so we form expectations
and we're listening to music and when these
expectations are fulfilled, we get a rush
of adrenaline, or not adrenaline, endorphins
and we feel a sense of reward for -- having
that expectation fulfilled.
When that expectation is violated, sometimes
it's funny.
And it causes laughter.
And sometimes it's just strange and new and
interesting.
and finally, music causes tension, so that
modulation of expectation, when there's expectation
and that expectation is not fulfilled immediately,
there is sort of a delayed resolution, and
so we feel tension when we listen to music,
or and that tension modulates over time.
And composers and performers make use of this
property of music to create a musical experience
that is moving.
So we'll talk about that, and we talk about
how this is done through sort of one, through
the use of prominence, making events more
prominent than others.
The use of contrast, so when things change.
And the use of time and timing, and tension.
So we'll listen to a bit of music that's a
bit different from what you've been listening
to in the break.
This is a Grieg song, one of the most popular
pieces written by Grieg, and I'm going to
have to step out of this to start the recording
and for those of you who read music, you can
follow along and even if you don't, it's like
a graph so you're able to see when pitches
go up and down, has that started?
Is the sound coming through?
Well, the sound's moving.
Can we try that again?
No, there's no sound coming through.
Thank you.
All right, you know what?
I'll play it for you.
Aha
[cheers and applause]
All right, I'm reading that screen over there.
. Oh, where's my pedal?
Someone took it.
[laughter]
you know, everything was set up just fine
before this session began, and we had to dismantle
it and so when we reconstituted it, some things
didn't get put back.
Ah!
Here it is, OK.
So again, Grieg.
(Norma has goosebumps)
[laughter]
>> OK, so that --
[applause]
That is how it works.
Thank you.
[applause]
So, if there's no sound for my computer, I
would have shown you how a cellist actually
has far more control over a note than I do. Once I play a note that it, I've done my deed and it changed
But for a string-player, they can actually
vibrate and make a sound that actually has
vibrato, and this is an example with vibrato.
And this is with a software called Eva that
we created last year in my lab and Eva takes the sound signal and it uses pre-existing code
that turns the sound signal and finds a fundamental frequency of a sound and then it can automatically extract
the moments when there's vibrato, using an
FDM technique, filter diagonalization method,
which again, was borrowed from another field.
And so here, every single vibrato you can
see the pitch is actually modulating very
quickly and there's a frequency to how that
pitch is actually modulating and with this
kind of modulation, you actually will then
get a very expressive tone in the way that
the music is conveyed.
So thats vibrato
Can you hear it?
Hm. Hm, I do want to play you this, so let's see
if maybe I can I can clip my microphone to my computer.
Oh, well, excuse me.
Is there a reason why my -- it's not allowing
me to have any sound.
>> There we go.
Go ahead and try now.
Can you hear it?
>> OK, for those, did you notice that slide
that Ian just did?
OK.
So he did, or the eeeeewww, dad, de-dum, and
this is a very different way of playing that
same thing ... ...
(Played with more of an upbeat tempo ...)
>> So, um, the top one is how Ian did it and
lower one is how Suzy did it, so we can actually
see exactly what they're doing, in that particular
note to make it very expressive at that moment
in time.
And we can actually quantify these things.
It's one of those things that's highly quantifiable.
You can get a slope, you can get a max pitch,
the top pitch, the bottom pitch and the rate
at which it's descending and so we have ways
of actually describing exactly whats being
done in performance.
So maybe the audio will work now.
Let's try that again ...:
So it's not only in western music that this
is done.
This is an example of Chinese music ...
OK?
So you can hear the vibrato.
So again, if you put that through Eva, that's
what you get, you get to see exactly where
there's vibrato and you can isolate the moments
where there's vibrato and examine and analyze
every single one of them so if you're interested
in doing that to voice or flute or any other
string instruments, you can download the software
and play around with it at this address.
OK, so next we look at contrast.
That is another way in which we derive interest
or generate interest in music.
This is Think of Me.
So let's see ... oh, yes, OK, here we go.
... ...
>> Lyrics: Think of me, think of me fondly,
when we said goodbye, me,
>> That phrase is repeated.
>> Lyrics: Once in a while.
>> There's a bit sadder next ...
>> Then again you long to take your heart
back and be free.
>> And we're back to happy moment.
>> ...
>> Lyrics: Spare a hope for me ...:
>> And the sun comes out.
[laughter]
All right.
OK.
You get the idea.
So there are these different moments where
change occurs, and we take note of these moments,
and -- well, there's the orange bit, the orange
bit, the blue bit, and the bright yellow bit.
Okay, and now we're going to take a look at
how exactly those moments are created.
So this is the -- so part of the reason that
this is -- evokes those kinds of feelings
when we listen to it, is that the composer
here, Andrew Lloyd Weber is playing around
with tonality, so major and minor moods and
where the bright sun comes out that's actually
where he takes a shift and takes everything
out half a step and so that's a very -- it's
a kind of a slightly kitschy way of doing
it
[laughter]
>> You'll see this done quite a lot and you
can try it yourself.
It's very easy to do, take everything up half
a step and it just makes it brighter and seems
like something really great has happened.
[laughter]
>> So this is -- this is -- well, this is
a technique, you could say, and so we can
try to track exactly what composers are doing
when they play around with these kinds of
tonality and tonal patterns, and so over here,
this is a representation of tonality that
takes the original sort of -- this is a well
known way of representing pitches that we
hear on -- that we see on a key -- on the
keyboard ... (Plays the keyboard)
So that's basically of I've just played what
is on a horizontal line.
And on the vertical line is: (Plays)
Yeah?
And so you can wrap it up, as you can see,
the things repeat and you can wrap it up to
get the three dimensional structure like this,
a helical model this is called a spiral array.
This is what my Ph.D. thesis was on and you
can represent things inside that spiral array
that represent tonal elements and this is
how the spiral array works.
Video: Calculates what's the closest chord
and the closest key as music is unfolding
so this is Bach's Prelude in C major and I'm
going to play the first chord.
So I've played 3 pitches, the C, E, and G
and you see the silver blocks -- you know,
I'm pausing that here, because I have a keyboard
and I have the software.
I will do that for you.
[laughter]
[applause]
AUDIENCE: Ooh!
[laughter]
>> OK.
OK. All right. So ... (Plays)
That's the chord of C in the
key of C.
Chord of D minor in the K of C.
G chord in the key of C.
C cord in the key
of C.
A minor chord in the key of C.
D major.
And so on.
OK?
So this is able to trace exactly what's being
done, and if -- so that was the Prelude, the
C-major prelude from the well tempered clavier
from Bach.
Now I'm going to do a parody of this by PDQ
bach and this is from the short-tempered
clavier, right?
basically it has those chords again.
F, ... .. (playing)
That's not supposed to
be there.
OK, right. So --
[applause]
Thank you. You can see
when PDQ Bach is actually composing like JS
Bach, he's doing things that are sort of in
the same key and in the right moment and
when he does things unexpected that veer way out, it makes these
big arcs outside of that close-knit circle,
that trajectory so we're able to see exactly
when unexpected things happen, and you can
also see things like this is again from PDQ
Bach from the same short-tempered clavier.
This is based on Beethoven's 5th.
So we know how that motif goes, and later
on he's going to when the motif comes back
he's going to play it wrong and what he does
is -- ... (Plays)
It's supposed to go ... right?
He's going to go (plays.)
All right, so and when he does that it's going
to shoot way out there, way up there where
it's not supposed to be so I'm going to get
into that and you will see how that happens.
(Plays)
So you see that yellow line goes all the way
up because it's not in the right key, it's
gone to the wrong region so we're able to
track when things are unexpected and when
things are unexpected is really when the interesting
parts of the music takes place.
When people get goosebumps, that's because
there's a change that's kind of -- well, sometimes
expected but sometimes unexpected but it's
not normally there, and so it gives you pleasure
when that happens.
So changes are very important in music.
PDQ Bach, I didn't come up with the idea.
I was actually inspired by a book by David
Huron called sweet anticipation.
So he writes about how expectations are formed and how music gives us pleasure
This is the score of what the PDQ Bach looks
like.
So by having these surprising moments, we
get humorous moments in music and that creates
laughter.
So this is where the PDQ Bach was doing funny
things in the Preludes in C.
This is another view of the Prelude in C, where it veers down at the end where its doing something unexpected.
This is that Beethoven 5th parody, and this
is where it goes instead of going to E flat
it goes to E natural, which is not in the
right key and that's another example from
PDQ Bach.
OK, so if you're interested in getting your
own version of the software, and playing around
with it you can download it.
It's on the App Store.
At the moment it only works on a Mac desktop
or laptop, so if you have one, do feel free
to check it out.
OK.
The theory behind it is -- can be found in
chapters in this book, that came out in 2014,
on the spiral array model and all the applications.
OK.
Ah!
So this is just to bring it -- draw it back
to the example at the beginning that I played
for you.
That is an example which is normally if it's
played by strings with all the shimmery sounds
and all of the vibratos, it's a very moving
piece.
It's one of the most moving pieces of music,
like many pieces that Grieg has written, it
has a very pretty melody and lots of people
listen to it because it has not just the melody,
but lots of changes that gives these good
feelings of expectations being violated or
fulfilled.
And the kinds of chords that it goes through
are here.
I've just sort of outlined them.
This is E major E minor and there's A minor
and G major and G major again, C major, E minor
it could be major or minor here, major and
minor and E major
And in the interest of time I'm not going
to play you this video or to stop out of this
to go into the MuSA.RT app, I could do that
but you know how MuSA.RT works now and you
know how it's going to move around in that
place and show you the chords that are happening
in the piece at those times.
OK, so when we think about -- if we go back
to Think of Me example.
This is where a change is taking place. So you can imagine in how one region
In the orange bits it's staying in one region
of the Spiral Array Space and in the blue
bits it's going to go to another region that's
going to go to relative minor and then it's
going to come back to the orange bit and everything
is going to shift up it's a huge change to
the half step up where the sun comes up.
So if you actually try to measure in the space
how much distance is traversed whenever these
-- whenever these movements occur, so how
much distance is traversed when we go from
one section or one segment of the piece to
another, you can actually see the amount of
change that occurs, and the greatest change
occurs when the orange bit goes to the yellow
bit, so where the sun comes out.
And this is -- you get to see this pattern
no matter what size window you use, this is
one where 248th notes window, there's 16 so
the window gets smaller, but you still see
that gigantic peak when that big change occurs.
OK, so time.
Time is important.
So we notice these moments of contrast and
change, but we're also interested in how we
can highlight these changes using time, and
so we take a look at -- I'm going to play
you a bit, and I'm going to stop or rather
pause where maybe I shouldn't pause, and just
a little bit too long, just to keep you on
your toes, and you're going to see how the
use of time actually creates these kinds of
anticipations and moments of suspense.
So this is an excerpt from a trio by Paul
Schoenfield. This is the second movement of his trio and it has a beginning bit by
piano ... (plays)
OK, I've waited too long.
I I've lost it.
[laughter]
OK, so these moments, I can hold it very long.
I can hold it very long, because you know
something else is coming and you want resolution
to that something else.
So let me do that again and I'll actually
resolve it.
(Plays)
OK, so much better, yeah?
OK, so because the expectation was set up
and it had to resolve, and because that expectation
was set up, you knew something was coming
and you were waiting for it and because you
were waiting for it, I knew I could take more
time, right?
And when I take more time, there is great
uncertainty -- well, you know what's coming,
so there's no uncertainty about that.
But the uncertainty comes in when that's going
to take place, so that's what I'm playing
with when I take time.
And we have the same thing here.
There's a moment in the piece, the Grieg piece
beings this is the middle of the piece, and
I will stick the microphone here and have
you hear it.
This is sung by a soprano, and at the moment
where she's taking more time than necessary,
you will see that in the orange bit.
(Elaine is snapping her fingers in time.)
All right, anyone tried to beat to this?
[laughter]
>> Well if you did try to beat to it, you'll
see that the beats are not the same length.
They actually vary quite a bit and this is
where we're going to talk about time and when
we talk about time, we're going to look at
those lengths of the beats and how they get
modulated, stretched or compressed.
So as to modulate your speculations.
And we're going to talk first about tipping
points.
We all know about physical tipping points,
right, when something's sort of at an edge
and the center of gravity is at the point
where it's balancing on and if you just tip
it a little bit it's going to just topple
over.
So the same thing happens in music.
Here's an example of tipping points.
This is an -- a quick example of Kreisler
playing his own piece and since I'm not a
violinist I'm not going to be able to play
this for you, but I'll just play the recording.
(Violin playing, and Elaine is snapping and
tapping with the time.)
>> OK, so this is how much he's changing the
lengths of the beats.
And this is not at all what is written.
What is written would have been a flat line
if it was played exactly how it's written
but instead it's played more like this, yeah?
So there's lots of tipping points.
He's playing around it this sense of going
up and down and sort of modulating our expectations,
playing around with it.
This is another example, it's going to end
up looking kind of like this and so I'm not
going to play from that recording but I'll
play from the analyzed data here.
(Piano playing, and Elaine is snapping fingers
with time)
OK?
So she took a lot of time before that last
bit comes back.
OK.
So we can do that again for the bit that I
had played you by Grieg, so what you'd need
to do is you need to have software like sonic
visualizer which you can annotate beats on
and once you can annotate beats you can extract
the data and plot it and analyze it so this
is what it looks like what she's saying.
This is Edith Oldrup and this is a visualization
of what she's saying with the data.
(Singing)
OK?
So this is exactly what she is singing and
how she's modulating the time and when the
time is modulated, what it may evoke in the
listener are feelings of tension, because
now we're playing around with expectation.
And last year, in a paper we proposed a model
for tonal tension, so as you can see when
things were unexpected in that Spiral Array
Space when PDQ Bach was playing around with
the expectations, things were going far, far
away and when things go far away, it's actually
creating a big space, so if we look at the
diameter of the points that are traced out
inside that space, we have a sense of just
how dissonant or unexpected the music is.
So the cloud diameter is a measure of one
aspect of tonal tension, which is that dissonance.
We can also look at Claude momentum, how much
is shifting around in that space, and that
momentum within that space, if that's just
too high, that can also cause feelings of
tension, and tensile strain is when the key,
the tonal center, the center of gravity is
in the region and you stray very far away
from it.
That also causes feelings of tension.
So in this here we have the Tristan chord
which is supposed to be a very tense chord
and you can see the three measures on the score for this chord, which goes like this ...
(Plays)
OK, so this is supposedly where the tension
is highest.
(Plays)
Yeah, and it resolves.
Yeah?
So we can then go back and do the same thing
to where people chose to take time, and see
how that correlates with the different tension
measures here for the diameter it's the tipping
points are happening just before where the
diameter comes to a low, and over here, if
we look at the cloud momentum, the tipping
points are where there's a lot of movement
and if we look at here, the tensile strain,
the tipping points occur where, again, there's
a lot of strain.
It's veering quite far away from where the
center is, and so a lot more time is taken
for you to actually experience that.
OK.
So now that we have a way of quantifying tension,
an application of this is in music generation,
so music generation has become very popular
recently because Google has this Magenta project
and companies such as Duke Deck are interested
in generating music that are copyright free
that you can put on your home videos.
There's also interest in music that's generated
automatically that fit different scenarios
in computer games, so it actually molds itself
according to how the game is being played.
And so part of the problem of music that is
generated by computers is that it often lacks
structure.
Not only does it lack structure, it doesn't
know how to transition from one section to
another.
And so in an effort to try to generate music
or find a way of creating music that has some
form of structure, narrative structure, we
use the tension model to constrain the movements
within tonal space for music that's generated.
We also use an existing program by David Meredith,
SIATECCompres and COSIATEC. To find repeated patterns inside an existing piece of music.
It uses existing music as a template and copies
over all of its rhythms and all of its repeated
patterns and so here is an example of repeated
patterns found in the PDQ Bach
piece so if we start with the patterns that
are found and following the rhythms of the
PDQ Bach piece, you end up getting a piece
that looks like this.
If you just randomly populate it with notes
that just fit the repeated patterns and the
rhythmic structure, and it doesn't sound very
good.
[laughter]
(Plays discordant music.)
OK, not only does it sound not good, it's
unplayable.
OK, so after you constrain it to fit the tension
profile learned from the PDQ Bach piece, you
very quickly get something that's more coherent
... (plays) and to iterate it once more, and
you go, let's go a bit closer to that, and
hm.
>> OK, so you do want to stop around there,
because if you keep going, you'd end up with
the same piece again and it's not very useful.
So --
[laughter]
Right, because there's too many constraints
and if we try to minimize distance to the
-- what you found from the original piece,
you might end up with something too close
to the original piece.
So this was done to many other pieces.
Amongst them, this is March in D by JS Bach.
(Plays)
OK, but that's the original piece.
Untouched.
And now I'll play you what MorpheuS, the program,
generated.
(Elaine plays) on keyboard.)
OK.
[applause]
So if you're interested in seeing more of
MorpheuS pieces, you can go online.
MorpheuS has a website and here are some examples
of other music generation systems.
And finally, just to recap: We've looked at
how prominence is modulated in music performance,
how composers create contrast.
How performers use time to exaggerate these
contrasts or shape your expectations, and
finally, how tension can be used in music
generation.
And if you're interested in finding out more
about these projects and others, feel free
to browse some of our websites and blogs.
Thank you.
[applause]