So my name is Heather Miller, I'm a professor
at northeastern University, I'm the director
at the Scala center at EPFL so I have one foot in
academia and one foot in industry land.
And, actually, this talk comes out of a course
that I gave last fall at northeastern University.
It was a grad course called programming models
for distributed computing.
And actually, there's even a book that kind
of came out of it that's not totally finished
yet.
But all the students in the course wrote this
book with me, and I have to edit it.
It needs some work.
But it's got a lot of really cool information,
and this is actually -- like this talk is
just about one week of course material.
So one and a half, maybe two weeks of course
material, so there's a lot of interesting
information and a lot of stuff to be found
at this book.
There's a link on the slide.
I'll put links up on the Internet if you look
around afterwards.
But anyway, so that's an aside.
But sort of one of the things that kind of
I really like about not just, you know, research
in general, but about kind of looking back
at sort of the history of things and how things
came to be how they are now is that research,
it's really animated.
It doesn't really look like that, necessarily.
Perhaps from the outside, it looks more like
this.
[Laughter]
You have -- you know, I think people sometimes
look at academic research kind of pessimistically
where research papers are crusty-looking PDFs
with big files that are a pain in the neck
to download and read.
They have way too much pages, too much convoluted
motivational statements that lack any sort
of actual real-world context, and they solve
problems that nobody cares about.
And, you know, this is some guy that's in
a room that has never seen daylight before,
and I think that's what a lot of people think
research is about.
But I think it's a little bit more dynamic.
They have these multiyear evolving and animated
debates where researchers arn the world are
solving similar problems.
And these different ideas and solutions and
things, they're super animated.
If you look at these things over a long period
of time.
And, you really, they're evolving via PDFs,
which people think are ultimately unsexy.
So by the end of this talk, I hope that I
will have communicated to you that something
is going on in research land are not, like,
crusty piles of PDFs sitting around somewhere
describing esoteric things that never went
anywhere.
And instead, we go to, like, a dynamic view
of arguments and designs and languages and,
you know, things just evolving over decades
with many design decisions from some of these
so-called esoteric languages actually becoming
somehow mainstream and then finding their
way into sexier things that you guys use more
often.
So.
Okay.
This is about distributed programming languages,
so can anybody name some distributed programming
languages?
Okay.
You guys know Chris then.
[Laughter]
So Chris is going to be so happy that you
guys said last was a distributed programming
lank.
Clearly, that means it's more widely used.
So we have Erlang.
What else?
There has to be a couple more.
I've never heard of that one.
What is it?
Shapeel.
Cool.
I'm going to look that one up.
Give me one more.
Linda.
Yeah.
Cool.
There's, like, a zillion.
Some you've heard of.
Mirage, Orca, I'm sure you haven't heard of
that one.
But there's a lot.
I can't talk about about every single one
of them.
But I'm going to go way too fast through at
least seven of them, and you're going to hate
me for it.
[Laughter]
So I can't get into a ton of detail, but,
you know, we can just kind of touch on the
big ideas.
So the first paper I'm going to delve into
is one by Barbara in 1988.
It's about a programming language called Argus.
And if you're not familiar with Barbara, you
really should be because she won the touring
award in 2008.
She laid the ground work for a lot of things
in object-oriented programming.
She was known for this language called Clu,
I guess is what some people call it that they
worked on in the mid-'70s, and it introduced
the use of classes with constructors and methods.
It also introduced a little thing called abstract
data types.
I don't know if you ever heard of these things.It
rarities, type safe parameterized types, and
an important definition of subtyping and object-oriented
programming that people commonly use called
the substitution principle.
So she's done a lot of things, and you should
know who she is.
So while she's kind of like a McJagger or
something in the land of object-oriented programming,
maybe you don't know that she made this weird,
wonky language in the '80s called Argus for
distributed programming.
And actually, it was super influential, and
you're going to be, like, what?
Really?
So back in the day, she had this observation,
and I'm just going to read it to you.
Distribution gives rise to some problems that
do not exist in a centralized system or that,
you know, exist in a less complex form in
a centralized system.
For example, a centralized system is either
running, or it's crashed.
But a distributed system may be partly running
and partly crashed.
Okay.
Cool.
So boast the nodes and network may fail.
The network may lose or delay the delivery
of messages or messages may just come out
of order.
Yet, somehow, programs should remain running,
and she had this idea in the '80s.
And one thing that she thought was super important
was that there -- is that data should remain
consistent when these situations happen.
So this is a really big deal.
She was, like, look, if everything crashes
or a bunch of things crash, we shouldn't,
you know, have screwed up bank accounts because
of it.
So we need strong consistency, and she introduced
this idea in the -- you know, in the context
of a programming language, which it hadn't
really been thought of in this context before.
So this paper actually runs through an example
in banking, and she notes a couple of things.
She notes two things.
So on the one hand, concurrent activities
made to interfere with one another, that's
a problem.
And on the other hand, there might be some
kind of failure that occurs.
And these things, we don't really do anything
about programming languages that we use now;
right?
So this object-oriented thing called clu,
other things.
So in the face of these two things, Argus
must provide some kind of strong consistency,
is what she says.
And I'm, you know, I think it's great to kind
of show these people's words rather than to
make up my own myself.
So I would like to just quote her here.
So she introduces Argus to support programs
like a banking system to capture, you know,
always used to be in this object-oriented
context, so she introduces two concepts to
have these things.
One hand, you have a guardian, which is a
special problem that runs procedures and response
to promote requests.
And then introduces another thing in the context
of this language that should make consistency
happen, which are atomic transactions.
So computations should always be organized
as atomic transactions.
And these are sort of the two biggish ideas.
And these guardian things fall into this world
of object-oriented programming; right?
So guardians, like I said, it's like an object.
A special kind of abe extract object whose
purpose is to encapsulate a resource or resources.
Importantly, the state of the resources maintained
in the objects stored in the guardian, so
these things are isolated.
The stuff inside a guardian is not accessible
outside of a guardian.
And the only way that people could actually
manipulate anything inside of one of these
special objects is via a handlers, another
guardian has to call some kind of handle that
affects something inside of a guardian.
Okay?
So the key thing to hold onto here is that
even though what's inside of a guardian is
a dynamic collection of data objects, they're
not accessible directly by anybody.
So that's a guardian.
And this is the very, very beautiful picture
that was in the paper trying to draw a picture
of all of the things that could happen inside
of a guardian.
It's not exactly the best picture.
But the idea here is that you have all kinds
of things.
You've got objects, and you have processes,
and all kinds of stuff going on inside of
this guardian.
And then you have these handlers.
In this case, one is called in cue and one
is called check.
It doesn't really matter.
But this is how you affect the stuff going
on inside of it.
So, yeah, just to summarize guardian and encapsulate
state, it contains a dynamic collection of
objects.
They're like an abstraction over a node or
they're like a microservice or something.
Interestingly, they can be moved and the guardian
can create other guardians dynamically.
So these are kind of what a guardian looks
like, what's inside of one, and kind of what
they can do.
And I mentioned there are these handlers that
-- oh, yep.
A guardian permits its resources to be accessed
by means of these special procedures called
handlers; right?
As I mentioned the way to affect stuff going
on inside of it.
Yep.
And also, handler calls can be location independent,
so you can be on some other node somewhere
and call a handler that affects a guardian
somewhere else; right?
Mamakes some kind of sense.
Cool.
So that's kind of like the high-level picture.
You don't have to actually try to read this
because you definitely can't.
This is just a screenshot from the paper of
what the code kind of looks like.
So this is -- this right here is supposed
to be an entire banking application for one
bank.
So this is, like, one branch of a bank.
And all that really matters here are the colors.
So here you have kind of where this guardian
for a branch starts and where it ends.
So it's like an object again.
It has a bunch of stuff inside of it.
The stuff that's inside of it, so there are
handlers that other guardians can call to
affect all kinds of state that's inside of
it.
And the other things are, like, types and
sort of local data structures inside of it.
So bank account numbers and other things like
a table of banks and bank account numbers.
Okay.
But fine.
The whole is motivation behind this programming
language was, well, partial failure should
somehow be addressed in Argus, so how can
it be addressed by guardians?
So basically, this goes back to this atomic
actions point, so the idea is that, you know,
I'll just go here.
So there are these atomic actions that Argus
makes possible, so all of these calls to handlers
and things, they should be atomic.
And by that, they, you know, they're not separate,
they're one, big action, and if you run a
group of them, they always have to be executed
as if they were run sequentially, and then
they have to be total.
Completes entirely, or it fails entirely,
and it has no visible effect.
So that's the idea.
So serialize ability solves concurrency problem
and totality solves the failure problem and
these things are invisible, they're atomic.
And this is all achieved by your favorite
thing on the planet, which is definitely locking
in synchronization.
I know everybody in this room really likes
this.
Everything is all read, write locks.
And there's this cool way of making a hierarchy
of these things, so things can be organized
in terms of, like, two-phase commits.
It doesn't really matter.
And then if you're part way trying to do something,
and then part of your thing fails or something,
there's a way to recover to roll back to,
you know, to stop this commit from starting
or this -- whatever to stop everything from
being committed.
And this is done via versioning.
And then, of course, communication between
remote guardians is done by RPC.
So it's all synchronized and locked and everything,
and it's, you know, definitely not super performent
but strong consistency, that's cool.
And another thing you might not know about
Argus is promises came from Argus.
I'm not going to go into that.
That's another week and a half of material.
But the idea of promise pipe lining because
you realize RPC can be really slow if it's
all synchronous, hey, we can make it asynchronous
with promises, and they're strongly typed,
and that's really great.
So there's another paper written by Barbara
called promises linguistic support for asynchronous
procedure calls in distributed systems.
I encourage you to have a look at that.
But just note, hey, this is where promises
came from.
Okay.
One short note about how Argus was implemented.
It was just calling random stuff in, like,
a special research kernel.
It was completely coupled with the kernel.
So everything.
Networking, storage, all of that stuff, it,
you know, required special research implementation
of Unix that they were using and, yeah.
I mean, she didn't make any sort of modifications
to this research thing that I think somebody
else is working on, but still.
It was completely coupled to this one version
of Unix.
All right.
That's all I'm going to say about Argus.
Just try to remember all of that.
Okay?
So the next thing I'm going to talk about
is emerald.
Emerald's another programming language from
the '80s.
I'm going to zoom in right here because I'm
pretty sure that this is not a quote from
Andrew Black and all of those people.
This is definitely a compote from Chris Meiklejohn in 2017, even though it says it's from
Emerald in 1987, they say while distributed
systems are now commonplace in 1987, obviously,
they were.
The programming of distributed applications
is still somewhat of a black art.
Definitely not a black art anymore; right?
We believe that the complexity of distributed
applications is heightened by the lack of
programming language support for distribution.
I swear Chris said that, like, two days ago;
right?
I don't know if he's copying it out of the
paper or what.
Anyway, these are some of the guys that wrote
the paper.
This is back when they put people's pictures
in the paper.
Isn't this cool?
I know a few of them, and they're much older
now, but I like that they have these pictures,
you know?
It's really cool.
Okay.
That's a silly point.
Anyway, the goal of Emerald was language support
for distribution.
Yay.
So this actually all started in other languages.
Actually, a few other languages.
One called Eden, which was in itself and another
language called concurrent Euclid.
And basically, they took concurrent Euclid
and they were, like, let's take RPC to this
thing and make it distributed. That'd would be so cool.
But as a result of doing that, they ended
up with two different versions of objects.
And they thought that was ugly, you know?
So on the one hand, you had these mobile objects
implemented in Eden, but they were extremely
expensive to use and nobody used them.
Instead, developers snuck around and then
reused concurrent Euclid objects, and then
they would communicate through shared memory
instead of RPC.
Like they were supposed to.
Obviously, that's bad.
I mean, assuming this was all on the same
note, by the way.
They're doing shared memory.
And then if it's -- you're trying to talk
to somebody else in another node, then you're
in trouble.
In any case, they're, like, let's try to fix
these things.
Let's try to unify this object system because
it's pretty bad and also, you know, not very
performent, so let's make Emerald to address
these issues.
So I'm going to read two more quotes to you
because I'm sure you love it.
We believe that distributed applications is
heightened for programming support for distribution.
That was Chris.
The rest is Andrew Black and his friends.,
for example, most distributed applications
are implemented by calling operating system
communications primitives, such as send and
receive and the programmer's responsible for
the target explicitly packaging parameters
and so on.
That really sucks liked it you're in a programming
language, and I just have to, like, go down
to the operating system and then package everything
up, make packets myself, send stuff around,
that's horrible.
So emerald, we want to go beyond simple sin
tactic support, we want to address some of
the fundamental semantic problems of distribution.
So note this fundamental problem of distribution,
what are they?
Obviously, it's objects.
Because programming language designers are,
like, if it's an ugly objects system, this
is bad.
This is the most important thing to distribution.
So basically, they wanted a single object
model that is performent's and used for both
programming in the small and the large can
be used for local objects as well as remote
ones.
That was a very important concern for them.
They thought abstract types were important.
I'll talk about that in a second.
That turns out to be much more important.
And then this specific note of object location
and moveability, so you should be able to
move your objects around.
So the three things that they offer with this
programming language, you know, these objects
that I mentioned before.
Emeraldons objects, which offers euphemism
sin tact taxic.
Can communicate between each other, via message
passing, and they're mobile; right?
They can be moved around the network.
They have a few things, identity, they have
some way of operations, some way of processing
these things but more importantly, they have
these other strange attributes.
One is location and the other one is that
an object can be immutable.
That's interesting.
So, you know, actually, turns out that immutability
was kind of like a marker, not really immutable.
But whatever.
Details.
And location.
So you should be able to, like, location should
be part of your object.
Okay.
That's interesting.
And then, yeah.
So it doesn't really -- this is maybe a less
important detail is that multiple objects
actually exist inside of this thing and are
selected by the compiler to make things more
efficient, so you don't have that funny thing
where programmers are using the wrong kind
of object for the situation.
They're trying to be in.
So the compiler selects the right kind of
object for you.
But you see all kind of one object; right?
But what's more important to me or what I
think is a bigger deal are abstract types.
So the idea that abstract types are statically
typed, but they argue that.
Okay.
Well, static typing has advantages, you know,
and the big deal here at this time in 1987
was that it enables better error notification
and by better, them better than small talk.
So that was the motivation, which I think
is cute and great.
But turns out that abstract types were more
important than design contribution because
they were designed to be used in so-called
open systems.
They use the word open systems where objects
may be added to a writing system, so you need
some kind of interface, and then you can swap
in a different implementation for that interface.
So they wanted abstract types to be able to,
like, these interfaces to be defined in them
to be able to allow old code to invoke new
objects, basically.
That was the idea.
Which that's super cool; right?
This is an awesome thing.
The next thing is so-called distribution support,
and this is super messy.
What's under this, like, subsection here.
It's a ton of things.
But to try to keep it short, you know, this
is about concurrency having multiple nodes,
having object location baked into these objects,
you know, sort of encapsulating all of this
stuff, and then to let people actually manually
move objects around if they feel like they
should.
And whatever, that's -- it's actually extremely
involved how this works.
And then they had to introduce a few interesting
things called, like, call by move semantics
for, you know, arguments that are on different
machines or something.
This gets super messy.
In any case, this is a support for distribution.
Okay?
All of these things to try to make these mobile
objects work.
And I'm just going to say, again, how is Emerald
implemented?
So let's try to remember where each of these
languages implemented point.
So it was implemented in a very pain-staking
way.
The compiler, again, was very closely coupled
to the kernel, it actually defined an interface
with the kernel so that operations could be
either performed by the kernel, the compiler,
or even compiler-generated code, like, it's
super baked into it.
And even more interestingly, emerald was the
only thing that could run on that kernel.
Nothing else allowed.
So this was super tightly -- must have taken
a zillion years to try to make this thing
work.
Okay.
We all know Erlang, I'm going to spend around
30 seconds actually talking about it since
it's not such a foreign concept to most people
here.
I say Erlang came out in the 1990, its first
public release was 2000.
The paper was written in 1990
This one that you see here was 2010 by Joe
Erlang. I'm sorry, Joe Armstrong in the CACM.
He could be Joe Erlang.
That's a pretty cool name.
But I think we know most of these things;
right?
So I'm just going to run through a quick summary.
So it's a fundamental programming language.
It's made up of lightweight processes, which
is the main thing that Erlang offers.
So the idea is that, like, how you should
write Erlang programs is that processes are
typically created for a short period of time.
They live long enough to do one, simple thing,
to handle one, simple request, and then they
can just go away, you don't have to worry
or care about these things.
So that allows there to be a zillion processes
to be happening at the same time.
Of course, everything communicates via messaging
processing.
Things are immutable, signs can't be changed
and the most exciting thing to me is this
very cool, dynamic VM.
So you have hot swapping is allowed, which
is really neat.
The idea is then you can upgrade applications
while they're running without stopping them.
Super cool.
And you can't really Tauber language without
mentioning OTP, which is a bunch of I would
say just libraries that are on top of Erlang
that define all kinds of things.
One thing that use a lot are these supervisors,
so you can have processes watching over processes
and handling their failures.
Oh, another thing I didn't mention in the
blue part or the dark part of the slide is
also that you have this ability to, like,
do linking.
So one process can be notified if another
process fails or disappears or something;
right?
So that's also very important.
Because then you can, you know, you know of
somebody died or something was failed.
Again, we all kind of know Erlang a little
bit, so I'm not going to say anything more.
So just remember Erlang for a second.
And it's a virtual machine, basically.
Compiled that for Windows and I'm sorry Unix
and Windows runs most places without issue.
Super concurrency focused VM.
It's, I guess, the nicest way to describe
it as a process VM, so there's no actual connection
to the OS processes running underneath.
Instead, the VM manages all of that itself.
And it can manage millions of processes, so
you can -- yeah, you can have really a million
processes sitting on top of just on S process.
And have one thread per core, basically.
And, of course, it has this really cool garbage
collector that independently collects all
process, since all of these are independent,
they can't share memory and whatnot, so they
have their own heaps.
That's neat and, of course, this hot code
reloading thing.
So this is Erlang; right?
Just footnote.
Linda.
Has anybody heard of Linda?
I think somebody mentioned Linda here?
You've heard of tupal spaces.
They're really out of this world spacey, I
have no idea.
Weird things.
Okay?
So I'm going to just kind of run through the
idea of what what these spaces are, but the
main point to remember here is that tupal
spaces were introduced as an alternative to
message passing.
So the argument is, well, message passing
is no good.
It's a coordination model that arises directly
from the architecture of networks.
That's horrible, you know?
We don't want that.
Yet, the use of distributed data structures
in a logically-shared memory is natural.
It's a naturally-understood way to approach
paralleled programming; right?
So, guys, the principle argument here is that
distributed shared memory is inefficient.
So if that's really all you have to say about
it, I have an idea.
We can -- whoops.
We can come up with a scalable and efficient
implementation of shared memory.
And, you know, we shouldn't be building all
of our applications around message passing
because it's developed to some consequence
of the fact that this complaint that, you
know, distributed shared memory is inefficient.
Like, so why do we have to -- what?
Now we have to change how we think about everything
and how we approach all problems just because
of this one thing?
Let's fix that; right?
Okay.
I still think it's a little crazy but whatever.
So Linda comes in, and they're, like, look,
we're going to make this efficient.
Okay?
We're going to solve this problem.
So they introduce the tuple spaces, which
is virtual associative and logically-shared
memory.
It's like when you take things out of a cloud,
basically.
You don't know how it works.
[Laughter]
So surprisingly, tuple spaces contain tuple
spaces, which is an order answer of data.
And, I mean, this is what they look like.
I took this from the paper.
This is a Tuple, so you put data into a little
thing with commas between data.
You just insert that into your Tuple space.
Either serially or in parallel.
So you have to create these things, this data,
and then insert it into this Tuple space.
So use this outmethod so it creates data and
inserts it one by one, like, you know, it
serially goes through the arguments here,
like, vaults them and then inserts the whole
thing into the Tuple space and the parallel
way, it's a little bit different, so the idea
is that all arguments to evaluate in parallel
in separate processes while the original process
that started this continues immediately.
So it's kind of a -- and then the thing goes
into the Tuple space.
So that's the idea.
You have, like, a sequential and parallel
way of doing it.
So there's no addresses.
If you want to pull something out of the this
associative memory, you know, the idea is
that you retrieve things on the basis of the
combination of their field values.
So if I want to get something out of a Tuple
space, I have these weird patterns, and I
can either read things via these patterns,
or I can find a Tuple via a pattern, or I
can read it.
That's the idea.
So this example here, this little RD thing,
that's the way to just read a Tuple.
This is how you say, well, this, you know,
I want, for example, a Tuple ABCD.
Wait, ABCDE.
Whatever.
And, you know, I'm looking for A, basically.
So I can pull it out by A. Does that make
some kind of sense?
It's a little weird.
So to read a five hive element Abcde, you
can write this ARDA and then the question
marks for the other parameters that you want
to match against and, you know, you'll get
something back, basically.
And interestingly, you know, if there are
multiple things that match, you just get an
arbitrary one, or it blocks some weights until
something matches that it can give you.
Surely, that's not a problem.
[Laughter]
And therefore, Tuple spaces are good, obviously.
And this is the documentation for why Tuple
spaces are better.
Because you have loose coupling amongst loose
processes and message passing, on the other
hand, you actually have to know what, you
know, other actors or whatever things are
in a system, you have to actually address
a message to them in a point to point system.
And this, you don't have to know anything
about your network, you don't have to know
about other people in your system, you just
put your stuff into this big cloudy thing
called a tuple spaces, and you get stuff out,
and you hope it's the thing that you wanted.
So that's good.
It's considered to be a win.
Producers of Tuples also don't have to coexist
at the same time.
Like, you don't have to have two actors live
at the same moment, so you have a process
putting into a Tuple space and three years
later someone taking it out.
So Tuples remain in this space until they're
removed.
Also considered to be a good thing.
So Linda was actually implemented as a language
intention.
So there's two variants of it.
Linda and FORTRAN Linda.
And the thing to note here is that it was
written in some kind of base language, in
this case either C or FORTRAN.
Sorry, it was a compiler of C or foretrain.
And it will automatically generate required
auxillary routines and incorporate different
optimized kernel libraries, you know, for
that platform and that target and whatever
to support the Linda operations that run.
So that's how it was put together.
Okay.
I'm going to -- this is another, like, two-second
one.
So Scala is a library, and that's a big deal.
So back in 2005 or '06, we were, like, hey,
Erlang is a cool thing but the JVM, it would
be cool if we had this lightweight processes
on the JVM, that would be cool.
But these JVM threads, what do we do?
So let's do some of that process management
like Erlang does but as a library with a thread
pool.
We can map it all down JVM threads.
And it turns out it worked.
You can have these lightweight... I wouldn't call them threads, processes, whatever, ala Erlang. Actually implemented on top of a fork-join pool,
and this is actually a really huge deal.
Had a big impact.
Akka later came out of this project called Scala
actors and then it was started by this guy
here called Phillip.
Anyway, so it was a big deal and a lot of
people jumped on using the actor model and
the JVM due to this actually working.
And it was all implemented on a Scala library
ran on a JVM and the same thing is true today.
And you have Martin doing a happy dance because
he's, like, yeah, look at that.
If you go back to this little example here,
you can't really see it very well.
But there's this React thing, which is the
message handler.
You know, that's really neat because it looks
like it's, like, a key word in the language.
It looks like it's built into the language,
but it's just library.
So my language is awesome because it can support
that stuff and also, it can emulate this thing
that required an entire VM; right?
So that's, you know, the Scala.
Cloud Haskell appeared a few years later and
was, like, hey, you know what?
I think there are a lot of different parallel
programming paradigms in practice.
And the difference is really the cost model.
I'm not a believer of the one-size-fits-all
story about parallelism.
I think we can't escape the idea that we will
need to write parallel applications using
different paradigms, and I would like to build
a language or language ecosystem where you
can use lots of different parallels in the
same application where you can have bits of
data parallelism and bits of message passing
all in the same application.
So it's, like, hey, Haskell, kind of, like,
it would be cool if we had some of these Erlang
message passe actor things.
That would be really great.
So Simon not stopping there believes, look,
we can do much better than just having these
actor things.
You guys don't have types.
We can fix that.
And everything is immutable also.
[Laughter]
And our functions are potent.
Obviously better and the reason why it's better
is if something crashes, you can run it somewhere
else, you can reconstruct things.
Clearly better.
And you can separate pure and effectful code.
Also better.
So I think we can improve on this situation
as sort of the basic idea.
So you have processes in Haskell that are
like actors.
They're blessed with this ability to send
and receive messages, they're all lightweight
and don't require much overhead.
Messages as well, which are basically the
way that this works is the actual -- well,
so these things all have to be serialized,
which is complicated.
Don't worry about that.
But the point is that basically one of these
processes can receive another message, which
doesn't have a explicit type associated with
it.
And then it uses type inferences to figure
out what it is.
There are also exist channels, which is a
data structure to send a message of exactly
one type to exactly one node.
So whereas every single node can simply receive
messages of any type automatically and figure
out what is supposed to be, be it the methods
or whatever you're doing with it or functions
that you're using with it, nodes must be given
an explicit send port structure that allows
them to send a message of one type to a channel.
So you have basically, like, kind of any message
that you want, and then, like, these type
channels.
And then they have special closures.
So these are super restrictive closures that
only allow certain things to be in the environment,
and you have to say how everything is serialized
to send it.
So this is what cloud Haskell provides in
the shortest possible description.
And it's implemented as a library.
As a domain-specific language with a little
bit of template Haskell mixed in there.
And it looks a lot like Erlang.
Just to show you a little bit of code.
This is Haskell on the top and Erlang on the
bottom.
Same ping-pong language.
And I have two more things.
I showed you I'm already getting close to
run out of time.
So the next thing is bloom.
Have you guys heard of bloom?
Wahoo.
So I'm really sad that I'm already close to
the end of my time slot because I'm -- so
it's by a group called -- a guy named Peter,
which I hope you guys have all heard of.
It came from a systems group at Berkeley,
and was attempting to indicator to the paramount
issues in the system community that typically
escape the PL community.
So namely, these are issues surrounding things
like coordination and data consistency that
really nobody seemed to care about so much
since Argus and these things should be dealt
with at the level of the programming model.
So that's kind of the why behind Bloom.
I don't have a lot of time to actually read
the quotes.
I'm going to put the slides up afterwards
so you can have a look at this.
This is really cool.
Basically, he's saying acid is slow, let's
have less coordination with things as things
become more and more distributed, basically.
And we have this calm principle that kind
of, you know, let's us reduce coordination
and maybe we can put this into a programming
language.
It's kind of the idea.
And we do this in a declarative language.
So it's a declarative language that uses program
analysis techniques, which enable both static
analysis and run time annotations on consistencies,
so you can make sure that consistency is -- you
can say something about consistency with,
like, you know, by giving somebody a certain
programming model and then analyzing the code
that they write.
So in this analysis like you said, it's based
on this calm principle, which is a type -- this
builds a tight relationship between consistency
and logical monotonicity, under any interleaving
delivery and computation, so basically, the
idea is, you know, you can deliver messages
in any order or whatever and the idea, you
know, is that you should have the same result.
And that result should somehow, monotonic.
So by contrast in monotonicity is requirement
of synchronization points.
So if you have nonmonotonic programs.
So it's, like, well, monotonicity is important.
It's important consistency.
So therefore, because monotonicity is a big
deal, bundles of declarative statements.
Statements are defined with respect to these
weird time stamps and there's no immutable
state, no side effects and things happen in
any order.
They argue that organized assumptions based
on this traditional vector that sort of informed
all of imperative programming, that's the
problem.
So therefore, we need no order at all.
Order is gone.
And then we just -- then we can do all kinds
of analysis to make sure things are monotonic
and think about where synchronization would
have to occur.
That's the idea.
I'm going to skip over the, you know, some
of the operations.
But the cool thing is that you have a bunch
of statements that operate on these weird
time steps, and then you get higher functions.
So you kind of reason in terms of these weird
time steps, and then you have high order functions
to, like, do more interesting things with.
So just a note.
And Bloom is implemented in Ruby, actually.
A Bloom program is just a Ruby class definition.
I'm telling you why this whole implementation
point because you should be notifying a pattern
over time.
The next one is Lasp.
I'm going to go since everybody think so that
Lasp is the most well-known distributed programming
language.
[Laughter]
I mean really, guys.
Lasp appeared because, you know, it's the
future, it's 2015 when it was created.
Everything is somehow distributed.
You got mobile games and add counters and
this Internet of whatever you want to call
these things.
I would use a different word.
But whatever.
So you have a bunch of things that are connected,
and you have all of these services being called
all the time and really stupid small programs.
Lots of things are happening.
And synchronization gets a little ridiculous
when one app has to make a call to three dozen
other services during its usage.
So got to somehow reduce synchronization,
yes.
And also, we can't get away from the idea
that state has to be replicated somehow.
I can come up with a silly example of a game
where, you know, you're fighting with some
other character having a sword fight, and,
you know, you each have health, like, health
counters, whatever, but you can see each other's
health counter because that's a replicated
state and if you're fighting this guy with
a sword, and you go into a tunnel because
you're on a train and doing it on your phone,
you've got to somehow continue playing or
doing whatever, and then you both have to
arrive at the same state.
Either you died or he died.
One of you died.
So that's a situation where, you know, it's
obviously extremely important, most important
situation you would ever need replicated state,
obviously.
And CRDTs are a thing that basically make
it easier to reason about -- reason about
replicated state in a distributed system.
And last, build CRDTs into the language.
I would love to talk a lot about CRDTs, but,
again, related to monotonicity and all of
these things, the idea that you can do a number
of updates in any order but two replicas of
the same sets should always arrive -- should
always arrive at the same result.
Should always have -- should converge to the
same state.
It's the basic idea; right?
So eventually consistent.
And then you can take this model of a CRDT
and implement different data structures like
sets, accounts, registers, dictionary, graphs,
et cetera.
And last, piggybacks on this idea of a CRDT,
and it's, like, guys, we could build really,
like, rich computations up by composing operations
on these CRDTs.
So these are data structures, we can kind
of have functional, like, high-order functions
and compose stuff, and it would be really
cool.
So last number of APIs, this functional one,
theoretic one, and then core API, which does
basic stuff, like, binding and updating, things
that you would expect.
And what's most important is, you know, this
is what it looks like.
You have -- I know what you all Lasp users,
so I know I shouldn't show you pictures of
what the code looks like.
It's really boring, I guess.
So it's all implemented on top of Erlang.
It's just an Erlang library.
Just Ayer language library, and it's built
on top of Reac, which provides a certain type
of CRDT and all implemented in Erlang, basically.
Okay.
So that was seven programming languages, guys.
So where did all the distributed languages
go?
That was the whole point of this talk.
And what I hope to argue right now is that
they didn't go anywhere, actually.
All of these distributed languages are just
DSLs now or libraries or whatever you want
to call them.
So at some point, I say, well, you have to
ask yourself what the hell is a programming
language anyway?
Do I need to implement an entire run time
system to count it as a language?
And honestly I believe is that we should probably
stop calling some of these languages, languages
and instead, we should just call them programming
models.
Haskell, Scala, Erlang, Java, all of these
things have proven to be good languages to
because he had entirely new smaller languages
or paradigms for doing distributed computation
in.
And, you know, there's really no harm in piggybacking
on the entire mountain of work that somebody
else has done to with some kernel or to do
some kind of portability out of some underlying
system.
So this DSL approach, I think is actually
where a lot of these distributed programming
languages are going.
They're actually becoming new programming
models implemented inside of another language.
And I'm going to end on this one sort of,
like, funny summary, in my view, of kind of
how I look at research.
I started this conversation -- or this talk
about, hey, research is actually, like, this
fast-moving thing if you zoom out in time
a little bit, and it's like people arguing
about stuff.
So you have this really funny, dynamic conversation
going on over the course of many decades where
you have Argus is, like, hey, guys, consistency
is super important.
Also, we should worry about partial failure.
I'm pretty sure it's going to be a big deal.
1988.
And you know what?
RPC is a good way to do requests and to make
requests to do response.
Should do RPC and promises are great.
One language came up with, like -- well, they
didn't come up with RPC but, you know, fought
for it.
Put all of these ideas, like, in one language,
which was pretty cool.
And then you have Emerald who pops up and
is, like, hey, objects, objects, objects,
they should be unified, mobile, efficient.
I agree definitely efficient.
Abstract types too.
Erlang appears.
Message passing is king, processes should
be light and totally independent.
Okay.
That was kind of some of the ideas that Argus
also fought for.
Linda somewhere out in a corner field.
Guys, message passing is totally crazy.
Shared memory model is definitely more natural.
Like, this is how we think.
So Tuple spaces, we can make them efficient.
You know, that's going to be the solution.
And then you have a Scala and Haskell appearing
here.
Like, man, Erlang is kind of sexy.
We like Erlang a little bit.
Do you think we could because he had this
Erlang stuff around language?
Scala is, like, hey, we don't need a whole
VM to manage these processes.
We can do it as a library.
Awesome.
Same kind of idea in Haskell.
But we can also do better.
Types and yay.
Channels.
Bloom appears, like, guys.
Programming language people.
Really, you guys forgot about the most important
thing.
Totally left consistency.
Everything that you're doing submarine monotonic
because you have no idea what order things
are going to happen in and make sure that
your parts of your program are monotonic so
you can move coordination.
Everything is great and programming languages
people are, like, whoa what -- I don't even
know what that is.
[Laughter]
They know what data log is.
And last appears is, like, hey, consistency
is important but so he so is compossibility,
so let's put this into the language.
Let's compose this, you know, these monotonic
things together and, you know, make this available
to people in a programming model.
That would be way more easy to reason about
than a data loggy thing.
So these are really conversations, and I hope
you see that at the end of this.
And it at that point, I'm sorry that I'm,
like, rambling for so long.
I'm going to say thank you for coming, and
you should probably come ask me questions
instead of raising your hand and doing questions
now.
You should also run to the keynote because
I definitely went over time, and I'm sorry.
[Applause]