So first I want to introduce you to our website, on the main website on here if you want to
read or test our theory based on the session types, and the order of information, more or less, will appear
here and we have a home, and there are either some news under -- our work was announced
by active developer in the conference on Scala.
Some of the session work that is applied to
that Scala language, and we
have application to Go where we talked about
our work at the Golang UK conference with developers, and like this, we have some information listed
here.
And then we have the home and then all publications are listed here, and so I will select some
of them to talk with you -- to talk today,
and about the other things that we have here.
And, also, tools, we have several applications with the session types to Go, and Scala, and
Haskell, and for example, you have C++, and the main project is with Redhat, Cognizant,
and OOI with Scribble projects,
of which I will talk about, and
actors in
the Python C, and the Java and so on
there, and those are the tools under public
source code available from git which you can get.
And I want to inform you about one thing,
and Kohei Honda was my collaborator and he
originated in session types and his information is also available here, but I
want to start now about the talk from here.
So what is a session type and session types is the
types, you know types, for example, Boolean, Integer, and Character, and also bit, which is difficult array
types
and in Haskell, you have functional types,
session types is a types likes functional
types for concurrency and method parsing.
Today, I introduce you about session types
and so that everybody here can understand
session types definitely
definitely yes. I promise you.
[laughter]
And so here you go.
And here is the current members of our group.
I have three female Ph.D. students, who's
female students coming next year: And also another postdoc
and this
is a selected list of our publications, I
don't know why it's not displayed properly
[fixing display]
OK, this way it's better.
And so I'm not talking on everything today,
and this is two years of our publications,
but, so I cut out my publications and there
are
three categories I can find: These types are
a very theoretical work of the session types
and session types is the type theory of concurrency, so these papers
are very difficult, probably, for you to read and very complicated.
However, green letters is about applications of session types to the programming language,
such as MPI, MPI code generation and verification, and Haskell and Java API
generations, and applications to the Go language
and the Scala, and we have wide, disparate
applications with the session types so that
you
can see it's very easy to integrate into the
programming language
So after this talk, I want to hear your opinion what is the maybe the application with that
session types to your problem.
And so, I also selected what you can
read among all the best publications not only
by me, but also of the team, and I selected
separate papers from theoretical, and binary
and multiparity
session types and I talk about Scribble description language and also about the last talk which
is about monitoring of protocols
Actually I'm also talking about the monitoring protocol and I will talk about it, and also
if -- if I have time, I will talk about the
code generations, and how you can apply the automata
theory and linking with session types to analyze the Go language
by Google end to end.
>> So let's start!
So five session types
Now currently, computation of concurrency
and the communication
is ubiquitous, and you can find the way to
organize software is increasingly based on
communication, for example, cloud and the
microservice and the message passing protocol, network protocol previous one is also best
under communications.
So questions here is how you can formally
describe, implement control, communication,
you said communication, interaction, but they
are not divisible, but how you can formalize
it, and reason it, and how to apply and there
is a past theory
of mobile process developed, particularly
in the European theory, and can be applied
to real distributed
application and programming language.
And these are the questions we are trying
to answer in our community.
So this talk I will show how to manage multiparty session types can be applied to verifying
large-scale cyber infrastructure for
E-science in US.
I am I'm going to show you how this project - Ocean Laboratory Initiative project
and this was run 5 years, historically, and this Ocean Observatories Initiative
is still running.
You can find the web page but the core project, developmental project, finished a couple
of years ago, and we participated and applied the session types to verify this cyber infrastructure,
which I want to a bit talk about now.
And so this is a very big project and very
expensive project, but the aim of this project
is extremely simple
So you get to that real time sensor data constantly coming from both offshore and onshore and
using bouey, submarines, and cameras, and satellites,
and transmit this data using high-speed
networks, so that various things and the university can use this data to analyze immediately.
And why it is interesting to observe the oceans, because this earth is 70% are oceans, and
they are a very, very active source of information.
For example, not only just temperatures, but also bacteria, and circularity, and circularity,
and also the sun and dust and the wind
All of this information
very useful to get to it so that you can use
to analyze for example, for example, to predict the forecasts and predict global warming and
also predict earthquake -- so getting analyzing this
data immediately, it's very important.
And so, so that's these things, and so this
is a big picture of the Ocean Observatories
Initiative and getting sensor data and from
our seas and transmit these data using very
big cyberinfrastructure, so that they can
develop scientific
projects, and realtime and remote controlling and things like this
and, this is a view of that cyber infrastructure, and
interestingly -- the interesting point of
this project is that they build this cyber
infrastructure from scratch using methods
with middleware, such as... I worked with the people and so what you can observe
here is that there are loads of loads of message-passing,
and because you need to transfer the messages
from point to point, and so that they're
use case is basically best with message-passing.
Here we have the questions: How you can catalog, manage, describe, control, and verify this
message passing.
That is reason why I work with these people using the theory of multiparty session types.
So why multiparty message passing protocol is important because we want to assure the
correctness of the message passing
For example, this cyberinfrastructure,
you needed to control the order of the messages
and the synchronization, and you want to guaruntee messages are robust and not and not circular, so
for example, deadlock freedom and liveness and also
this cyberinfrastructure, it's
too big to verify statically, so you need
to do something
dynamic analysis, and monitoring, discovery, also maybe you want
to control the message logically, for example,
using information with the timers.
So why did oceanography people interested in the theory and this fundamental work and
work with us?
Their cyberinfrastructure is very expensive,
so that it was assumed it would retain 30 years,
so if we retain 30 years, you want it
to build the correct infrastructure, that is
the reason we are working with them, and the part of that project.
So why multi-party session types?
But I want to say why type best verification
is important?
So Robin Milner is one of the two Turing winners in the UK
and he -- he initiated ML -- functional programming and also he created ccs, process calculus.
>> And he said why types are important...
is that types can digest the computations,
so as I will explain, session types can describe the communication protocol types, and why
types are important is that you can combine the notion of types through programming language and through
the chain easily, as you know, with Java and Haskell and Python
Python is not a typed language, but these
kind of things can be easily integrated to
-- to the change.
Another thing is that types are very cheap
comparing, for example. the approach of model checking,
because
normally it is finished by linear type checking is finished compiled under linear type or
polynomial type, and session types most of their verifications,
are polynomial types, and also it is easy
to extend, for example logical verification,
even dynamic monitoring, which I will explain now.
And before that, I really think, and this
is ideally, I ask you to also communicate
with academic people, because I believe that dialog between industry and academia are extremely
important, also discover the very theoretical fundamental discovery, and the reason is
that multiparty session types was discovered by the interaction with industry people, which
I want to explain in a bit of detail.
So session types, it's starts at the type
theory of the mobile process, actually quite
a long time ago, '98, and at that time, nobody used it.
Just a theory of the mobile process.
But after that, whoever saw this coming and the people tried to control or verify web service
language, and so Milner, Honda and I are invited to join W3C working group, one working group
called choreography description language group
And where we proposed to use session
types.
However, their language, standardization language was very, very complicated, so that we spent
five years to formalize the idea, because
we didn't understand what they are doing.
[laughter]
And so Kohei it was a bit; (he) initiated this project,
and then he invited a couple of industry people,
and then they started a venture company called
Pifortec, and we started a simplification
of their language called Scribble.
And that is the original multiparty session
types.
But what I want to show is that.
These is the original CDL language and you
know where industry people meet and discussed
about the standardization, it becomes extremely complicated and this is a protocol of Hello
world.
But, you don't understand that this the protocol of Hello world!
Because they want to put for example, roleType, participantType, channelType and so on
And so it's quite complicated.
And so Kohei sent -- Kohei -- sent quite a
bit of emails to
a couple of industry partners.
Let's forget the CDL and start from scratch to write a very simple protocol language called scribble,
and that is the start of that multiparty session type theory, actually, and so this Scribble
language, I will introduce later, and everybody understands
this is hello world protocol.
And so here is that protocol declaration,
and the keywords and the hello world, and
they are two persons -- You and World.
And we send a message hello from you to world.
And this is the type to describe the global
protocol
And so after that, actually, I went to show
and also I'm going to show, how binary session
types, it's extended to the multiparty session types, but very long time ago, we couldn't
extend and we don't know how to extend to
theory of binary session types to multiparty
session types, but using the idea with the
Scribble with CDL, we could actually extend
to the
multiparty session types and so we wrote the paper that accepted at POPL, top-tier conference of
the programming language and we had quite a benefit of that engineering idea.
So we are always welcome to getting the idea, and also, because theoretically extended and
Scribble is promoted at one at the later group projects after that.
And we started to work with several industry people and also currently expanding this circle.
So now I want to show what are the session types, and actually I hope everybody here
understands at least the binary session
types, because the idea is very simple.
And binary means two-party session types,
OK?
So, let's think this is online shopping,
and there are two participants, or roles,
buyer and
seller.
And the buyer tried to buy a book from the
seller, for example, Amazon, sending that
message title, under this type, and then seller sends back the quote to the buyer, and then
there are two choices.
OK, or quit, and if we click OK, and the buyer sends an address, and then the seller sends us the variable date, and
otherwise, if he doesn't like that quote,
he quits the protocol.
OK?
Everybody understand?
And basically send and receive, and there
is a choice, and then if choice,
one choice, will continue, otherwise quit
that protocol.
And so these session types from the buyer's viewpoint, written like this, OK?
So up means !, ! means output.
Output to string, and input is a quote, and
this plus mark means there's two choices.
OK or quit.
If OK, send us the link and get us the date
and end the protocol, OK?
And then quit, end the protocol.
So there are your choices here, OK?
So that if you can write a UML diagram
nearly using the session types.
Next, and then now you get to the idea.
Interesting thing is that seller session type
is the dual.
What do we mean dual?
Dual is swapping output to input, input to
output
So ! means output, input means question.
So this is the viewpoint from the seller and
the buyer, and this ampersand, it's
waiting a choice, so he is awaiting the choice,
OK, or quit.
And once you type that program, using the
session types and the buyer and the seller,
you can see there is no deadlock, because
input match output, output matches input
and there is a choice always then waiting
a choice, OK?
In this way, you can guaruntee deadlock
freedom using the session types, just checking
the duality, and this comes along -- the underlying idea
comes from linear logic by Girard and that is an important
point of the session types.
Now, these are the two players, two people,
but how you can extend to that managed parties?
So, there are three parties here, and I just
extended this scenario to that another buyer,
and now scenario is that you tried to buy
-- two buyers tried to collaborate with each
other on sending a message and buy the book, and now, protocol becomes a managed party,
and so seller, first the buyer sends a title
and the seller distributes the quote, both
buyer 1 and buyer 2, and buyer 1 sends that
quote, how much he can contribute to the buyer 2,
and then there is another choice repeating
like this, OK?
However, how you can manage deadlock free with more than
two parties?
The idea is not so simple, because you may
think, this is like let's divide the binary--
-- into binary
in this managed party protocol.
That doesn't work.
Why it doesn't work?
Because you need three separate session types, and previously, because you have three combinations:
buyer, seller, buyer 2.
Ok?
And all protocol becomes split.
And not only this protocol.
Then this protocol becomes a type of if we
use binary session types, but what we want
to prove is that describe and check with this multiparty session types, how you can do it
using the idea of the session types.
And here it's a bit technical and faster.
So the idea comes from the choreography description language and as I told you before, and first
of all
you need to write the global protocol because
you wanted to give that protocol.
For example, if there are Alice, Bob, and
Carol, and this role, and this
type of T1 message to B, B to C, and then C
sends to A. You just described this as a type
like this, and this examples of the choreography protocol, like A send to B, B send to C, C
sends to A like this. This is a type which you need to describe first.
And then next step is that.
You need to then this to project into the
binary
session types, so that each endpoint can
have the interface with output and input
and the choice so if you implemented the program
following this sequence, then each people
interact correctly.
And, but this is a projected, because I would
be
able to throw down, supported from the viewpoint
of A. A sends the type of message, T1, to
B, and which
means send B type over T1, and C sends the
message T3, to this person, and annotated
by this participant, who am I going to send,
and from whom you are going to receive.
So A has a data type.
B has this type, C has this type.
Because these three are projected from these
global
types, and once you get to these types, each
participant behaves correctly, so that you
can guarantee deadlock freedom, Ok?
However.
This is a bit difficult.
So maybe it's a bit difficult to explain,
but if you do not follow these global types,
this is the bad local type which does not
follow this projection, but this is a dual with each other but
you can see that more people are waiting and, even dual with each other, so that this is a deadlock.
So writing global types and the project does work to check the endpoint protocol.
So now I'm going back to the sea again, and this this is the ocean observatory initiative
institution,
and in front of the sea, because they like
sea, and this is the pier by University of
San Diego, I
think, and they started the oceanography first
in the world, and this is the storage
which stores the instruments.
and we feed with them and worked with them and they developed some architecture with their
developers.
And this is my student, and this is my post
doc who developed their protocol.
And so this work, and so --
[laughter]
I want to use these global types and the global type is ... these multiparty session types are used in various
ways and I only introduce one way today at
the main applications, and the rest I will
quickly explain today.
I hope I have time to manage it.
So first of all, global type, its projected
to local types, but these local types looks
like the state machine, and using this information we write a program for example Alice, Bob,
Carol, and check incoming and outgoing messages correct against these local types
That is the application I will explain.
And before that, I want to briefly explain
about what
is Scribble language, and Scribble language
is the -- Scribble language -- is a kind of programming language to describe that multiparty session types, and as I said
session types start from the types of the
theory, of the concurrency,
where we write all these papers with Greek-letters and then industry partner said that they don't want
to read Greek-letters paper
and they want to read this kind of notations,
so we developed this protocol in the description language with them, and they designed them,
and then automatically you can -- you can
project to it, but before -- because I don't
have time, I really want to quickly show what is that application here, and so, this is
a protocol we try to specify from the Ocean Observatories Initiative.
Project: I show here.
And so this is the Scribble web page.
If you are interested after my talk, because it is quite a big project that I will explain
later.
And this is web page that you can test Scribble protocol and then you can check under whether
this is correct, and you can project this
is automatically like this, so this is a bit
of an education tool.
So what I want to show today is how we try to
verify that using the session types architecture,
this protocol between the customer agent and the provider agent, and interactions specification
of the ocean observatory, and so as you can see, the developer wrote about this kind of
UML diagram.
It is very complicated
and it is very ambiguous, and it is not clear what they want to do with this kind of -- on
the natural language explanation, so what
we did is that we that actually tried to write
down, and before that, I want to show a
bit monitor architecture of this OOI and the
what they do is that they analyze and control
this
kind of message passing, and using various
kinds of hierarchical architectures, and you can see how Scribble is located at the bottom
part: And they can intercept in the various
sophisticated policies and sent out with that
architecture and decide to--sorry--whether you can throw
away and
the message that is orchestrated, finally, can control whether
you can throw away messages or not.
This is the way that you can integrate a lot of different tools and ideas.
That was part of the Ocean Observatories Initiative
Tool.
But before that, I want to go back to our
stuff.
And so, if you use that session types, you
can write this kind of ambiguous protocol
very clearly and first of all, you declare this is a multiparty protocol.
Actually only two roles, but negotiate
role communicator as C. Role producer as P.
And C and P are abbreviations.
Next, we can write that C gets a message and that this is a submessage and
operations is a propose can be sent from C to P and there
is a choice after P, and then for example,
accept and confirm, or reject, and propose
are like this.
You can add these kind of things and then
choice can be nested and also you can not
understand probably the declaration, but there is the causation of this protocol so that you
can choose stop or because of the protocol, you can try and try many times like this
And the next step is that two you can automatically project the global type to local type by checking
the global type is correct, and this is that projection from the viewpoint of consumer, and the basically
just chop that view of the global types to
the local types.
And then you generate the state machine, and so this is that corresponding, this corresponding
with these local types and so that you can
check that incoming and outcoming messages
correct against this state machine.
And this is Scribble and the web page, and I show it and we have a GitHub and various
source files can be get from here, and
we have several applications based on this,
but probably I'm not sure how much time I
have remaining, but let's see.
And this is the big thing of the OOI so that
we can finally control
all of these kind of things by underwater vehicles and this
is the pictures, and so I'm -- this is that
interface of the OOI so you can get this message
constantly.
So I want to show the demo of that monitoring, how you use the Scribble to monitor the message
and very quickly to two minutes.
[prepping demo]
So this is an RPC protocol in between
the Scribble
language and this is the Python code, endpoint code, you
want to monitor in it and you can see that
there is something like -- sorry -- I think
it's better if I stop it
its a bit quick.
So this is the that global protocol which
tries to describe the interaction with the
provider and the requester and first you needed to write this kind of protocol which you want
to monitor.
And then this is a Python code which you want to monitor and whether they correctly behave
or not.
And you can see several other operations such as accept and reject, and invite.
We want to check whether the message is correct or not.
And this is some kind of wrapper and Hello client and now we tried to run the
batch machine of the OOI, and so first you
needed to execute the tool and batch machine, and then Python monitoring,
inside this capability.
[running demo]
over here.
And then so now we have hello client,
and so, then, now you can see message is correct
monitor or not, and returns a status, such
as correct, and correct, and correct, and
you can correct message input and output and now you change this correct program to the
wrong incorrect program, changing accept to
invite, and then then monitor again.
And the first one is correct and then you
can show
the next message is incorrect like this, and
like this by monitoring the message against the Scribble, you can guarantee that you can
detect the bad message,
and protocol and this is quite a simple application for that session test.
Like this, we worked with the OOI people
And, I'm showing this -- sorry, where are
it going?
[prepping video demo]
And so, I show only one application on dynamic monitoring, but this general idea of global
protocol and this projection can be applied to various different applications which I
want to show a bit quickly, and I show the
dynamic monitoring, and also, you can of course
use the session types by type-checking, using the session types as types, and write some
programs
such as Haskell and do the type-checking integrated session types and so and so on that you can guarantee
that it will involve many participants.
Also, interesting application is that you
can generate the code for that global types,
and for this we have two works of the MPI
code generation and Java code generation.
Probably, I cannot do the demo, because I
have a shortage
of time today, and so also, you may think
the other way around, not writing global
type, but generating global types from the
communication
of the program, may be useful.
Actually, we have the work of this, and we
applied this to two different applications
which I just want to very quickly show,
and
this slide I'll skip.
And basically session types have mathematical
correspondence with communicating automata.
I don't know if you know the communicating
automata, but automata which can describe
input and output and asynchronous messages
and I was very shocked, these entity I discovered
in very old literature of the communicating
automata, which exactly corresponds with that
of binary session types.
And the communicating automata is that basically it is very powerful and it is undecidable
to check
whether this communication is deadlock-free
or not, but if you restrict that,
this communicating automata, with certain
kinds of conditions, which exactly similar
with the session types, deadlock-detection
becomes
decidable and actually this was proved before
the session types appeared, so that mathematically
good structure arrived in the different areas,
That was one surprise thing
when you do this kind of research work.
And, so on this I may skip a bit.
Interestingly we applied this this approach
to this legacy code analysis of a bank application,
but I will skip it.
And I want to show one example of how you
can build the session types from the communicating
automata, so there are -- so natural question is whether you can
extend binary approach to the multiparty approach?
And the right-hand side is the communicating automata,
and you cannot see how they interact, but
you can imagine this kind of flow of the message, it's analyzed by the source code, for example,
Java or something, and then you can get to this
automata, but you don't know how they interact
correctly or deadlock-free, but we could
build the
session types by using a certain kind of theory
and decidable and then you can check whether this automata for party interaction is correctly
globally organized and then translated into that BPMN choreography language.
This is just a couple of applications and
I just want to show one quick application
to the ...
Go language by Google.
And I don't know if you know -- oh, maybe
it's better to show that a little bit fast.
[prepping video]
I guess many of you know that Go programming language by Google, which is based on the
process calculus such as Csp and pi-calculus, basicallly
they are based on message passing and channel communications,
and it is written here and their communication is basically -- they encourage to use message-passing
instead of shared communications.
And we applied this approach to analyze deadlock detection
and I have five minutes, so that I will show
the demo here.
[opening demo]
So, this is the Go interpreter, and this
is Go programming language.
You can see send and receive work
and so this is -- this describes that
basically.
Sorry, it's made too quick.
And, This is the deadlock, because send and receive are mismatching, and if you run this
program by Go interpreter, you can see send-to, and receive-one, so it is obviously deadlock.
And, then, actually Go has a runtime deadlock checker.
So you cannot write, because they detected a deadlock, but their deadlock analysis is
first of all
dynamic, and cannot capture that partial deadlock, and we tried to solve this
using the synthesis of the session types.
And now we change the protocol just using the while loop like this, and then this is a
still a mismatch of course -- protocol.
And working, working, working, which means that because each Go routine that's running,
they're deadlock (analysis) dynamic tool
cannot capture this deadlock, OK?
So now we are trying to use our Go tool which generates
the automata from each Go routine and build a global type
so that  you can check whether the Go language
or Go program is a deadlock-free or not by static analysis.
And so first we create the state machine,
from each Go routine and with this we can
show that
first of all
and, like this,
You can create just a state machine from each Go routine code, and then use synthesis to
try to find out the matching between input and
output, and
using our session types theories.
And so we check it ...
[checking]
and generate it, and then here I can say -- sorry -- I can say here we said this
checking
it's incorrect, because it doesn't -- input
and
output -- doesn't match, and it is not also
well-formed
So what you can describe visually in the session type
is that ... ,
because you can generate from these kind of global types, using the session type theory,
and you can see there are two ends which is incorrect global types.
So this shows a deadlock.
I cannot explain details with this time.
And now we change the correct program, only we have send and one receive and then now we do
the same things, and generate and check now, whether they are compatible or not using the
this -- our automata theory, and then it returns correct now?
I think so.
OK.
And since its check is true and now we can build this tool using the .dot applications,
and now because we see that this interaction is correct, like this.
And so I wanted to show another real code generation
example, which applied to Scribble to Java directly,
but probably I don't have time now?
And so maybe I should probably stop, or I
can just quickly show it.
>> ZEESHAN: ...
>> Can I do, or maybe better to have questions?
>> ZEESHAN: Yeah.
>> Yes, OK, OK, because it's probably better to -- and so, anyway,
so I will finish my talk here, and every information
that I said, you can see from the web page, but it's quite probably difficult to understand
what tools and papers you should read, and it also depends
on interest, you know, if you want to use
the session types to verify and specify the
message passing, and you are very welcome
to directly send an email to me and so that we can start a really good collaboration
and thank you very much
[applause]
>> ZEESHAN: We have time for a couple of questions and then head out for lunch.
>> So, you mentioned that one of the benefits of using session types compared to model checking
in like CCS or pi-calculus or CSP is that
you don't have the same kind of (state) space explosion
that you would if you were doing model checking in a process calculus.
Do you have any intuition for sort of like
where that boundary is?
Where the model checking approach isn't
going to be as useful
because for a lot of the examples that you presented, I think
you could do the same kind of static analysis and produce something in
one of these process
calcules -- calculus -- calculi -- and run
them through a model checker, and sorta do
the same kinda of checks, and so I would
be interested to hear if you have a sort
of have an idea of sorta where that becomes
untenable, where you sorta have to do this type-based approach instead?
>> Nobuko:Yes, yes, so we actually have the publication
to to the TACAS this year on linked model
checking and session
types and we used a model checker and also a session
type checker to run the benchmark, which
is
good.
And also, an automata approach, in TACAS 2016, so this year's TACAS paper and compare.
Actually some kind of checking, you can
use model checking and some of the examples, model checking scales very well, because,
now, it is out of bounds, but certain kinds of
normal kinds of session types
structure between the program language, still type-checking scales much faster than this,
and this is really depends on
the examples.
And actually, I said generally, you know,
session types scale well, but complicated
examples,
and because of the effort of model checking people, it may run sometimes faster for big
examples.
Actually there are many interesting big examples.
And so,
Golang, we have
our next work, which we used -- actually --
more like symbolic semantics, because
session types
are too limited.
So,
there are various links of the types
of the pi-calculus and
the session types, and so,
this is a
really good question.
Thank you.
Yes.
>> ZEESHAN: Any other questions?
All right, thank you, that's good.
[applause]