Today's talk is going to be a talk that I
haven't done before with parts of the talk
that I'd actually promised to do for the conference.
If I can get there.
We'll see how far we get in the slides.
Let me just find that PDF.
Where is it?
Oh, there it is.
Generated 15 minutes ago.
[laughter]
All right.
So Zeeshan reached out to me because I had
referenced a talk at a conference I gave called
Eyeo.
Largely people who are working in the design
fields, along with artists, working with code
and data as creative materials, so I'm going
to do a talked that's related to that.
But I went down a social justice rabbit hole
last night, so there's going to be loads of
stuff that I've been thinking about for a
long time but haven't necessarily articulated
in a complete talk but it has plenty of examples.
So we also agreed that I would do this bit
that I call shock and awe, which I'll explain
in a moment, which is essentially all of my
work for 18 years in about four minutes.
[laughter]
No, I'm not kidding.
So the title for this talk, in case you weren't
aware of it, comes from a piece by Jenny Holzer
called truisms, which are these series of
texts or things that sound like commercial
slogans, almost, but they're kind of hard-hitting
and quite deep.
You know, the idea of abuse of power comes
as no surprise, so you know, paraphrasing
that, I call this talk abuse of an algorithm
comes as no surprise and I think most of you
can probably agree with me.
So this is the one from the same series, I
just like this one a lot, because cruelty
is always possible later.
And finally, if you aren't political, then
your personal life should be exemplary.
You know, in these election times, I don't
know if being political is quite the sort
of copout.
So my name is Marius, I'm from Norway, I never
went to art school, but I'm an artist.
I never completed a degree, but I teach people
at master's and Ph.D. level sometimes and
I started coding on TRS-80 color computer
back in the '80s, but then I got to computer
science which I always thought this is what
I'm going to do and I realized at least computer
science, at least the way it was taught in
the early to mid '90s is the most boring thing
I could do with a computer.
Traveling salesman has its place, but it didn't
connect with me.
I hope you don't find that statement offensive.
It's obviously not that I think computer science
has no potential, it's just more the things
that I was interested really in doing it with
just wasn't being taught.
So I dropped out of computer science and started
working with graphic designers, trying to
apply ideas from code to design problems and
to artistic problems, which meant that in
'94, there was nowhere you could go for that,
so I started designing rave posters, doing
these crazy 3D rendered things that were all
generated with code, so that means that you
know, 20 years later I find myself as an autodidact
coming from a quite sort of mutant hybrid
practice.
So today I do all kinds of things.
I'm an artist, I'm a creative technologist,
you can hire me, I call myself an aesthetist
for hire and also I teach workshops and also
at proper educational institutions.
That's me with my original color-basic instruction
book and if you look in the corner, you can
see that's actually the TRS-80.
I don't think it works anymore.
And my work looks like this.
This is basically what you'll get if you Google
image search me and to give you the complete
overview, I will open processing.
And do -- show all of it.
Let's see.
I need 3.
Does everyone know Processing?
Yeah?
So Processing is the kind of tool which might
be a little superfluous to requirements for
proper coders in quotation marks, but it takes
away all the tedium of creating projects and
setting up Java, etc.
It's essentially a Java framework for creative
coding.
And it works quite well.
So this piece is, let me just check my display
settings, because this piece was created a
few years ago, so this was like 1024X768,
so I've got to optimize a little bit.
Essentially I collected all the images I could
find of my work and made a playback system
that plays is back in -- let me see what's
going on here.
Oh, that's the wrong -- this is the wrong
version.
I fixed that yesterday.
But now it's going to be full screen.
Where is it?
That should be the one.
This would be much cooler at a conference
where you don't know code.
[laughter]
(Chuckling) they would be impressed.
Here it's not so much.
Let's see if we can run this.
So if we can get the lights, and and turn
up the volume
[Electronic music]
Booming booming booming booming booming booming].
[Electronic Music]
[cheers]
[applause]
All right, so that was 919 slides if you
watched the meter, and of course it accelerates.
All of that is from '94.
So I have to give credit to Golan Levin, one
of the people who's supported open frameworks
into existence.
He's also been involved in processing, but
he suggested to me, because he knew that I
had thousands of images just lying around,
why don't I do an interactive presentation
where I just skip through all my slides and
have people say wait, wait, wait.
But he trusts audiences way more than I do.
So I did the noninteractive version.
And now for something slightly less pleasant,
but way more important.
>> So when I talk about political issues to
people who are not necessarily interested
-- it's not that the audience isn't interested,
it's more that but this isn't what I do, why
do I have to listen to this?
I feel compelled to include a lot of disclaimers.
Some of the ideas I'm going to talk about
might seem controversial.
I don't think they are, but the basic argument
is technology is p not a neutral thing.
Technology is never a neural a priori innocent
object, because technology is always applied
for the users and the people who create tools,
hence whether you -- you created an infrared
sensor or a machine learning algorithm, there
are implications of these tools that you cannot
disavow.
You got that?
(Chuckling).
Is that a fair statement so far?
Because I think as coders, it's very easy
to become seduced by this idea of a perfect
world of algorithms, which is kind of like
the way that economists become seduced by
the perfect world of the market, you know,
the invisible hand, the banks will regulate
themselves, it's going to be great.
Which turns out to not be true and when you
combine banks and algorithms, you get some
really profound fuckery going on.
Because coders are people, right?
I mean who in here can say that like I've
never written a flawed and stupid project
in my life, right?
Like it's just a thing.
When you think about sort of the real-time
mission critical stuff, like you know, things
that have to control space stations, that
stuff becomes terrifying and in fact, you
know, how many space missiles have they lost
because of you know, flotation mark errors?
Like, it happens.
So the goal in putting out the following sort
of concerns more than conclusions.
Is that I'm interested in not in political
correctness, because that's kind of bullshit,
because it's just a pseudonym for decency,
when you consider
IBM's Watson, where he's moved up from playing
Jeopardy to figuring out your medical charts
and who knows, maybe Watson is excellent at
that, but all these trends that we're seeing
right now are deeply linked to understanding
and facilitating human experiences.
That means that you're moving into a whole
other area than optimizing traveling salesmen,
you know?
But the corollary is also that even the most
unassuming software developer has the power,
particularly in this day and age, to affect
society.
If Uber is able to disrupt labor politics
primarily through an API, and a set of protein
columns, and Airbnb is able to pretty much
undermine urban planning, why shouldn't your
apps and APIs be able to effect change in
a positive way?
Before I begin again, you know, I'm a white
guy.
I'm a Caucasian male, born in Norway provided
with a safety network just by default.
In Norway, we don't believe in people living
under bridges.
You're not going to drop out of society just
because you've got a health problem.
And I'm not trying to say anything about America
like based on that...
[laughter]
...but let me just say that I'm aware of the
privilege that that comes with.
Also, most of the issues that I'm talking
about here, you know, the overlived reality
that I don't share, so I don't presume to
talk for anyone else, but I can talk about
it from the perspective of being a developer
who hopes that the tools I create won't impact
other people negatively.
So this is an email from Dave Schroeder from
the Eyeo Festival, and it's not an exciting
email, but the first is all about content
and in that email he stipulates you can swear
on stage, but you cannot denigrate the experience
of someone who is other than you.
You know, or even, you know, it could be another
white male, you just, you know, be a decent
human being and consider the political implications
of being onstage.
I don't get these emails a lot.
I know that Papers We Love have a code of
conduct, right, which is something that came
out of our conferences not having them and
failing miserably at addressing harassment
and abuse happening at conferences, because
it happens.
So if we're awesome, why does the word brogrammer
even exist?
When I heard that word, I was so upset.
Do you want to identify with that word?
It's a word that separates people in different
groups and reinforces the power of one.
If we are all you know, potentially geniuses,
why haven't we been able to get rid of brogrammer?
I mean it's such a stupid word, too.
So you know, the fact that people are smart
does not mean they're automatically good.
That's been pretty well proven through history
and I'm not saying that the present audience
is racist or sexist, in fact I have a pretty
good idea that you're very unlike to be, but
stupid shit does go on and sometimes good
friends of yours surprise you negatively.
So the geek feminism wiki has a lot of these.
One of them I think was the fork joke at the
Python Conf, like I don't remember when.
But if you look at this, and it starts in1973.
Does everybody know the lemma image?
The sort of canonical image, the same way
that the Utah teapot is the Te test measurement
for three meshes.
It's a Playboy centerfold, you know, that's
fairly implicitly sexist right there.
The image is not offensive itself, but it
says something from the cultural context it
comes from and it also goes on and updates
it and it's quite depressing to read, but
the fact that this exists means that we can
do better.
So Moritz Stefaner, he's a speaker at conferences
regularly so he created a data visualization
to look at him or the group that he belongs
to which happens to be the group that I also
belong to.
And figure out you know, what is the gender
balance at these conferences and this is where
transparency is actually based on databases,
if we have a dataset that represents participants
and winners of awards, then we might actually
be able to look at what are the facts in our
own community, and if we can't do better,
then how can we expect anyone else to?
This is quite funny article that came out
which just, you know, purely using the, you
know, mathematical facts, it proves that the
idea that you would have an all-male panel
at a mathematics conference is just, you know,
astronomically improbable, and this is one
area where I think that like these tools which
technically, like you know historically have
served sort of the status quo and the technocrats.
What if you turned that data back on them,
well, that's really unlikely that you would
have an all-male panel.
I've sat on all-male panels and I've vowed
to not do it again because it's pretty uncomfortable.
Here's another good piece by Aandand Prasad,
it stipulates that in a random selection of
20 people, women represent 20% of speakers
these are the more likely distributions that
you would get.
In fact, it would be more statistically so
any time you go to an architecture conference,
and there are no women on stage, you know
there's something that prevents them from
being there.
So that's cultural buy y that's one of those
big bugbears that we can't agree on and we
all agree that it sounds like a good idea
but I don't even know how do I invite more
women or people of color etc. if I were organizing
a conference?
What if I don't know them so it's a very complex
issue.
But there is a simpler issue which is what
happens when technology becomes the bias?
When the bias is actually coded into the technology?
Which I think, you know, that's one of those
similarly to that statistics exercise, it
becomes hard to argue that you know, like
a facial recognition software that can't identify
non-Caucasians is not hard to say that that's
biased and coded in algorithm.
So can an algorithm be racist?
Yeah.
Take a wild guess.
Why should it be any different?
However, you can say that like, oh, but software
developers can't be expected to deal with
these issues because they're so deeply ingrained
in like social and historical factors, but
we adhere to principles of connect accessibility
on a routine basis.
The first time that I really came across a
story that sort of involved this was 2009.
HP released some laptops with webcams that
had face-tracking, you know, an algorithm
that we now take for granted, every camera
has it, but two coworkers tried it out, and
the black coworker realized that the image
tracking stopped working as soon as the white
woman moved out of the picture and HP at the
time came out with the by-now-traditional
statement like, we don't know what's going
on, it's an algorithm, we don't really know.
And at the time, I remember like seeing it
and thinking like, well, I can see how that
would happen.
I don't see how, like HP could like support
it continuing to happen, but it sort of, you
know, early days of technology or whatever.
You know, in terms of like the offensiveness
rank, it's like, yeah, that's really not great,
but no one's going to die from not being tracked
on this webcam on a laptop.
But then I read this article, which is an
amazing article that I recommend everyone
to read.
I will publish this PDF with these links as
hyperlinks, and this is a link -- this is
a story by Syreeta McFadden about white balance
and her roam of self-perception and also like
her family memories, because white balance
was developed to be calibrated to be like
guess who?
Yeah, people who look like me, which means
they did a get job of representing people
like me, but they didn't do a good job of
people with color and so the white balance
was thrown out, and reading just these paragraphs
is kind of heartbreaking because the idea
that you learn at an early age that you cannot
be represented in a photograph, that's some
bad technology.
And some bad cultural impacts.
It's a fantastic article, I recommend reading
it.
But then you look at these things that color
balance was based on and you start realizing
why something like this comes about.
I love sort of the basic look and the kitsch
of these.
These are generally called Shirley cards.
It was Canon who came out with them.
And I think the one on the left is actually
an composition of several decades, I'm assuming
the bottom right is the '80, it looks very
plausible to me.
And the one on the right, while, you know,
just exciting in its own right.
[laughter]
Is obviously excellent for color calibration,
because it has all of them.
So just the fact that the word normal is implied
there, it implies a normal.
There is a technological normal when it comes
to photo reproduction.
Now, I'm not saying that the people who developed
the chemical processes involved in making
film were like, dyed in the wood racists and
wanted to prevent people of color to be represented
well in photography.
Not at all.
That seems unlikely.
Most of these examples are very unlikely to
be you know, the result of like a conscious
bias, however there's a cognitive bias and
basically like you -- you have your known
unknowns and you have your unknown unknowns,
and that's where bias hides.
Your known unknowns might be if you're organizing
a conference and you know you should invite
more women, but you don't know any more women
to invite, that's your known unknown.
So this is a slightly more upgraded one which
reminds me slightly of the announcement of
this series of underwear where nude is a color
for everyone.
[laughter]
So this is a project by a student of mine,
Greg DorsaInville and he did a project where
he was able to use open CV to track basically
face in prime time television and then he
was able to do an indexing to find out what
is the color representation or the ethnicity
representation in an evening of programming,
so he did this sort of index-based thing.
To me this is an excellent use of data.
To use it to express something which is, you
know, of course an implied and experienced
reality as a hard observable fact.
That works.
This is for light relief, actually.
You might have seen this, this is Adam Harvey
with a project that essentially, it gives
you instructions on how to avoid being recognized
by a facial recognition software.
So it's the opposite problem.
Essentially since open CV identifies certain
ridges and certain configurations of features.
If you can demolish those features, remove
your eyebrows and make things sideways, it
works.
OK, this should not be here.
I'll just turn off the internet or turn this
thing off.
So it's the opposite problem and I'm sure
you've seen it referred to.
For instance, I tweeted about this, which
is from elementary, you know, the Sherlock
Holmes show.
It's a really stupid implementation compared
to I think Adam's implementation is way more.
This is like the worst punk you ever met.
[laughter]
But he -- it's also included in Minority Report
where one of the people has facial tattoos
to obscure facial recognition.
It's rare, but it's happened a couple of times
where I know people's work had ended up on
sciencey procedural shows.
But if, you know, simple image processing
can be, you know, problematic in itself, mostly
due to calibration errors, what about machine
learning?
Machine learning just to me is just, you know,
like I have so many friends who are extremely
excited about it, this entire new genres of
work popping up and yet we know, you know,
they're fuzzy and they're prone to like error,
and you know, we like them because they have
some reliability, but in the real world, if
you're going to make this into a product,
then some of that just gets terrifying.
Because -- and you know, an object recognizer,
which is hilarious in like misidentifying
objects while you're debugging could misidentify
objects or people while not debugging and
just, you know, have a huge impact on your
brand.
If you're just an app developer, I mean if
you're Google, you can survive it but if you're
like a single app developer, probably that
social media firestorm is something you couldn't
survive.
Because this is the Daily Mail, not my favorite
newspaper, had an article about Flickr introducing
autotagging in a very rushed way around the
same time that Google Photo started doing
it, and this is the gate to Dachau concentration
camp, which it has labeled "support architecture
jungle gym," which of course as technologists,
we could all see, yeah, I could see how that
makes sense, but as your grandma end user,
that's not going to fly.
This one is not hard to catch I'm not saying
they're trivial.
But this is some fucked-up shit.
Finding a tag album in your Google photos
where you and your friend have been tagged
as gorillas, that's not forgivable.
You know.
Those software engineers and those project
managers should get -- yeah.
Hm, heads should roll.
My favorite thing about this, not that there
are any favorite things about this, but the
bottom is like, he says, what kind of sample
image data you collected that resulted in
this, son?
(Chuckling).
Which, yeah, is exactly the problem.
So but that's, you know, the -- again, like
still, this is simpler stuff, this is about
like tagging images, sure it's hugely offensive,
but it's unlikely to ruin your life.
This should have is likely to ruin someone's
life.
This is an article from ProPublica, which
has been dealing a lot lately with the idea
of bias in algorithms, particularly in machine
learning etc., and this about crime risk assessment
software where the risk of someone repeat
offending is calculated, based on various
factors, factors that we as the -- you know,
the public are a loud to know, because it's
a proprietary commercial software.
And they weigh different factors in different
ways and sure enough, it seems to have a predilection
for identifying white offenders as unlikely
to reoffend and other, you know, people of
other colors, likely to offend.
This is, you know, this is real.
The fact that this is out there, in courts
right now, the fact that people don't necessarily
have the right to address, you know, what
-- how is that judgment being made, there's
no good systems of recourse.
I mean try critiquing an algorithm in a courtroom.
We all know how that went for Apple and Google.
If you follow the transcripts of Apple versus
Google trial, half of it was people explaining
expression algorithms to lay audiences so
good luck trying to explain the machine learning
system which we all believe in, has been trained
badly.
What about the machine-learning algorithm
that the CIA, etc., like, uses to identify
terrorists, when they admitted that we only
have training data based on 20 or 30 known
terrorists, too and that thing is used to
inform drone strikes, that's some bad technology!
So that's probably the biggest one of all.
A more seemingly trivial one is the idea of
data collection.
If you're writing a social media app, you're
going to write into it all kinds of ways of
recording interactions and metadata, you know,
again, metadata is also a favorite of people
trying to track terrorists and the reason
why is because metadata is extremely revealing.
If I can see all the text messages you sent
to different people, I can tell who these
people likely are in your life.
If there's a gap in your message data like
one of my students had, then there's a reason
why you weren't there, if you were in hospital,
or you were traveling, or as happened in this
case, someone was stalking you.
We accept that corporations have the right,
or the privilege to collect and correlate,
whereas in Europe, there's actually very strict
restrictions on -- you might be able to collect
this data over here, but you can't correlate
it to that over there.
In America, how often do you hear of a corporation
being defeated from doing that?
If you've ever passed a car with an automated
number plate reader, like on the street, then
you know that that -- you know, that car is
just sucking down number plates that it sees
it.
Might do it directly for law enforcement like
they do in England or it might just be agglomerated
into a distributed database using the idea
of distributed data collection, which they
then can sell to whoever for whatever purpose.
So not only is the issue of what data is collected
and is it controlled, but how is it collected?
Do you collect more than you need?
You know, how many times have you turned off
permissions for an app where like, I don't
think you need my contacts.
You're a picture-taking thing.
Also, which fields are being collected?
OK, thankfully we do have some restrictions
on that, like very few social messaging apps
are going to ask you about your sexual preference,
unless it's Grindr.
But you know, for the most part, we know that
some stuff that they're not supposed to do.
But our tolerance level for like clicking
yes is remarkably high and on the developer
side, who's going to tell the developer not
to collect more than you need?
Which should be the principle, right?
You know, collect what you need, don't collect
more than you do.
Because down the road, you know, all the hacks
that we have, etc., people can start correlating
data from multiple services, I mean let's
face it, no service is essentially unhackable.
You know, they might be less likely to be,
but I think the interference of hackers from
wherever in the current American election
is kind of showing us a new future in which,
yeah, just assume that data that you are collecting
as part of your algorithm or your database
might get out there and what might that mean
for the people whose data that is?
And similarly, what in society, where data
is missing, you know, what could be the plausible
reason for that when you know, the government
collects all kinds of other data, and of course
I'm talking about the horrific recent streak
of -- well, this is not recent, it's the discussion
about it is recent.
You know, the impunity by which the police
is able to act violently and kill members
of society, primarily African American, without
any real legal repercussions, and without
that even being recorded by society.
That absence of data isn't -- there's not
an accident.
You know, if they collect all your tax records,
but they happen to not collect data on like
potential ties between politicians and like
tax havens, like that wouldn't be a mistake.
That would be by design.
So there's multiple of these.
This is the counted, by the guardian.
Which again is ironic, which is a liberal
UK newspaper.
They've done a pretty good job.
They've had an open data record related to
data journalism which is exciting on its own.
But there are also some others, fatal encounters
is probably the most important one.
They started tracking around 2002 ... Ferguson,
which is not far from here, happened.
Fatal encounters formed the kernel for the
data collection for the Washington Post.
So if you're doing open data, your success
might be someone else's Pulitzer.
That might taste a little funny.
[laughter]
So the idea is that power comes with responsibility,
which is something that we know and in general
we accept this, but I think when you're developing
technology, the you know for the same reason
why drone pilots and fighter pilots in general
have like an easier time killing whoever,
than someone who has to do with it with bayonet
up close, like there's research that most
soldiers will not shoot a human being at like
less than 30 yards.
They will shoot in the air.
There will be a small percentage that will
actually shoot.
But if you're just operating some drone platform,
you know, you're at a great, great distance
and in the same way I would argue that the
distance that we have to the people that we
collect data on, for instance, if we're creating
apps, it kind of trivializes in the moment
the idea of what we're you know, what could
be the potential harmful implications for
them.
I have no doubt that the developers who wrote
that algorithm for prime risk assessment were
not necessarily bad people.
You know, maybe they're slightly leaning more
towards law and order, but I'm sure that they
think their crime assessment algorithm is
relevant.
The problem is, could, without transparency,
and first of all, you can ask is that ever
a relevant way of doing justice?
Do we want a drudge dread type of justice
where we have yes or no the moment you walk
in the door?
And if we do accept automated systems as part
of our crime system, how do we review them?
You know, what is the transparency aspect
when the algorithms are proprietary.
So I would say in general, you know, collect
only what you need, don't overstate your intentions,
don't assume that what works for you works
for everyone else and don't blame the algorithm.
By which I mean it's your fault, not the algorithm.
So acknowledging that you have bias or privilege
is not the same as admitting fault or guilt.
That's a very unproductive feeling, which
is, you know, a very reasonable thing to think.
Particularly if you're confronted with something
that you are not necessarily proud of.
But, you know, your intentions were good or
whatever.
But acknowledging that you have bias is acknowledging
that you're alive, that you're a human being,
like every human being has bias of one form
or another.
You know, you select your friends based on
who you like.
That's a bias.
If you select them based on, you know, skin
color, that's a slightly different bias, but
you know, they're related.
So again, they're both known unknowns and
unknown unknowns, so acknowledging the fact
that you might not know everything there is
to know is kind of a good place to start,
and when all else fails, apologize.
And make it a real apology, don't prevaricate
and say you know, we don't know how it was
calibrated, all that stuff.
But stereotypes in general are seductive because
they have an parent ability to explain behavior,
right, they reaffirm our beliefs about the
world and they allow us to extrapolation decisions
about people we meet.
Most of the time that's fun and easy.
All Europeans have this shared thing where
I meet a French person and I can be like you're
surely a snob, right and they could say back
to me, oh, you're a Norwegian, you're a dark,
depressive soul and I could be like yeah,
I'm not saying you have to eradicate the biases
from your life.
Just figure out when you should have them.
I'm willing to offend a French person and
I know there's French people in here but I
own that and so apologies in advance.
And finally one thing that comes up constantly
and when I talk to women who are important
researchers and creators within the field,
for instance I worked with this woman Madeline
Gannon and she works with robot arms, and
upon first meeting I said, so, you're a woman
in robotics, that's really not a useful phrase.
That implies that you're something that's
not the regular thing in robotics.
So expecting people who are potentially being
harmed or discriminated against to explain
to you what is happening or stopping you from
doing it, is kind of -- that's a really bad
solution.
You know, like when the -- all eyes in the
room turned to the one Norwegian guy in the
room and say, like, so how can we include
Norwegians in this conversation?
That shouldn't be mine to answer.
So to quote a good friend of mine, you can
either be the best or you can be the worst.
All right.
How are we on time?
We've got, that was 45, right?
ZEESHAN: You've got some time for questions.
>> I did have the talk like that I actually
like promised is also in here.
How many have implemented circle packing?
Not more?
How many computational geometry fans in the
room?
Oh, that's better.
Yeah, I heard some Martian cubes being mentioned.
So this is circle packing.
This is what you get when you just search
for circle packing.
This is circle packing architecture.
Architecture is great for looking at sort
of algorithms as creative cliches, because
they're just cycling through them really rapidly.
If you know what Grasshopper is, which is
like a patching based writing for Rino that's
a good CAD tool.
This is my circle packing project.
I can like claim, well, I did it in 2007,
you know, in this field that's like a long
time ago.
[laughter]
Voronoi, also very popular.
This will be in the PDF.
This is a fun one.
This is the grasshopper forums and it's a
request for quod to help them do what you
see on the right which of course is my work.
And I guess -- and inadvertent kudos, like
you know, the most sincere form of flattery
is copying?
I can't do this justice, I hope the justice
talk was worth it.
I find those examples terrifying partly because
I work with a lot of people who might be the
creators of these things.
That's why I talk about it from my perspective
that I'm terrified of being a creator of a
tool that's destructive.
One thing -- I should include another half
to complement that which would be the tools
that actually do the opposite that support
the people in taking back the power.
And so on and so forth.
And there are those tools.
But I think it's not going to happen on its
own.
Questions?
I have a remark.
From what I understand there is a new European
Union regulation coming up that is supposed
to make the algorithm for the creators to
be able to provide explanation for their decisions,
so it will be a pretty exciting change for
all the algorithm designers.
>> Yeah, that's like page rank.
Page rank is proprietary and maybe for good
reason.
I haven't followed the sort of the recent
politics in Europe, living in Brooklyn, but
in general, you know, like over here, when
Germany says to Facebook you're not allowed
to collect that data, you know, the media
here is like, look at those crazy Germans,
why shouldn't you be able to?
Anyone else?
Yup?
>> I was wondering if in your experience,
you had run across anyone, who had, you know,
noticed a problem and then corrected it in
some sense, like better requirements or better
testing or more --
>> I wish I had some great examples.
>> Can you repeat the question.
>> Yeah, the question is am I aware of anyone
who's figured out that like whatever service
they're working on has that kind of bias issue
and then corrected themselves.
I'd have to say I'm not aware of it.
I fervently hope that just like alien life
in the universe exists, I hope that it exists.
I would love to hear that story.
>> Airbnb is in the middle of working their
--
>> Oh, right.
>> So that there's less racial bias.
>> That's an interesting case, because Airbnb
and that other neighborhood watch service,
I don't remember the name of it, Next Door,
primarily the changes are more about terminology
and reporting and it's like -- I used to have
to argue to my students that the web page
design of Facebook is the same thing as like
designing like the house you're going to like
act in, but even that kind of stuff, which
is fairly trivial to even like imagine and
you'd wonder why they wouldn't do it, like,
in the first place, that stuff should get
done.
OkCupid is an interesting case there, where
you know, is everybody familiar with OkCupid?
It's like datalog, etc.
It's an interesting one because they have
a real dataset that represents dating.
The problem is they have one article which
primarily shows, like, who is preferred, you
know, as groups on OkCupid, but that's sort
of the problem.
I don't show that to students because I don't
want to reinforce in my students' head that
is how it is.
That is one of the problems with data collection.
You tend to believe that that's how it is.
And you are not necessarily considering what
are the affordances that might lead to to
be true.
I'm not saying you should have some didactic,
you know, part of OkCupid like encouraging
you to date along gender and racial lines,
that would be a little patronizing, but to
think that it is just true that there is that
divide is not understanding the data.
So yeah?
>> So to piggyback on this idea that we as
developers should really be thinking actively
about these questions, how much data do I
collect, what does it mean, I've kind of heard
this similar thought with do-good data for
social justice and they find that people just
don't understand the impacts of their data
or what kind of data they have.
Can you recommend any resources that are good
for people to digest perhaps as an introduction
to saying, these are actually the data.
I'm curious if there's anything you can hem
that can help start that discourse.
>> I can't recommend one offhand but I know
in the process of teaching one of the things
that I've found is teaching students about
data, using like an existing big dataset is
pretty much useless.
Make them travel like their own travel through
the city, that gets creepy real fast.
There was someone who actually did that at
SVA, where they collected the moves app, they
collected all the moves data for all the students
in the class and sure enough, they found out
who was dating, that stuff gets creepy because
of what you can see, and most people accept
in the abstract that sure, you might be able
to see this, but I think most users are simply
not aware of the power of it.
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
>> Any final fun exciting questions?
I think I need to lighten up that talk.
[laughter]
>> I mean it's real, but it's a little -- for
the record I should say I personally don't
develop any social justice tools, I'm not
saying that, like, I know how to fix this.
All I know is I have a lot of people who are
very good people and very smart developing
tools, and I'm -- yeah, kind of terrified
of seeing where this goes.
There have been multiple -- there are actually
some good examples where -- there's a tool
called flood watch from the office for creative
research which helps you track like online,
you know, tracking software, etc., that's
one of those areas where there is quite a
lot of research.
Ironically privacy in data has become sort
of the cool macho thing, which is like -- which
is ironic, because that's actually a fairly
easy thing to track.
Bias is a way more powerful and harder thing
to track.
So Adam Harvey who I showed you earlier is
he's like really in the privacy thing.
In an interesting way.
Along with that project where you kind of
obscure your face from a facial recognition,
he also has an anti-drone burka, which is
essentially a heat reflective material which
does make you invisible to infrared cameras,
it's pretty amazing.
Recommend looking at it
ZEESHAN: Thank you very much.
>> All right.
Thank you.
[applause]