my name is Justine and I work on building
network systems, but this talk applies to,
ooh, this is pretty echoey.
I'm going to move this down a little bit.
I think this talk applies to pretty much anybody
who builds software, and in this talk I'm
super-open to questions and conversation.
In fact, in graduate networking classes these
papers are sort of notorious for leading to
arguments and discussion which is part of
why these are two papers that I really, really
love.
>> OK, so we've all had the experience of
working with our piece of code and we start
talking about the features that we want and
at some point we start thinking about how
other people or services are going to use
our widget.
And we usually do this by implementing APIs
to talk to these other services.
This is actually a very short narrow view
of our piece of software in the world.
In reality it's a small part of this big ecosystem.
There are other service that is our widgets
talk to directly, maybe some extensions up
and down the stack.
Maybe you're running on one of multiple different
platforms that you support and maybe many,
many layers away there's some human user.
[laughter]
So today we're going to talk about design
philosophy and we're going to talk about principles
for thinking about the world outside of your
widget, even and especially if your widget
is kind of abstract, far down the stack, and
invisible from the average human.
This is David Clark.
And many people in the networking community
sort of worship him.
He's a research scientists at MIT and well
deserving title, Internet Philosopher.
Most of the seminal work on this topic is
due to things that he was involved with.
And to I recommended three papers for the
Papers We Love community to read and upon
realizing that I only have one hour to speak
I actually cut one.
So these are the papers we're going to talk
about.
All three involve Clark as a coauthor.
As a side note, I met David Clark at a conference
once, he told me he liked my talk.
It was great.
[laughter]
Anyway, before we dig in the papers, I'm going
to give some background and what systems folks
mean when they talk about laird architectures,
because we're going to talk a lot about layers,
and we're going to focus especially on the
internet because that's what I and David Clark
work on an for those of you who internet all
day, just hang with me as I go through some
material we're familiar with it.
So we talked about modular.
And they fit together in layers.
One of these is the internet model we have
here.
At the bottom we have our physical layer,
this is the thing that turns electricity and
wire into bits.
The link layer is all about turning bits on
a wire into messages, you've probably heard
about ethernet.
When machines are talking to each other an
a wire, they're using ethernet.
The network layer is the internet protocol.
It's the thing that gives us the addresses
that allow us to talk across great distances.
And the transport layer is the thing that's
concerned with connections between hosts.
Often the transport layer is responsible for
resending data that has been lost or making
sure it doesn't get corrupted or reordered.
And at the very top we have the part that
your average Joe actually see, the tip of
the iceberg speaking.
Web browsers, email, chat clients, etc.
The way these pieces fit together I'll show
through a demonstration, so here I have me
and Zeeshan, and I'm going to send him this
sweet paper in a PDF file.
At the application layer, I load up my PDF.
My application is going to send this down
to the transport layer, which establishes
a connection and converts it into packets.
These packets, it's going to assign some sequence
numbers, it's using these sequence numbers
to make sure that things don't get lost or
reordered.
These packets get handed down to the network
layer where we put an IP address on them,
that is how we know where to send the data
and then down at the link layer we hand these
packetized into the physical layer which takes
in the bits and ships them across some wires.
At the other side the physical layer hands
this back up to the link layer, reconstructs
our packets, hands them back up to the network
layer, now we know, OK, this is really me,
these are the packets sent to me.
The transport layer we double-check, is everything
in order, have I lost any pieces and then
we glue everything back together and hand
it back up to the application layer where
we can reconstruct or PDF.
Sweet.
So the internet is just one example of a modular
layered system.
Components are implemented independently with
layers between them.
Different layers may have multiple implementations.
For example, you have wifi versus wired internet
as your physical layer, and different layers
may offer slightly different APIs and different
functionality.
For example, TCP and UDP are both transport
protocols, but TCP guarantees that nothing
will get lost and everything shows up in order.
UDP doesn't give you any such guarantees,
and to make your end to end system work, data
has to pass through multiple layers, we're
plugging all these components together to
make our big internet.
Now, networks aren't the only systems with
layers.
People in the storage systems draw diagrams
that look pretty familiar to me.
You have your application, your and then things
get written out to your disk or your solid
state drive.
Virtualization, also another context where
we run into layers, your hardware has a kernel
on top of it, your kernel is running a hypervisor
on type of it, that hypervisor has some guest
kernels and those guest kernels have user
space on top of them again.
So there's layers all around us.
So today's questions when we're talking about
design philosophy is how to not get myopic
about living in our own little layer.
We need to think about the outside world and
not just about the APIs that we expose to
the components we're talking to directly.
We need to look all the way up and down the
stack, and even up to the users on top.
So, further ado, got some background now and
we can talk about paper No. 1.
Papers called end to end arguments and systems
design, it appeared in November, 1984, three
years before I was born.
Appeared in ACM transactions on computer systems
which was kind of a big deal and it's one
of the very influential papers that people
tend to read in all sorts of graduate systems
class, network systems, databases, etc.
And the paper starts out with an example that
you should now be familiar with, now that
I've shown you how the internet works, and
it involves an oversimplified layer system.
We only have three components.
We have a file system, a program, and a network,
and notice that we've now sign p seen diagrams
of file systems and networks and we know that
each of these components has lots of layers
inside of it.
We've collapsed all of that down into this
one block.
So in this example we're looking at a careful
file transfer.
Program A calls upon the file system and the
file system passes it to the file transfer
program in fixed-size blocks, these fixed-size
blocks are happened down to the communication
program.
The communication system is going to transmit
the tile using some communication protocol
that involves splitting the data into packets.
The data communication network moves the packets
from computer A to computer B, and it at host
B, the communication program removes the packets
from the communication channel and hands the
contained data up to the file transfer application,
the part that operates within B. At host B,
the file transfer program asks the file program
to write the data to disk.
Done.
Problem.
What if Zeeshan later reads the file and finds
that it's corrupted?
What could have gone wrong?
Well, it turns out a lot of things can go
wrong.
The paper lists a long list of reasons.
You could have problems in the disk storage
system, bit error, whatever.
Storage, you could have problems in the file
system, the file transfer program, some buffer
overrun in the data communications system,
some error in copying.
You could have some bug in the processer,
a bit flip in memory.
The communications system might drop packets,
have corruption, deliver a packet more than
once.
This is actually a thing that the internet
does sometimes.
Either of the host might just crash while
you're in the middle of it.
The question is, how do we redesign our system
to make sure the file doesn't get corrupted
and to start we need to know where do we make
these changes?
Do the we change it up to the file system?
Do we do them in the program?
Do we do them in the network?
This is what the end to end argument is meant
to help us with and I've added in some red
text that I think makes it more readable.
The end to end argument goes like this: If
the function in question can completely and
correctly be implemented with the knowledge
and the help of the application standing at
the endpoints of the communication system,
then, providing that question function as
a feature of the communication system or lower
layer, is not possible.
However, sometimes an incomplete version of
the function provided by the communication
system may be useful as a performance enhancement.
So let's look at the first part.
The if, then, and forget about the however
for a while.
If you could implement your function at the
end, at the top layer, do it there.
Don't do it somewhere down low.
Here's why.
Let's say that I went ahead and just made
a perfectly reliable communication network.
I had introduced some sort of network coding
or acknowledgment at the network layer to
make sure nothing ever got dropped or corrupted
on the wire.
Well, if we go back to our long list of things
that can go wrong, I'm just circling the components
that can have problems, not the actual problems
that happen.
Fixing our errors at this low layer here actually
only fix things for the communications system.
It doesn't fix anything going wrong in your
processer, it doesn't fix anything going wrong
in your disk, it doesn't fix bugs in your
code.
So it just wasn't very helpful.
The paper then proposes an alternative better
solution which they call end to end check
and retry.
Here's the idea.
Our sender is going to read the file in its
check sum from disk and then it's going to
verify the file in the check sum and make
sure they add up.
Then we send both the file and the check sum.
Everything proceeds exactly the same as B
packets down, they get sent across the network
and at the other end when Zeeshan receives
the file he's going to write the file to disk
along with its check sum and then read it
back and verify that the two match up.
If they match up, we know we're done, end
to end, the whole thing is complete and we
got the right file.
And if they don't match up, Zeeshan will go
back and ask me, can you just resend the file,
something went wrong.
Note that checking at the end all the way
past the finish line we'll be able to catch
if anything went wrong anywhere along the
line.
So we actually would have to do this check
no matter what.
And if we're doing it here, why bother doing
it at a lower layer?
>> It's usually redundant.
And second of all, they argue that it can
often cause confusion and they give an example
of a communications system at MI where they
kept seeing corrupted files.
Turns out there was a memory error, but everybody
just assumed, well, our communication system
is reliable, so we don't have to check anything
at higher layers.
The paper then goes on to suggest other places
that the end to end protocol can be useful.encryption
is a really great example here.
You still need end to end encryption, because
just because your VPN offers encryption, it
doesn't mean that the person at the other
end can't see your data.
You need ACS at the higher layer.
You will you see this played out in the earlier
days of the internet.
People said the internet needs to be real
reliable.
Today's internet doesn't do any of those things.
Transport protocols at the endpoints of communication,
double-check if something got lost or corrupted
and resend if it got missing.
So, there's one caveat to this implement everything
at the endpoints argument.
Sometimes as a performance optimization you
really do want to implement things at the
lower layer of the system, rather than -- at
same time as you're implementing at the higher
layer and that's only when you really, really
need that optimization.
Consider if all of our loss was really happening
at the network layer, and that loss rate was
really high, the higher the loss rate in the
network, the less likely it is that our whole
PDF, end to end, is actually going to make
it all the way through.
If we have these five packets and each one
has a 28% chance of loss, that's a really
high chance, 65% that the file wouldn't make
it all the way through.
So as a performance optimization, we might
want to bake in some reliability at the network
layer, but we should do that redundantly,
and without forgetting that we have to do
it end to end, as well.
Anybody have any other thoughts on where this
kind of thing plays out?
Where you can do a redundant performance optimization
in your system?
No?
Wifi is a great example.
Wifi redundantly does retransmission.
That's because wifi can get really lossy when
somebody turns a microwave on.
OK, so far this has been pretty dry.
What the heck is this classic networking argument
that grad students argue about.
There's nothing really to argue about here.
Well, that's because the paper, in like the
very last section, turns the argument a little
bit and tweaks it.
And they make a stronger argument.
They say, and in many cases while it's not
just a waste of time to build things at low
layers and it's not just confusing, it's actually
really harmful to the internet.
Whoa, OK.
Here's how that plays out.
Well, one way to add reliability is to add
some extra bits, like network coding.
But that also means that you have slightly
less bandwidth coming through your network
layer, you've taken up some extra bits.
Another way to do that is to use acknowledgments,
and to withhold packets until you've got all
the data.
If something goes missing, you wait for a
retransmit, and once you've got everything,
you pass it up to the application layer, which
adds more latency.
So this is really not helpful for an application
like Skype.
With Skype, I really don't want my packets
showing up late.
As a matter of fact, I don't care if all of
them show up.
I don't care, because I'd much rather have
a small blip than receiving everything 30
seconds late but knowing that I got all of
it.
So this shows how some applications can actually
be constrained by extra functionality that
they don't want.
In our Skype case it's that having better
latency and bandwidth is more important than
getting all the data.
So what's good in one context isn't good for
everything.
This paper that came out in 1984 was oddly
prescient because in the internet today this
problem is a huge deal.
Here's one example that's super-common in
network enterprises networks today.
Everyone is expected to run antivirus to protect
them from bad guys on the internet.
We've used the endpoints to protect us from
badness.
But some people don't always keep their computers
updated and as an optimization, many network
administrators want to filter traffic based
on what they suspect is malicious and nonmalicious,
to protect these users.
And they do this by observing what traffic
usually leads to attacks and what usually
doesn't and they tend to be pretty conservative
about this.
Web traffic and email, it's usually OK.
Start seeing IRC, that stuff is dangerous,
strange port numbers, not so good.
So it's really common to put some box in your
network that enforces this.
Only allow web traffic and email and maybe
that's historically all you've seen your users
use.
But then somebody has some cool new app that
runs over some high-number port number.
It's perfectly safe but it isn't HTTP or email
and now it can't get through our network because
we've baked in a security optimization into
the low layers of the system.
So here's a paper that came out just a couple
of years ago, and it proposes that we should
now use HTTP for everything, they say that
when you have your new app nowadays, firewalls
block pretty much everything except HTTP so
you either go around to every network administrator
in the world or you can just build arbitrary
programs.
So this whole paper is how to build random
programs that look like HTTP web traffic that
aren't web traffic at all, so despite the
good and useful security benefits of our firewalls
and our IDSs, they've constrained what applications
are or aren't allowed in networks, in a way
that's not great.
Here's another example, from the real world.
Your iPhone usually connects to web services
over LTE or 3G and this is what we imagine
it looks like, but in practice, many ISPs
insert consent caches to make things load
faster for you, so they're keeping copies
of frequently fetched data and instead of
you collecting all the weight of their web
server, you're connecting to their cache.
I but this problem arose when some folks in
the UK started designing a new transport protocol.
They called it multipath TCP and the idea
here was to send some of your traffic over
your LTE connection and some traffic over
wifi, so you get better bandwidth.
And then these caches looked at it and said,
this looks like a TCP connection, but half
the packets are missing.
What do I do with this?
Now, they could have just said, OK I'll let
it route through, I won't perform any optimizations,
but instead they just blocked it and the whole
thing broke.
So this this paper the multipath TCP authors
talked about challenges they faced when they
tried to use this multipath protocol on the
public internet.
It just turns out that all of these optimizations
that normally had made things faster were
causing problems for their new protocol.
Luckily this story does have a very happy
ending, the authors developed some work-and.
And multipath TVP now works in your iPhone
so that's great.
And this is where grad students start to go
off the rails, the internet is hopeless.
I think most of us have some sort of story
where we were being blocked or filtered, we
had a hotel that wouldn't let us use SSH.
What's going on?
So I'm just going to recap the arguments I've
heard from the end to end argument.
The basic argument, the thing that's not so
controversial.
In you could implement functionality completely
at endpoints, do it there.
Don't do it at a lower layer.
It saves on redundant work and it can avoid
confusion, but you might, and sometimes you
really want to, make exceptions for performance
optimizations.
Then there's the strong argument, you should
really avoid putting unneeded functionality
in lower layers of your system altogether.
It's harmful and as many have foretold it's
going to doom innovation on the internet forever.
Extra functionality at lower layers constrains
how applications are designed at higher layers
so we should just avoid it.
OK, that's the end to end argument.
Any questions up to here?
Yes.
Do they talk at all about opt out functionality?
>> So they'll talk a little bit about that.
So the question is, do they talk about opt-out
functionality, making sure that if you add
extra functionality, can you optimize it.
In this next paper we'll get a little bit
into that.
>>
[inaudible]
Verification -- if you implemented verification
at the file system there, wouldn't that have
the same problem of constraining -- according
to the Strong argument of constraining behavior,
if you were check summing at the file system.
>> It's true that I might have some application,
so the question here is this end to end communication
argument really assumes that the network is
at the bottom and that the file system is
somehow high lea and we should be checking
things in the file system.
But it's true that in other people's diagrams
of the world the file system is down here
at the bottom and maybe I have some app that's
reading lots and lots of data really fast
and it doesn't have time to do verification
check sums.
These questions are super tricky.
That's a great point.
I'd never thought of that one.
OK.
>> So we've given some good arguments for
why you shouldn't bake things into lower layers
and then we've said that for some optimizations
you probably really going to want to sometimes
bake things into lower layers, but it could
be harmful.
It might not be harmful.
Sometimes it's helpful.
So who decides what optimizations and constraints
are OK to employ at core layers of our systems.
>> 20 years David Clark comes out with his
internet philosopher crown -- that crown is
not real but I would like to give him -- and
he says the internet is not a single happy
family of people dedicated to universal packet
carriage.
What?
And here are some examples he gives us of
our very unhappy family.
People want to talk in private over the network
and the government wants to build in some
wiretaps at the bottom layers of our system.
Conservative governments put their users behind
firewalls.
Users not only don't like this, but they actually
just route around it, they install VPNs.
ISPs tell us you can have one host on this
network connection, and we are enforcing this
by giving you one IP address and everyone's
house has a network address translator with
lots of laptops behind it.
So in the tussle paper, the authors call these
arguments tussles.
It's the ongoing contention between parties
with conflicting interests surrounding a mechanism.
Different parties adapt a mix of mechanisms
to achieve conflicting goals and others respond
by adapting the mechanisms to push back.
We need to emphasize the term mechanism here,
because this is a really interesting conflict
in that the mechanism is both the object of
the argument and it's something that pushes
back on people and makes them change their
behavior.
>> Here's a recent example.
Back in 2014, there was some controversy about
iCloud.
Apple had this great iCloud data storage system
that allowed you to back up your data to the
cloud.
It was pretty cool.
But the government wanted to access that data.
They wanted to subpoena information that people
were storing in iCloud.
We had two users, we had all of us who wanted
to use it for storage and we had our government
who thought great, we can use this for legal
investigations, but Apple questioned whether
or not the government's use of their customers'
information was in the public interest.
So they expanded their encryption feature
with the release of iOS 8.
So even Apple itself wouldn't be able to unlock
it.
The government
didn't like this.
They tried to get Apple to change it again
by developing a new back door to get them
to access the data during the San Bernardino.
This tussle is still going on.
It didn't end.
The government got somebody else to build
the back door.
But this will not be the last we'll hear about
this mechanism companies are or aren't allowed
to implement and what restrictions they can
bake into those to stop the government from
acting on it.
So to describe these arguments, the tussles
talk about an actor model for tussle.
Basically everybody has their own goals and
desires that everyone is constrained by the
system that they're using, and they're trying
to use the system to compete -- to achieve
their own competing desires.
So here we have a designer, Claire, whose
design is constraining her users, Dahlia and
Zeeshan, so Claire designs, the system imposes
some constraints on them, and Zeeshan and
Dahlia are adapting, building work-and, so
they're asking for a back door to be built,
they are a designing a VPN to get around it,
maybe they're moving to another service.
So in response to these work-arounds and adaptations,
we go through this process over and over again.
Now, note that these redesigns can sometimes
extend restrictions or they can actually help
the work-around.
I like to think of when people, you remember
when we used to write RT in the retweets and
then copy-paste somebody's retweet?
This was because there was a lack of ability
to.
Twitter noticed this work-around and thought
that's a great work around.
That's awesome and now they have this nice
little retweet button.
And there's an open question about this process.
Whether the tussle is going to be driven out
of the system, actors are all going to be
forced to align, everybody is going to agree,
hold hands, go home, or whether this sort
of semi-stable dynamic where we just keep
adapting and changing and adapting and changing,
is going to persist forever.
So back to design philosophy.
We're sitting here thinking about our wig
ets, we're now aware of tussle.
We're 11 layers down the stack, no one has
ever heard of with what we're building.
And we need to think about how do we impact
the world around us?
How do we design for tussle?
There's two ways to think about designing
for tussle.
One is to think about staying out of the tussle,
just let people's fights play out agnostically,
you stay out of the fight, your system is
it pure.
Another way is to design to influence the
tussle.
Take a stand.
Now, the paper is a little schizophrenic on
this issue.
It starts out talking about how you should
design to stay out of the tussle, build these
beautiful agnostic systems and then it pivots
towards the end and it talks about designing
to influence the tussle.
So let's first talk about the design principles
that they talk about to stay out of the tussle
and where they start to pivot after that.
So first they say, design for variation outcome.
Do not design as if to dictate the outcome.
Stay out of the way.
And they propose two rules, two design principles
for us to follow.
Modularity, and designing for choice.
I'll talk about each of these.
First modular design.
Now, my description of modular design is to
make somebody else' decision, not yours and
they give two examples.
One of bad modularity and one of good modularity.
Bad modularity is DNS.
The DNS is the name of the service.
That's it.
For the world at large, the DNS is a trademark,
it's someone's name.
So this international technical organization,
who managed service IDs is now embroiled in
trademark disputes in every country in the
world.
Here's poor
Carly Fiorna, who forgot to buy her own domain
name.
We've conflated the idea of service ID and
trademark, we shouldn't have been in this
game in the first place.
Here's good modularity.
Internet quality of service many.
The way it works is pretty simple, here we
have our IP header and we've put in a couple
of bits.
The higher the number, the less important
we assume you are.
So alternatively, we could have removed these
bits all together, to save on bandwidth we're
using lets bits and that's it great.
And then we would bake into the system, all
right, failed calls are the most important
and video games are the least important.
But then we have baked into the system a choice
about what is or isn't important and that's
not really our job.
Instead, the people who instead QOS said it
should be up to the community or the enterprise
in that region.
Those communities can decide for themselves
what they do or don't think is important and
they'll just tell us, they'll give us an ordered
ranking so this is good modularity here.
Now, the other principle they present is designing
for choice.
Letting the user decide.
How many guys are from the EU?
Anybody?
Yeah, OK.
You recognize this screen?
So when you install windows in the US, you
get Internet Explorer, that's it, that's the
only option and the EU said this is anticompetitive,
this is not fair, you have not designed for
choice.
In the EU when you installed Windows, you
get a screen that lets you choose what web
browser do you want?
And then you just choose whichever.
And they install that one for you.
Designing for choice I think is a little bit
easier to reason about than modularity.
We're sort of used to thinking about modularity.
We all have different email providers, we
can run different operating systems, regardless
of the hardware that we run.
Sometimes it's not quite clear, what's the
difference between designing modularly and
designing for choice.
And I think the big difference is really the
context in which you apply them in.
Until modular design you're concerned about
a global decision that has to be made for
everyone.
For example, those QLS bits.
I know plenty of people who would say that
I think that my video game traffic is way
more important than 911 calls.
I do not want to let them design for choice.
There has to be a global decision made somewhere
but our architecture that we've designed,
shouldn't assume what that choice is.
You should outsource it to something that
represents the decision of the community or
the company or the place where it's being
deployed.
Designing for choice is what you do when the
decision doesn't need to be global.
Where it's really totally fine that to each
his own, everybody does things differently.
So the paper goes on to discuss another -- a
number of other places where tussles come
into play.
Here are some examples: Some ISPs ban users
from hosting web servers and so they block
port 80.
User solution?
Obviously just run your web server hon a different
port.
Residential broadband access is another place
where they were oddly prescient, here they
are back in 2005, saying today we have about
6,000 dialup providers in the US and people
have lots of choice about their provider but
we're worried about broadband and today.
The internet today has not designed for choice
when I get to choose between which providers
I have.
Trust is another place where tussles play
out.
People want to talk to me, but I doesn't want
them to communicate with me.
I set up firewalls, I set up filters, I set
up antivirus.
The internet is open by default, but how should
this mechanism in the middle decide who to
listen to?
Me who says don't talk to me or the person
who's sending me all the spam.
Anybody think of any other systems designed
by choice any time you're done your own work?
Electrical grid.
>> Electrical grid.
Tell me more.
>> We're starting to see where you can choose
your electricity provider, but the grid is
a utility.
>> That's fantastic, I didn't know about that
example.
That's great.
>> Similar to the internet.
>> Did everybody hear that?
The electrical grid?
Yeah, that's on the captions.
Cool.
>> OK.
So facing all these challenges, the tussle
paper gives us some pretty stern commands.
After saying you should stay out of the fight,
you should design for choice, you should make
it somebody else's decision, they then say
there's no such thing as value-neutral designs,
don't assume that you know the answer.
You weren't designing a playing field but
at the same time you can't be value-neutral.
So here's the editors' bias.
Their bias is that openness, choice, and tussle
are good and they're reacting to a lot of
pressures to end choice in the way that we
build our infrastructure.
There are app stores that restrict what apps
you can and can't install on your iPhone or
Android or Kindle.
There are protocols to standardization efforts
that have been undermined by governments that
want to restrict strong cryptography.
There are firewalls, IDSs, and filters that
both protect us from badness and implement
censoring, filter out competition and downgrade
undesirable traffic and typically these are
corporations and governments who want to control
what's going on.
So when the authors of this paper say to design
to stay out of tussle, they also are simultaneously
telling us influence the tussle in that everyone
gets a say.
Don't bake in features that you're pushed
to do by the government or a corporation or
some user who you really like.
Let it play out in the world, in the community.
They then return to the end to end argument
and they say, look, sometimes you're going
to have to make some decision, you're going
to have to bake some optimizations or features
down into that network layer that are going
to strain the rest of the world.
Evolution and enhancement of existing, mature
applications is inevitable but you should
always be worried about new applications and
new use cases and keeping the net open and
transparent for new applications should be
the most important goal.
>> And the most that we can do is to protect
maturing application is to bias the tussle.
To bias the tussle in terms of continuing
to play out, rather than stagnating and coming
up with some locked-down design that only
does one thing that one person has allowed.
Yeah, David Clark.
[laughter]
So back to you and your widget.
I hope that you're now armed with some design
principles, you can look at end-to-end system
design to implement complex functionality
at high layers of your system and keep those
core layers open and flexible.
Let multiple options be available to your
users and design modularly, so that your system
is agnostic to which decision is made and
different communities can make their own choices
about what is or isn't appropriate to bake
into the lower layers of the system.
Now, fur if you're interested in reading more
on this, first of all there's the paper that
I downgraded.
The design philosophy of the DARPA internet
protocols.
Among other things, it's really interesting
to just look at what motivated them at the
time.
They were super-worried about nuclear bombs
destroying the internet and not worried about
privacy or cryptography at all.
Very strange.
There are also the other two papers I talked
about that reflect on how the network, the
internet today, is constraining application
development.
This is HTTP action the narrow waist of the
internet and is it still possible to extend
TCP paper.
And finally a very controversial paper which
I think is very cool is a paper that says
that the evolution of laird protocol stacks
leads to an hour-glass-shaped architecture.
There are a lot of protocols that we use at
the physical layer, there are a lot of application
that is we run but there's only one internet
protocol.
Why don't we have many?
This paper tries to answer that question.
So at the end of the day, going back to your
super-widget, remember: Are you giving your
users choice or are you adding constraints?
Thanks very much.
[applause]
>> Hello, thanks for the talk.
In the paper, they kind of criticize DNS and
say that it's bad for trademarks or something.
>> Yes.
>> What sort of concretely positively, like,
are they suggesting?
>> So they don't suggest an alternative.
Which I found really annoying reading the
paper.
I actually spent some time trying to imagine.
You could have some sort of opaque service
ID and then yet another layer of indirection,
where you could subscribe to Google's naming
trademarking service and that would be relevant
to the US and in China they would have their
own trademarking service that would map to
those service IDs, it seems a little hokey
to me, actually, everything I could think
of to separate those too, was a little eh,
iffy.
>> Thank you for this excellent talk.
The -- I certainly see the value and the philosophy
behind pushing things up to the end, but how
do you address, for something like say TCP/IP,
the sharing network that we hope will launch
this year, if there's something that you know
every application is going to need to do these
things, even if you say we could solve this,
but we still have to worry about corrupted
hard drives, so we're still going to have
to do the end-to-end check but in turns of
trying to get a thousand applications getting
everything right?
>> Well, so what operating systems do today
on this front is actually very nice.
Your OS knows about it.
CP, knows about UDP and your application is
not reimplementing TCP every time.
The communication layer at the bottom isn't
making the decision for you, so they've designed
for choice in that way.
They've pushed it to the end points but they've
pushed it in such a way that applications
can plug and play which component they want.
>> Not all the way up.
>> Yeah, so not all the way up.
Into software.
>>
ZEESHAN:    Any other questions?
>> Great, thanks.