I'm with PDFdata.io, I'm not going to get
into anything related to what that does, this
is not a sales pitch, but while I'm up here
I feel I must take a minute to recognize how
lucky I am to be here, as we all are, and
maybe take a moment to recognize those outside
those four walls that struggle to survive.
Thank you.
So programming data for display.
And what does this mean?
To really crudely characterize what we do
and what we're interested in, we do computation,
right?
And how might you think about that?
You get things coming into our world of computers,
through all sorts of sensors and human input
and machines talking to each other, computation
and communication of all sorts happen in between
and at the other end you have some kind of
output, some kind of result and the output
that I'm talking about right now is display,
obviously one of the essential mediums with
which we have to perceive these sorts of results,
and we're all very interested and very immediate
feedback from the sorts of work that we do
with our computers, as you might have seen
previously with the visualizations of the
keys with that spirals of tonality display
and animated visualization is a special way
to have the data that we're performing.
But it wasn't always like this where we could
have things twirling around on screen.
All through the prior decades of course we
have had a lot of mediums for displaying the
data and information and results of computation
from telegraphs and teletypes through all
sorts of dynamic displays, especially during
the Cold War motivated a lot of this development,
especially through air traffic control and
simulations research for vector displays and
then raster displays, but also printing has
been around for hundreds of years, and one
of the things that so many people throughout
the computer revolution were concerned about
was how to distribute the results of computation
and put tools into the hands of as many people
as possible, so that you could have modern
equivalents to the movable type press essentially
and so fax machines for example were a huge,
you know, formational input to PDF and all
sorts of page description languages that were
sort of percolating around in the '60s, '70s,
and '80 as computation power made it possible
to relate with information from your computer
in ways that were richer than teletype.
And there's an interesting story of how CAD
and CAM systems are a variety of display that
happens to manifest itself through -- and
it has correlation to 3D printing as well.
Just to sort of set some ground terms, what
page description language means is any characterization
of a layout of a page that's more efficient
or expressive than a simple bitmap.
So if you're familiar with bitmap graphics
or rasters, you might have a 1440 by whatever
bitmap, and that's sufficient to describe
what's on my laptop screen, perhaps, but that's
obviously not sufficient to describe what
you can print through a high resolution offset
printer, or a vector-based plotter, and so
there have been progressively more capable
page description languages over the past 40
years, essentially, trying to tackle this
problem of how do you describe what some set
of data as a result of computations or communications
should look on a page or a screen or on a
plotter, and other media, but in a way that
is independent of that medium.
So there are dozens and dozens of documented
page description languages, you can go on
Wikipedia to find references for a variety
of them.
These are some interesting ones I'll talk
about a little bit.
And all of them are trying to characterize
a page and something besides draw a pixel
here, then draw a pixel here and draw a pixel
here, etc., etc., obviously not practical,
even today, never mind back in 1978.
So I'm going to sort of going out an a limb
a little bit and say that ASCII may have been
one of the first page description languages
and this isn't talked about in any of the
Wikipedia page or any of the modern literature
about page description languages because it
is so primitive of a medium, but these first
32 control characters here make possible the
-- make it possible to force an output devices,
like a teletype to render a set of data in
a way that is visually pleasing, practically
consumable, and so on, so for example, fixed-width
tabular data like this was commonplace for
centuries, essentially, where you had first,
you know, lead movable type printing presses
being used to produce tables like this for
newspaper consumption and things like that,
and then on to, you know, teletype printers
that produced displays of tabular data for
efficient viewing and consumption by humans
in a way that we can understand this data.
Outside of this kind of visualization, because
it is a visualization, understanding this
data would be extremely laborious, right?
And it's only because of the control characters
that were baked into ASCII, for example, there
are plenty of other competitors, but it has
these control characters that allow the printhead
at the time, to move forward a space, move
back a space, move down, run to the next sheet
of paper, etc.
Thereby allowing an author of a program to
fully control the materialized view, so to
speak, of a set of data.
And so as demands increased over the years
and various considerations drove development
for more time, essentially, we got to the
use of CRTs and vector displays for both realtime
-- this is actually an asteroids game that's
being implemented on top of an oscilloscope,
but exactly the same technology was used originally
to implement air defense systems, air traffic
control systems, and hear video games and
all sorts of realtime simulations like planetariums
back in the 60s, '70s, and '80s.
You want to be able
to include raster images.
So you can produce it onto a printer or other
output device.
And then probably the hardest nut to crack,
so to speak, in the history of page description
languages is text and typography.
Not just because of -- not just because of
-- there are so many factors, obviously,
[laughter]
So with both vector graphics and rasters,
the domain is very well defined and constrained,
right?
So if you want to draw asteroids, I know what
you need to do.
You need to describe that I want to draw a
line here and a line here and a line here,
etc., etc., to produce the, you know, vector
representations of your asteroids and spaceship
or you know, nuclear missiles or whatever
you happen to be doing.
Likewise, raster images, an artist produces
these laboriously by hand and they need to
be ferried along to whatever is going to be
doing the document.
Text and typography, on the other hand, these
are an enduring role throughout the construction
of a document and throughout the maintenance
of a document.
There is this notion of fonts which honestly
didn't exist prior to the more sophisticated
page description languages likes Postscript
and as you get no, if you remember the ASCII
chart there, there's only 127 code points
compared to for example, unicode today.
So these are a lot of different challenges
that page description languages have to cope
with and the history of the most successful
one, which happens to be PDF, is sort of littered
with the inventors of it learning along the
way how to cope with these particular challenges.
So just a little bit of sort of thumbnail
history, there was this company called Evans
and Sutherland that in 1968, I believe was
founded to custom produce systems for realtime
simulation and CAD/CAM systems, so they built
the projector systems in planetariums, and
also the very high precision mechanical canons
through computer aided machinery and the way
they did that is they used an internally developed
page description language where the page was
the set or the operators over the quote-unquote
page were a set of motions that a drill head
or a router might make on a block of aluminum
in order to produce a particular artifact.
It was all the same set of fundamental technologies
beings whether they were, you know, joking
on the sealing of a planetarium or producing
a cog for a machine.
So a couple of fellows, Chuck Geschke and
John Warnock worked at Evans and Sutherland
for a number of years and went off in the
mid '70s off to Xerox Park where they helped
to develop all kinds of things there including
interpress.
It was essentially bytecode, so if you think
of the production of a set of vector graphics,
like I said, you want to put your pen down
somewhere and you want to draw a line, 20
coordinate points this way and 10 down, and
then along this way, 10Up and 12 right and
an arc of a particular, using a particular
set of parameters.
Those were all encoded using bytecodes that
were incredibly efficient and very necessary
given the space and computational constraints
at the time.
We're again, talking about, you know, 1978
or so.
Lower is that John Warnock
was upset.
In 1970s, dollars it was a billion-dollar
company, producing printing systems and they
were using -- they would build a new page-description
language for every printer that they produced.
Obviously an incredibly laborious thing.
And interpress was John and Chuck's attempt
to make a device-independent output medium.
So you could take the same interpress file
and send it to a plotter, and a bitmap display
and a laser printer, which they were experimenting
with at Xerox, and have reasonable interpretations
of that page description to the, you know,
highest degree of fidelity that each device
allowed.
So they were frustrated with Xerox might being
able to commercialize that and so they formed
their own company called Adobe where they
produced Postscript.
Postscript ended up being baked into the first
laser writer that Adobe and Apple essentially
coproduced and that's essentially what set
up desktop publishing and the consumerization
of printing around publishing and design and
all of that and I just described it in about
20 seconds, but the set of technical feats
that were necessary are really astounding,
because prior to Postscript and laser writer,
I was talking about text and typography a
second ago, there were, you know, a set of
6 fonts that each computer happened to come
with if you were lucky.
I remember I had an Omega as a kids and it
literally had six fonts.
They were hard-coded bitmap fonts.
You had what you had available to you and
there was no such thing as going and getting
a new font that would look nice in your community
flyer or whatever.
In the process of developing Postscript they
developed vector-based fonts and ways to describe
those in an output-method-independent way
and a way to encode those for different computing
plat forms, including DOS and Apple IIs and
the Macintosh eventually, etc.
And then as a refinement to Postscript and
I'll talk a little bit about Postscript again
still, they developed PDF at Adobe and the
first version was developed in 1983, I believe,
and has developed over time to really saturate
the set of use cases that people have for
display and printing technology, and describing
what needs to be displayed on any output device
in an independent fashion.
So this is Papers We Love.
Sadly, as an accident of history, I suppose,
there aren't a lot of papers that were published
and peer reviewed about the development of
interpress and Postscript and PDF and all
the other page description languages back
in those days.
In part because a lot of this development
was driven by commercial organizations as
opposed to academia and so a lot of the information
that is available about how these languages
and technologies came to be is passed along
as folklore essentially and I'm not sure who
Brian Reid is, but there's an extremely comprehensive
history of Postscript and interpress and a
comparison between the two, from 1985 on a
news group dedicated to laser printers.
And probably 20 pages of solid news group
text talking about the very minute technical
differences between those, and how a Postscript
represented an incremental but essential advance
over Interpress, and if I remember, I'll such
on some of those differences.
And then later, in 1991, as Adobe started
towards developing PDF, it's not a paper.
Again, but it was an internal memo, essentially,
within Adobe, where John Warnock laid out
the broad vision of what they were called
Camelot at the time which turned into page
extension.
And they were talking about the prevalence
of fax machines and the problems that the
limitations of that technology had for the
people that were using it so if you were sending
an contract or a love letter through a fax
machine and it comes out on a horribly pixelated
thermal mess on paper.
That is not the kind of representation of
intent that you want to have.
When you go through the trouble of printing
this beautiful document, you want to be able
to send it to anybody anywhere in the world
and have the other person on the other side
of that communication channel see exactly
what you intended.
And fax machines were being used widely at
the time, because of, you know, essential
business needs, but they didn't capture that
respect for the original intent of the author,
essentially and so that's one of the key considerations
that sort of drove a lot of feature development
in PDF, being able to take this artifact,
ship it somewhere, again just data, not over
phone lines or the fax infrastructure and
have that be materialized on somebody's machine
exactly as you could see it on your side of
the world.
So that's a little bit of the history and
how sort of from a human sense, how you know,
the people involved in the project sort of
arrived at PDF and I'll talk about a couple
of technical characteristics of both Postscript
and PDF.
Their further antecedents are sort of lost
to memory.
I am aware of some interPressers, but I've
never laid my hands on them.
But I have some familiarity with Postscript
and too much familiarity with PDF.
So Postscript is a stack-based interpreted
language.
This is interesting insofar as other page
interpreting languages are not fully declared
programming languages at all.
So SVG is an example of the latter where there
is no stack, there is no higher-order abstraction
of facilities within SVG you are strictly
describing what should be presented on screen
or via a printed medium.
Postscript on the other hand is, as it says
a stack-based interpreted language and so
what this means is that you have a programming
language semantics, you can write Postscript
programs that can do anything in the course
of producing out put suitable for a printer
or immediate visual display device or other
things.
There's actually a little cottage community
on GitHub of people using Postscript to do
all sorts of non-printing, non-display-oriented
things.
There's tons of little Fibonacci examples
and people that use things within Postscript
that end up printing.
That sort of thing.
So you can do anything you want within Postscript.
And Postscript provided for a lot of essential
features that its predecessors didn't.
For example, you can embed bitmaps within
Postscript, where as in other page description
languages, you would send the page description
and then along with it, additional assets,
images, headers, etc. that needed to be referred
to using relatively fragile means, like a
file name.
And so this was -- this was -- ended up being
problematic for things like fonts which you
couldn't bake into Postscript, I don't believe,
and so a very common thing and we run into
this today, as people who are enthusiastic
about academic papers, if someone happens
to publish a Postscript file of a paper or
that's the only version that happens to be
available from 20 years ago, you might download
it and you don't have the font that it was
originally rendered in, and your system will
automatically and usually unfortunately choose
a bad alternative to render it in and it ends
up being useless so again that goes back to
one of the failings of Postscript that Adobe
addressed within PDF where you could send
a single contained blob across a wire and
not have to worry about whether that person
had the bitmaps or that person had the fonts
that they needed to render that document faithfully.
The most interesting thing to me for various
reasons about Postscript is that it was an
interpreted languages, but it wasn't interpreted
on a -- like a general-purpose computer, necessarily.
So you would have your computer attached to
your laser writer, for example, in 1985, and
you would send that Postscript file over to
the a.m.
Apple computer or whatever you happened to
be using and that printer would evaluate it
and render the result on each page and so
this was an example of edge computing where
the edges were these devices, where every
single Postscript output device had a full-fledged,
you know, two-spec Postscript interpreter
running on its own hardware.
Yeah.
So like I said, I've been working on this
for about an hour and a half or so.
That's as far as I got with slides.
[laughter]
[applause]
But thank you.
But I have things I can show you.
And someone's going to have to tell me about
time, because I have no idea where I am.
So if I remember I'm going to bring up -- so
this is a -- this is the Camelot project.
I wonder if it's worth trying to go to full
screen here.
Anyway, this is that Camelot white paper and
it has some handy and easily digestible chunks
of Postscript here so a big part of the Camelot
paper is motivating the design.
And the challenges that it has and one of
the essential challenges that it -- that they
identified was that because each device that
renders a Postscript file needs to have that
full fledged interpreter and because the language
was a fully Turing-complete language that
had all sorts of, even today, very interesting
and useful features, for example, you could
rebind any name at any time anywhere.
And so this might remind you of a variety
of dynamic programming languages that we use
today that are difficult to optimize, and
sometimes hard to use.
And at this point in time, people were still
writing Postscript by hand in order to produce
very intricate designs, there were, you know,
manual Postscript type setters essentially
that would write Postscript to get, for example,
the logo of a company just right and they
would have this bit of Postscript that they
would carry around in their documents around
the country and one of their things was to
simplify the set of operands so that it wasn't
as powerful as a Postscript was with regard
to the flexibility of forwarded to the programmer
or the programmer that generated it.
And here John Warnock is talking about this
Postscript file that draws a ten-sided polygon
that redefines this ang constant and then
does a loop.
This is -- this is repeat, this repeat operand
will run this block of Postscript ten times
and if you run through it in your head, it's
producing a 10-sided equilateral polygon.
What they wanted to do was get to a language
where you strictly say what should be drawn
on a page or through the output device so
rather than allowing people to write subroutines,
essentially, which is what this poly ends
up being, that's a subroutine within that
particular file, rather than allow people
in programs to do these sorts of things, they
essentially flattened Postscript into a language
where it's still stack-based and it's still
interpreted but you don't have the ability
to define constants or functions for lack
of a better term and you cannot rebind things
like built-in operators.
And so there are, you know, move and draw
line operations within PDF, they're not called
move to and line to.
That was before PDF was built, but that's
just a mock-up essentially.
You do need to write out sequentially every
single line, path, character, etc., that you
might want to render within a PDF, which makes
the interpreter simpler and makes them easier
to optimize so that when you send a PDF over
the wire to a printer that could render that
PDF, it didn't need to be nearly as powerful.
So they were already looking forward to, you
know, portable computers and much -- still
more constrained environments than what was
typical in a work station at the time.
So I think that's it for Postscript.
Postscript is really cool.
It's fun to tinker around with if you're slightly
masochistic.
Can people see that?
OK, I'll bump it up one.
Or a couple.
Better?
So I figured -- I think I've basically run
through what I have, so I thought I would
give a five-minute tour of what a PDF looks
like internally.
I'm sure you've all opened up PDFs in notepad
accidentally and seen this garbage but I thought
I would go through it and show a couple of
the highlights.
Within each PDF document -- each PDF document
is organized as an object graph.
This is interesting in a couple of different
ways and actually addresses the same use cases
that redefining procedures in Postscript had
in that language, so you can define -- each
object within a PDF can contain a set of operations,
much like I just showed in the Camelot paper,
describing how to draw a particular shape
or what text to render at a particular point
in the page, as well as sets of matrix operations
that transform the vector space that describes
the output device in an abstract way.
So this makes it possible, for example, to
have a single object within a PDF that describes
how to draw a header in a document, and then
throughout that document, each page's description
can simply refer to that object.
And so you don't repeat all the information
that's necessary in order to render that header
over and over and over for a 500-page document,
you can describe it once and simply refer
to its object.
And so each PDF contains this object table.
These are all byte offsets that you see and
there's a lot of offsets in this particular
PDF.
There we go.
Each of these is a byte offset within that
particular file, that indicates where that
object begins.
And so
this is one reason why, for example, you can't
just edit a PDF.
A lot of people say, why can't I edit a PDF?
There's a lot of reasons, but one of them
is its essential structure is fixed at generation
time, to a large extent.
There are ways to add objects and mark these
previously written objects as being overwritten
essentially, but relatively few tools support
that and so that's why PDFs are generally
considered to be immutable once they leave
their point of generation.
One of the huge -- oops.
Let me just find the -- I'm finding a font
for you.
And I'm following object references if you
want.
If you'd notice -- here we go.
So one of the big innovations of PDF documents
like I was saying was that rather than needing
to ship the fonts necessary to render a Postscript
file, for example, along with that Postscript
file, you can embed and usually fonts are
embedded within each PDF, except for there's
a set of 14 fonts that were originally defined
as part of the Adobe spec that are expected
to be at every location.
Which is like, you know, Times and Courier,
and things like that, those basics that were
available in 1994 or whatever.
So within each PDF document you can embed
whatever font you like, as well as encodings
that map character codes that are used to
output each character to that slot, essentially,
within the font file, and this is where PDF
documents sometimes run astray, where if you've
ever tried to copy and paste text out of a
PDF document, sometimes that works and sometimes
it doesn't.
Very often, the reason why it doesn't, unless
it's just an image-based PDF where it's just
a bunch of bitmaps from a scanner or whatever,
usually why that happens is because as an
optimization step, what you can do is take
a font file that describes 156 or 256 or you
know, 4,000 characters and when you output
the PDF, if you know you only used 36 of them,
you can shrink that font file, rewrite it
so that character position 0 in that font,
instead of being null, is the letter A. And
the mapping between the character codes used
within the PDF and the character codes that
are used within the font are described in
these dictionaries here.
These are mappings between characters and
in this case, separate objects that describe
how to render each character.
So that's one interesting side effect of the
optimization steps that are available by dint
of being able to embed any font file into
a PDF.
I wonder if this has any images.
That one doesn't.
Another interesting thing about PDFs -- Postscript
could embed bitmaps, but they always based
64 that data, so it could be transmitted over
ASCII-only conduits.
PDF made no such constraint, and so if you
open a random PDF that contains some images,
you often find binary garbage floating around
in it and so you have, you know, much to the
chagrin of people that write PDF tools, you
have this interleaving of clear text descriptions
that relate to the object graph within the
document, as well as metadata associated with
each object.
That's where you see this, this is a subtype
of image, you have a width and height for
the image, you know, how many bits per sample
are found in that image, which color space
is used, etc., etc., and then the key right
here, this filter that uses the zip deflate
algorithm, so as a parsing tool, you need
to run your parser over that plain-text portion
and then switch to a binary, you know, slurping
of that data for however far its length goes
in order to obtain the bitmap that you need
to render on page or on the screen.
And honestly I could do this for a long time,
so I won't
[laughter]
I'm going to stop right there.
Depending how time is, I can do more if people
care.
[laughter]
But: -- so I'll stop.
Thank you.
[applause]