I'm very excited to be here, because Papers
We Love has always been a really good community
to discuss ideas and to do research papers,
and do it in just a fun way.
So I'm very honored to be speaking here.
So my name is James Long.
I'm a web and iOS contractor under my company ShiftReset LLC
I used to work for Mozilla for about six years on developer tools and other projects
I consider myself a PL nerd with an attraction to lisps
Although more recently i've been interested in the ML family of languages
A recent project that I built that was successful was Prettier, which many of you may know
its a JavaScript code formatter, sort of similar gofmt, and it's been very widely adopted in the JavaScript
community which has been pretty cool.
Sorry.
So yeah, so I'll be honest
I'm not really somebody who, you know, prints out a couple research papers at night,
grabs a beer and
sits down and falls asleep with papers all over me.
I don't read papers that often.
But I still, I still love papers, because
even so when I look back at moments,
in my career where I really grew as a programmer,
many of them really happened because of papers.
I'm also very passionate about taking ideas
from the deepest parts of research and pulling
them up into real applications, it's very
important to me to be able to at least read
papers to have a pulse on what's going on
in that world.
Because I think some of the best things that
can happen, happen when you can do that and
apply those ideas.
That's actually what happened with prettier.
So I can think of four times when I was stuck on a problem
and I discovered a paper to helme through it.
Not only did it help me solve a problem, but
I gained deeper insight about computing and
ways to approach these problems so I'm going to try to explain all of those papers in this talk
This is why it's a little bit different talk than I'm used too
I'm going to be jumping around to four different
topics that aren't really related.
So I know everyone just ate lunch but hopefully
this will be fun.
And I will also talk specifically about what
I learned and how each paper influenced me.
OK, so let's start all the way back with college
James.
In 2006, to graduate, I had to write a research
paper, sort of like a very small thesis.
And it was supposed to be something in computer
science.
Most people chose something purely in the
realm of programming sort of like data structures
or databases or stuff like that, but I was
really interested in graphics programming
and so I chose -- I chose to study techniques
for real-time rendering of the sky
and now it turns out that most of my paper was about
math instead of programming, so even though
it was very technical, I don't think my teacher
even knew how to grade it.
Like he just gave me a B+ and it was kind
of like he did that because it looked good,
but he didn't actually understand the math.
So I guess it worked out.
[laughter]
But, yeah, so I wouldn't be so brazen as to
talk about my own paper at a Papers We Love conference
The first paper I'm going to talk about is
the paper that it was based on which is
Rendering Outdoor Light Scattering In Real Time.
I know that the title of my paper is basically
the same with a few words moved around.
I wasn't very clever back then.
[laughter]
So this paper was by Hoffman and Preetham, published in 2002.
This paper is a bit different than the rest of the papers I'm going to talk about because it's about computer graphics
It focuses on bringing realistic atmospheric rendering
to real time simulations
so my challenge was to get the techniques of this paper working in a real app
and write my own paper about that.
So I implemented it for my paper and I got
it working so these are screenshots from
my app that I created that I was able to implement.
And these are all completely real time.
You can walk around this world, can you adjust
parameters of the sky, so back then in 2002,
which is when the paper was written, I wrote
my app in 2006.
Back in 2002, the hardware was very limited.
This was a cool technique because this was
just around the time when shaders were starting go big
to actually be in the mainstream.
If I have my history correct.
But we were finally able to start doing stuff
like like this so this was one of the first
papers or one of the early papers to start
really leveraging shaders to do this kind
of stuff.
OK, so a little background.
In 1871, JW Struck published a paper that
talked about how matter is scattered by small particles.
This answered the question why is the sky
blue.
The fundamental thing is shorter wavelengths
are scattered more than long wavelengths.
So, why do we even see color in the sky, except for the sun?
If you look up, why don't you see black in
the sky and the sun as a disc which that's
actually what happens if you're on the moon
but down here on the earth we have the atmosphere,
so light is hitting the atmosphere at a fairly
uniform direction and the atmosphere is scattering
the light and it scatters into your eye.
So the reason it's blue is because shorter
waving lengths are scattered more than the longer wave lengths
violet and blue are on the shorter spectrum
you don't see violet for some other reason. blue is a stronger color as some other phenomenon
It's also the same why is is why objects
in the distance look more blue.
This happens because the farther away an object
is from you the more light is scattered into
your eye from the sunlight, so there's more
atmosphere between you and the object to scatter
the sunlight into you and not only that there's
actually an extinction factor where the color
of that object is actually scattered away.
So there are two things that we need to worry
about: Rendering colors of the sky and also
aerial perspective, which tints objects far away
Luckily if your implementation models for
how scattering works, we get both of this
for free and this is in contrast to earlier
papers where they couldn't do per-pixel-shader work
so they couldn't implement in real time how to model this.
So they had to do -- ... will you we're just
going to implement this in the shaders so
we can approximate how it works and we don't
have to worry about the difference.
To do this we need three effects.
Absorption is the effect of a particle absorbing
light rays.
Outscattering is the effect of light bouncing
off a particle away from your eye, similar
similar to absorption, and inscattering is the effect
of light that is not going to come towards
you but it bounces off a particle towards
you.
So there's both light that is scattered away
from you and towards you and this paper contains
the equations for calculating for these terms so they can be implemented by a program.
These are absorption and out-scattering
I don't have time to fully explain the math,
nor am I honestly sure that I could, but I'll
try to summarize.
Absorption and outscattering can be treated
the same way in our case.
We don't really care if light is absorbed
or scattered away.
We just need to ignore that light.
What these equations are saying is you take the initial color of an object
and you exponentially continuate it over the distance to the viewer
so the farther away an object is it exponentially gets more skylight and less color of the object
So for each pixel we generally know the point
in space that it's at and so we can calculate
the distance to the viewer and for every single
pixel we know the distance
and we can run this model.
so in-scattering is a lot more complicated
but it's not as complicated as the math makes it seem
and I definitely couldn't explain this math
It's sort of hard to read this out of context because most of it is predefined variables and functions
But the main thing that you need to understand
is the phase function.
The phase function approximates the amount
that light is scattered by a particle.
It takes the angle of the incoming ray and
returns the amount scattered at that angle.
In the original work he proposed this equation
to approximate it.
So this is the phase function.
1 plus cosine squared theta.
if you think of a ray entering from the left, the phase function approximates how much light is scattered at each angle
The most is scattered forwards and backwards
and the least is scattered at 90-degree angles.
To put this into perspective here's how it
would work in a program.
You have the sun position and a viewer position
and we need to calculate the color of a specific pixel
We generally know the position of the pixel is in the
space so we have to calculate the angle from
the sun to the viewer and run it through the phase function,
and that gives us an approximation of how much light is scattered at that point towards the viewer
So this would be about in between like the
minimum and the maximum light scattered because
it's about 135 degree and it's like in between
90 and 180.
So there are a lot more things that you could
factor in, particles of different size and
different sizes have different effects.
For larger particles they have a different
phase function which is me scattering and
that's a different thing.
The distribution of the particles in the atmosphere
may not be constant, right now we're assuming a constant atmosphere
these things definitely complicate things a lot more.
But even simple versions of these equations can produce pleasing
results.
The best thing about this paper is that right around 2002 was when shaders were taking of on graphics cards
and this allowed developers to implement all this sort of stuff with ease
in previous papers, you know, they were forced to do all sorts of other hacks
So after presenting the math for modeling
atmospheric scattering
the paper ends by providing much simpler equations that can be implemented in vertex and pixel shaders
These are simple because it assumes that constant
density atmosphere and relatively flat terrain
which gets rid of a lot of the complicated
math.
So all of the variables here are super straightforward
to calculate.
there's the angle to the sun, there's two scattering coefficients, and a few other things
It's basically some additions, divisions and
cosines.
Now, when I was implementing this, I was back
in college I had done some decent programming
but nothing on this scale, really and this
blew my mind.
I remember feeling super overwhelmed trying to pick through all of this
and even though i didn't understand much of the paper
the conclusion which was where the simple
stuff was, you know, maybe they should put
that at the front.
[laughter]
I was like, okay, that's super-easy, why do
they have to complicate it so much and I saw
this and I was like, I can just transfer this
into a vertex shader and I get it to work.
and i got it working. it was amazing.
I could walk around in this world that I created
and so, yeah, that was cool.
[laughter]
So what I learned is that first of all it's
very hard to make realistic graphics, so after
that, after that phase where it was amazing,
you know, then I looked at this and I was
like, well, that actually kind of sucks, like,
that's not really realistic at all.
So it's very hard to make realistic graphics.
It was also the first time I experienced translating abstract ideas, in this case math, into executable code.
which is surprisingly difficult
if you're an experienced programming, you do this daily
but at the beginning of the process, it's a hard
skill to learn.
It's not something that's intuitive where
we learn as a child.
It's something that takes a lot of work to
learn.
So it was interesting to go from this like
looking at these equations and learning how
to filter them down into something that could
become actual shader code.
And computers are amazing and we can create
stuff from nothing, and also, don't give up
if you don't understand something at first.
Once I found a piece of the paper that I could
finally understand, I got something working
and from there I could work backwards to the
paper and understand more and more.
All right, so that's that paper.
This paper was a bit different than the other
three papers I'm going to talk about because
it was heavy on math and computer graphics.
The rest of the papers are mostly about compilers,
so if you don't like math, don't worry, there's
no more math.
The next paper is called an incremental approach
to compiler construction.
This came out in 2006 and I think I read it
in about 2007 about a year after my graphics project
and i was just starting to get interested with compilers and scheme, and more niche languages
but I was still very intimidated by all of it.
This paper was written by Ghuloum, who created Ikarus scheme,
the paper describes his approach to creating that scheme
Ikarus is interesting because it compiles straight down to native assembly.
so it doesn't use ... i can't remember if LLVM even existed in 2006 or 7.
but it just compiles to platform assembly
and so it does that to take advantage of the
native platform's capabilities and also for speed
It was also interesting because it was self-hosted
so the entire thing was written in itself,
with very little written in C. Very little
of the run time.
So compile to assembly made the Ikarus compiler
so fast because it was self-hosted.
so every speed improvment that it made, it could take advantage of
So to somebody new to compilers, this was
very intimidating
but Ghuloum used an incremental approach to develop this, which made it a lot more accessible
and this paper outlines 24 explicit steps to reproduce a compiler with many of the same features as Ikarus
Each set built on the last, and search step
is very small and incremental and approachable.
It sort of reminds me of this talk by Guy
Steele called growing a language
He shows that when you start with very simple terms, that are the absolute minimum that you need
to start talking and actually doing stuff
you can build and create higher level abstractions
and you can build those and continue to build
on those.
This is a super-interesting talk that if you
haven't seen, you should watch.
So here's the very first step in the paper,
write a compiler for a language that returns
a fixed-sized integer.
So our entire language is just numbers.
That's it and this is how the paper approaches
it.
Let's write a small C function that returns
an integer.
Now, we don't know how to do this yet, we
don't know assembly code and so let's just
write a C function which returns an integer,
returns 42 and let's compile it out and look
at the assembly and learn from the output
and see what we need to do.
This is a really fun way to learn.
So the only part that really matters to us
is the two lines at the bottom here.
Where it moves the constant 42 to the eax
register, and then it returns.
So now that we have that, let's implement
our compiler.
Here it is.
It's three lines.
This is a compiler to a whole language and
it's really simple because the language is
literally integers.
And the emit function you can figure out.
This might seem trivial, but this is a great
way to break down barriers and make things
like compilers more approachable.
I remember feeling instantly connected to
this paper and super-excited that I might
actually be able to follow it.
I didn't really have to work at finding which
part of the paper to connect.
It was organized in a way to help me learn.
Contrast this with the graphics paper I was
like, what the heck is going on, you know,
two weeks into it, I finally found the end
and I was able to understand it.
So note that we are initially relying on the
host scheme.
Parses it into a data structure, so these
are a bunch of lists.
Nested lists, that's all they are and because
Scheme's syntax is so simple it can be represented
as these lists so we can use the host Scheme's
read as the parser.
However, since parsing lists is pretty easy,
the paper goes into a later step to show to
you to implement this remit function.
Next up in the paper is the ability to handle
different constant types, you also want characters,
maybe a floating point, booleans, no, and
all these other kinds of variables, well,
maybe you don't want no.
But we can convert that constant value at
compile time to the shifted value.
So this is a compiler now, say that you're
compiling a program that say integer 5.
The compiler is going to take this, it's going
to convert it into an immediate representation,
which says this is han integer, I'm going
to shift that value, so it shifts 5 over a
few bits and marks that as a type of integer
in the lower bits and we can go on to emit
characters and booleans and other things like
this.
So I'm going to keep walking through some
of the earlier steps to show how quickly but
clearly this moves, but it's awesome.
So far all we have is the ability to return
a single value.
The next up is to implement a basic function
call to actual think do withing it.
Single argument functions provided by the
function.
So this is our compiler now.
It turned into a recursive function, because
now we need to recursively handle nested expressions.
If it's an immediate value it emits that assembly.
Now if it's a primitive call we get the name
of that primitive call and here we're going
to implement an add one primitive call and
we're going to compile the expression that
we're adding one to and that is left into
the eax register.
because that's the return register  that always has the value that was previously executed
And then we're going to emit and addl.
So we're going to add 1 to whatever it is
in the eax register so now I have a function
add1 that we call on integers.
And you can implement a bunch of other things
like this, too.
Whatever other unary primitives that you need.
So unary primitives are easy because there's
only one value that we need to put somewhere,
right?
What about binary primitives?
So here we have a plus and two limitations:
We need to put these two expressions in intermediate
places that the plus operator can work with,
right?
So when you start adding more arguments, we
need to put multiple values somewhere.
Basically you need a stack.
So a stack is a continuous array of memory
locations and we have a pointer to this continuous
memory in the ESP register.
The return point is sort of at the base of
it and we're free to use places above it for
our negative values.
And it's based on 4, because that's our word
size, so every value is 4 bites.
And the compiler traction the current index
into the stack and so this is what our compiler
looks like now, now I have an extra si parameter
which is the second x, this is an example
of how you could implement binary primitives.
Now we have pulled out the code.
And now we are going to implement the plus
operator which is a binary primitive.
What we do is compile out the operand we move
that value onto the stack.
And then we compile the second operand or
we move the stack pointer to see how the second
expert it says minus ss word size, we move
it by the word size.
Because we don't want to mess with the value
that we put on the stack already.
And then we say addl with the value we put
on the stack with eax and are able to compile
the valuables.
You can implement a lot of binary primitives
this way.
So now we have a stack, local variables are
pretty easy.
The compiler passes around an environment
in addition to a stack index.
When a new variable is introduced, you compile
the expression, you push it onto the stack
and you add that variable to the environment
with a stack location.
And when a variable is used, we get the stack
location from the environment, and you read
it from the stack.
And that's it.
So here's the code, for how you could implement
local variables, it's getting a little long
for a slide so don't worry about reading all
of it.
I'm not entirely sure you can even read it
but there are three main points.
One is this is where if a variable is used
it looks up the stack index from the environment
and it just reads the stack.
Here is where it compiles a value of the variable
and it moves that variable onto the stack
and here's where the environment is extended
with the new variable with the stack index
that it has and the stack index has moved
itself.
So it pushed something onto the stack, we've
tracked it into our environment object and
then it can be used later to look up that
variable.
So this was the fifth step out of 24.
Obviously it moves super-fast but it keeps
it simple enough to be approachable.
It goes on and on.
I'll summarize a little bit of the rest of
the paper.
The next biggest missing piece is heap allocation
and the paper describes a simple way to do
this.
You basically preallocate one large contiguous
array and pass it into the entry point and
to allocate, you have whatever number of bytes
you need to allocate.
You and then you are able to pass pointers
around into that heap.
So that's it, right?
I mean obviously there's a omission here which
is garbage collection, but the whole point
is that this actually gets us a heap that
we can run.
It's pretty easy to come back and implement
a much more robust allocation strategy.
So now we have a heap.
We can move on to more powerful things like
user defined functions and closures.
We needed heap allocation.
And because it creates this run-time closure
object that we needed to create.
And so you needed a heap to create this but
now we have this, even if it memory leaks.
And it goes on to show you how to use macros.
It just uses the host scheme's macro system
but I think this is a super-interesting technique
where you have this very simple language that
compiles out to extremely fast code and simple
code but then you have a macro system that
is able to leverage some other more powerful
Scheme's environment.
So you let the user extend the continue syntax
and do all sorts of crazy things.
Now that we can read source code and we can
even pars it and we have a compiler, it really
is building towards self-hosting, now the
paper doesn't actually go this far but now
that we have all of that we can do this.
You can point the compiler to the compiler
source and generate a new compiler from it.
If you've never done this before, I highly
recommend T you kind of feel like you're king
of the world after that first self as a compiler
but then you kind of want to shoot yourself
when you implement a new feature and the compiler
can't compile it.
So it's a fun cycle.
Anyway, what I learned, having to implement
a language from scratch without relying on
any of the virtual machine environment teaches
a lot.
You really have to learn that you have to
build everything from just raw bytes.
It really helped me understand the cost of
closures at run time and how closures actually
work.
In general it just made me appreciate all
of the work that virtual machines and jits
do.
It really influenced me in a big way.
I remember that very first thing that it does
which is that it writes that three-line C
function to compile out and just learn what
it compiles to and that way it uses that technique
to teach -- kind of teach -- you can teach
yourself by just doing things.
So really I think about this a lot when if
you're really stuck on something and you don't
even know where to get started just start
writing something and that will start your
process about learning stuff and give you
more ideas when you go along.
When I was younger it really helped me believe
that I could actually do this.
And it's OK to ignore the complex details
at the beginning.
OK, so the next paper is about compilers,
as well, but for a much different reason.
It marks a time when I was intensely searching
for a solution.
I think this was around 2002.
I enjoyed blogging a lot and I really wanted
to write tutorials with an interactive JavaScript
debugger right there in the browser, so no
extensions, just literally was able to write
this JavaScript debugger.
This is clearly a tall order.
I did not realize this at the time, but basically
if you have this code, I wanted the ability
to somehow stop the execution right here.
And you know, I just didn't really know enough
to know what I was getting into.
I was willing to compile this into whatever
JavaScript I wanted as long as it could be
run in the browser without any extensions
or anything.
I figured there was something I could compile
it to to make this work.
He so here's a fun hack I try at first.
I'm going to start with this program.
Just a quick demo.
Oh, I'm sorry, I have to shift, fn, f1.
Cool.
So here's a fun fact.
So I started a server.
What this is is these are two iFrames and
I've load loaded a program in the left one.
And I can click this run button to run the
program.
And so let's see.
Let's run the actual program.
What the program does is it just outputs a
bunch of stuff to the screen.
0-14 hello.
It just creates a div and I can run it.
What I was wondering if can I have this pause
function that it can pause, let's say in a
6th iteration, it will pause.
How I implemented this pause function is I
created a xml request to and a synchronous
request to a server and I wrote a server that
never responds to that request.
And I can literally run this.
It terms out that Chrome doesn't literally
flush the side effects.
Because I can't even press any of the buttons.
Chrome just literally is hosed.
I just have to run this in nightly.
Or Firefox Nightly to get this to work.
So let's see how Nightly does Firefox.
So I can actually see it at least.
The buttons are still hosed.
Can I refresh?
I can't refresh in Firefox either.
So how can I get this to work?
So I thought what if I opened a new window,
because it can't stop me from that, right
and I created a different page, which has
a continue button.
What this continue button is when I press
this, it's going to hit my server and say,
OK, respond to that request and now when I
hit continue, it continues.
[laughter and applause].
And actually, you know, this is kind of cool,
I can pause in every single iteration, maybe,
so I can say run, yeah, yeah, that's the first
one, continue, continue, continue, continue,
it's like a stepping debugger, right?
For some reason it always stops around 6 or
7.
I have no idea why.
The browser is just hating me for doing this
to it.
So clearly, you know, clearly that hack was
a horrible hack, but it was fun.
So yeah, so my next idea, which was a little
less stupid, was called YPS, which I call
yield passing style which makes no sense because
you're not passing anything around.
I was thinking, generator has a function to
pause at any time.
So there anyway that I can leverage but I
wanted it to be a deep pause so what I did
was if you took this code, what if you injected
yield statements in every single extension
and you have to run this why your own single
machine and this quickly died.
He so I wanted to search for something more
robust and what I was realizing was that I
was basically working on continuations.
Now by this point I understood those problems
so well that instantly I knew this was what
I needed to do to get this to work.
This paper describes how to compile continuations
in JavaScript.
One option is to convert the continuation
passing style and everything but then you're
dealing with a whole different form of code
that doesn't run well at all in JavaScript
engines and we don't want to miss out on the
excellent jit capabilities of what I really
wanted was a debugger and not really first
class continuations.
I didn't really care about the cost of creating
a continuation.
So when you're implementing continuations
you usually make like a tradeoff where it's
either you take like a perf hit.
Or you optimize normal code and creating a
continuation is super-costly because it has
to traverse the stack and copy it and stuff
like that.
So this paper shows a technique with a latter
tradeoff.
But the code itself runs pretty well.
So the first part of this paper shows basic
idea.
Summarizes existing work and -- and it shows
two forms suspend and resume.
This is example.
Now, this is a deep suspend, so all functions
need to be instrumented so that they can save
that they can save their state and be restored later.
So let's look at suspend.
It creates a special type of exception, called
continuation exception and it keeps track
of the handler and it throws it.
So that's how it works.
Now, let's look at the necessary instrumentation.
If we have this function, we need to capture
all of this state.
So here's the first pass.
This is only half of it.
This is just the suspend code.
It's a little verbose, but it works.
First we wrap everything in a try/catch, we create
a frame object and we store all of the values
of the local variables to that frame object
and push that on to the continuation and rethrow
it.
So every single function in this stack is
going to catch this, capture its frame, recatch
it, throw it so we're going to have a whole
list of frames.
Another thing we do is start keeping track
at what point of code this is running, so
you see the index variable, which is set to
1 and 2 right before it invokes F and G. When
we resume it, we need to be able to jump somewhere.
Now, we haven't transformed it so that we
can jump it yet, but we're at least tracking
it.
So the next part is the part for resuming.
So this is the same function.
The main thing is the big block the a the
top that we've added.
When resuming we set a global restore.do restore
flag.
And it pops the flag off the stack and it
resets the frame.
We've also now fully transformed the code
into a state machine, which is this switch
statement.
This lets us judge ump to any part of the
code that was suspended.
So we set that to go to and the switch statement
will switch from go to and flip to that piece
of code.
So that's the basic idea.
You save your state, you can restore it and
you divide up the code so that you can jump
to it.
So here's our original code on the left.
We'll fully transformed code on the right
it's a little ridiculous, and maybe it's OK
if you don't care about code size and for
me I didn't at all.
It was never downloaded over the internet
or anything like that and this tradeoff is
intentional.
This large complicated code block is catered
to play nicely with current JavaScript engines.
We get to reuse all of the native stack environment
and things like that and we've only added
a small amount of overhead which is the switch
statement and some temporary variables and
a couple other things like that.
So the performance hit of normal code is actually
not too bad.
So there are a few tricky things that we need
to address.
One problem is with closeover values.
Here's a function G which closes over x and
y, we want to leverage JavaScript's native
scope for performance but it causes a problem.
When the function suspend call is invoked.
That function is still going to be closed
over the old values of x and y, the old kind
of references to x and y, so even though we
x to 3, after it's resumed.
The paper object is by boxing all nonconstant
references to variables.
So even if the references are not kept correct
across restorations, the value in the box
will still be seen across them.
All right.
So far we've been talking in terms of suspend
and resume.
If you want full call/cc there are a few things
we need to think about.
We're most of the way there but there are
still a couple of other problems where the
variable references get lost, similar to what
you just saw.
The paper goes on to show how we would generalize
it into full proper call/ccb making sure you
always keep those references.
So let's talk about how to actually implement
this, though.
If we need to transform code into a state
machine, isn't that hard?
Take this example code, we want to break here
but there's a for and if, how do we actually
be able to jump arbitrarily into that?
The thing is we need to invert it into a state
machine and have control over it.
Luckily a machine was built right around then.
So I was able to take this and hack -- I forked
it and I implemented it to like expand everything
so every single expression is a jump point
in the state machine, so if we have this function
with a why loop.
You have a switch statement with next, next
is the jump point for it to nextto, so case
0, if we're not stopping, we jump to 3, which
calls the entities, wit jumps it to 7, and
then it jumps it back to 0.
So here's a quick thing of it working.
I was able to pull this up and the page is
a little busted but it still works.
The cool thing about this is that -- this
was my proof for -- I lost my cursor.
This is my proof that -- because my main concern
was I wanted it to do sort of graphics stuff.
Oh, you're right, thank you.
That was close.
So my main concern was performance, because
part of the thing that I was thinking of was
doing like 2D or 3D graphics tutorials.
Let's see if this works.
So the resolution is a little messed up.
Let's see.
That's better.
So I wanted to make sure that I could actually
run simulations and have they will be interactive
at 60 frames per second.
I have all of this here, I can run this, and
this is all compiling out to the continuation
stuff, and running it, but it's still fully
interactive.
So the jit is able to just eat this and still
make it very fast.
But what's super cool is I can even come down
here and prove that this is running in my
my machine by setting a break point right
here and it paused and I can step through
the code so this was sort of my goal.
This is super cool.
It looks like actually works.
In fact if I interact with this some and keep
playing with it, you can step over each single
frame and see it in each frame so I have complete
control over what's going on right now, which
is pretty fun.
All right, now, since I came this far, I thought
that I should go ahead and explain continuations
as a first class value because that's super-cool.
I'm not going to explain this a whole lot.
If you know about continuations you know how
this works.
I'm transporting the value 5 back into where
the continuation is captured and the key here
is that when you call x when it's a continuation,
the function will never return.
Delimited continuations are really the best
and we saw Kenichi's talk about that this
morning.
What I learned is try to figure out how much
work you're going to put into a useless side
project before you do it.
[laughter]
So, yeah, way too much synchronous HTML requests
is ...: And how it influences me was like
spending all this time and thinking about
continuations and how to implement them really
has helped me pick up more powerful ways of
computing like algebraic effects and things
like that I think are super interesting.
Just good way to learn because it breaks down
a lot of stuff and it's made me appreciate
having power over a control flow.
OK, so hopefully you're still paying attention,
because kind of jumping around here.
Just one more paper to go and this last paper
also helped me in a time when I was stuck.
More recently and last December I just got
so so fired of mainly formatting my JavaScript
code and I think all of you know what happened.
I set out to build an automatic form attar.
I knew that for this to work, I need to take
line length into account.
I looked into all of the existing printers
and none of them do that.
They all just printed certain types of code
on one line so there are so many styles of
code in JavaScript that we have to take line
length into account to know when to break
expressions and things like that.
Interestingly enough, Go format does not do
that and people seem to love Go format my
only thought is that Go doesn't lend itself
to, but JavaScript has a crap ton of syntax
and you can't do that.
The best printer that I found was in a project
called recast and it did try to take the width
expressions into account but its measurements
were crude and it didn't really work out in
practice.
But it had a ton of code for handling things
like comments so it was a really good start.
So I forked it and started searching for a
better solution.
After being in my head on the wall for a while
I saw that I needed to implement a completely
new system for measuring the lines and also
a system for how to express how the lines
should be formatted so I did have to go into
recast but it was still useful to base it
off of recast because it had a ton of other
grunt work done like handling comments and
stuff like that, which is really ugly.
So recast, recast is the only reason why I
was able to do it in just a few weeks.
After for the measurement system after poking
around a little bit, I found this paper, a
prettier printer by Philip Wadler and this
paper shows a very simple and elegant way
to implement it.
This paper uses Haskell for its examples and
I don't really know Haskell, but because I
hit this problem in a real application and
I've thought about it for a little bit, I
knew the problem well enough to be able to
read it.
In fact once I figured out the basic terms,
it -- it all started clicking and within a
few hours I really understood how the basic
algorithm should work.
This is probably the best case of going from
I have no idea how to do this to finding a
paper and just a few hours saying, oh, I should
just do that and that's why at the beginning
of my talk I was saying I love to be able
to read at least the gist of what a paper.
is trying to say so you can pull it into more
real world code. This paper is the reason Prettier exists and is successful.
And so Prettier was born and this was so cool.
How many of you have used Prettier in here?
That's cool.
A little disappointing, yes.
[laughter]
So I will show you why it's cool.
Maybe most of you all don't use JavaScript,
I don't know.
So let's say I have this code.
Does this work?
Yeah, let's say that I just wanted to change
this around, you know, reprint it up.
AUDIENCE: Screen!
>> Oh, goodness.
Thanks, guys.
Let's say I have this code.
Let's say that I'm working around with it
really fast and you know, I wanted to change
this, to just this function call.
You know, kind of make it over here.
Oh, no, that didn't work.
Yup, there you go.
And then I wanted to say it map node and into
-- I'll just do this into an object.
So basically I can just type the code and
just reformat it and it just was going to
reformat it however it works.
I don't have to care what I'm typing has actually
changed the syntax around it.
So that was just a very quick demo, because
when you start working with it, it really
is enlightening and helps you focus.
So a brief overview of the paper because I'm
running out of time: This paper starts by
considering the case where each document has
only one possible layout and it gives you
these operators to define the layout.
There's a concatenation and nil, and text
and document.
So let's say you had a tree data structure,
here's how you might implement a layout for
that tree data structure, you would use these
operators to compose them into this layout
system so this recursively goes through the
tree and it's concatenating the show of a
tree with a comma and then a line.
So the output of this would be something like
this and this literally is there's only one
document representation so a line means a
literal new line.
It's not doing anything special.
This is the only representation for it.
Now I want to consider a document with multiple
possible layouts, we will view a document
as not just a single stream but a set of streams
and this is achieved with a group operator.
Given a document the group operator adds one
more representation of that document one where
everything is compressed onto one line, meaning
all the new lines are stripped out or maybe
they're replaced with spaces.
So here as an example.
This group has the text foo, blind with a
new line and next bar.
There are two representations of this, foo
space bar or foo new line bar.
When
you start nesting groups you start getting
into more and more representations of what
that code should be.
So group is really the key to all of this.
It gives the layout system boundaries for
where things should break.
So now we can implement a better layout function
that chooses the prettiest representation
of a document.
Pretty takes an additional parameter which
is the preferred line.
I'm sorry, pretty takes additional.
Pretty will choose the collapsed representation
if it still fits on the same line within the
line width that you give it.
Is otherwise it will recursively keep measuring
groups.
So here is back our tree code the one that
we had before.
Now the only thing we've added is we've wrapped
it into a group but because it's recursively
going down, there are recursive groups, right,
if you have unnested tree structure that is
wrapping those into groups, there are nested
groups and this would be the output of the
pretty function.
The top level aaa node was broken up into
multiple lines because they couldn't fit.
But the inner node, the children nodes were
small enough to fit onto one line.
So now we're starting to see how we can measure
something.
If it doesn't fit, we break it up into multiple
lines and we recurs down it and measure the
groups until we're done.
That's basically it.
For formatting code we need to tailor this
in several ways.
In a data structure you can pretty much get
by with something simple, code, especially
something like JavaScript is super-complex
to work with so we actually needed to introduce
a lot more advance operators that Prettier
uses.
But now we have group, concat, indent, conditional
group.
Fill, if break, line, soft line.
So sometimes there are what times when you
want to break the inner group before breaking
the outer group and things like this and this
allows us to give that control.
This is part of printing arrays.
There are so many things to get right with
JavaScript code that it's a bit verbose, but
I still think it's a pretty readable system.
It's all composing these operators and the
measurement system can take this expression
of this layout and choose -- yeah, choose
the best representation of it.
So what I learned ... Philip Wadler is da
bomb, first, that's the first thing.
Second, JavaScript has a crapton of syntax
and there are so many different ways to combine
them.
But we weren't sure this was going to work because
we kept running into cases where this thing
fit really nicely in this context but when
you wrapped it in function call they looked
terrible but luckily we landed on something
that actually works very well.
Three, way more people wanted this than I
thought.
How it influenced me.
I see it structured, as long as within between
these two statements, I just write the right
kind of code I don't have to care about how
it's formatted so it's drastically improved
my ability to code and that's all I have to
say.
Thank you.
[applause]