Thank you very much, I'm Kenichi Asai, I'm
really honored to have the opportunity to
give a talk here today.
I I'd like to thank Zeeshan and all the organizers and also like to thank all the audience coming
to the conference.
So I'm one of the rare species who uses delimited continuation constructs shift and reset in day to day programming.
So whoops -- no, it's not working.
I think it's not working OK.
Yeah.
So after I introduce what delimited continuations
are, I would like to introduce a lot, lot
of examples, to share the feelings that I
have with you about delimited continuations,
so I will go into the six examples in the
increasing order of complexities, and then
I will finally speculate some future of the
delimited continuations that I want to see.
But before I go into the main topic, I -- well,
this is a Papers We Love conference, so I
would like to talk a little bit about the
papers, and these are the early papers, early
representative papers on control operators,
and the first is about control and prompt
and the other two are about the shift and
reset.
They are similar but a little bit different
but I won't go into the difference today,
and for you, the last one is the introductory
paper that is suitable for many people, so
it will be a nice introduction to delimited
continuations and but that paper is based
on the CPS transformation, so you need to
know about the CPS transformation, but today
I won't go into the CPS transformation,
but I will explain what delimited continuations
are in the direct style so in mind set that is more closely specialized in that paper
So what are continuations maybe I should
say, OK, what are continuations?
Well, continuations are the rest of the computation.
So whenever you talk about the rest, it is
the -- it is a relative concept, so you need to talk
about the current and the rest.
So I will talk -- well, I will talk about
the current computation and I will describe
it inside the bracket.
And the rest of the computation outside the bracket.
So for example, let's have the arithmetic
expression, 3 + 5 times 2 minus one, so the
first thing we want to do is 5 times 2 so that is the current computation and what is the rest of the computation?
One we get back the result of 5 x 2 then we want to do add 3 to it and minus 1 from it so that's the rest of the computation,
and -- that is the -- I need to switch my
brain to English mode.
I came here --
[laughter]
I came here from Japan last night and it's
not completely working right now, so I -- OK.
Start over.
So the current continuation is 3 + something,
minus 1.
So given a value for the whole, add 3 to it
and subtract one from it, that is a continuation.
So it is like a function, so given a value
for whole, which is X, then we want to compute
3 + 6-1.
>> OK, what are continuations?
Well, as computation proceeds, continuation changes, so at first we are talking about
the 5X2 and the current continuation + 3 and - 1. But first we get back the 5 x 2 which is 10
Then the next thing we want to do is the 3
+ 10.
So that becomes the current computation.
And then at that time, the current continuation is just -1.
And then we get back the 13, the last thing
we want to do is 13-1 so that is the current
continuation, and the current continuation
will be empty.
OK, here are some examples.
Please identify the current expressions, continuations and their types.
OK?
Well, for the first example, the first thing
we want to do is 2X3, if we assume that the
computation goes from left to right, and so
the current computation is 2X3, and then the
current continuation is something that does the rest of the work.
So the type of 2X3 is integer, so the type
of the continuation will be given an integer
for the whole, we'll compute the rest of the
computation and give back an integer.
So that's a type of continuation.
So for the second one, we want to -- we want to concatenate two strings, either hello or hi with world.
And this hat operator is the concatenation operator for strings.
So the first thing would he want to do is
OK, we want to decide that what the predicate
part is, so that is 2 equals 3 and then given
that value, we want to do the rest of the
computation.
So 2 equals 3 is a boolean, and so the continuation will receive the value for the boolean and produce
some string either Hello World or hi world.
So that string. I think this is easy.
Then what are delimited continuations so delimited continuations is the rest of the computation
up to some delimiter.
So in this talk, I will use the syntax 'reset'
'fun' unit, RON, so this will delimit the context
up to the reset.
So for example, if we write like that, then
the current computation is 5X2, but since
the 3 + 5X2 is surrounded by reset, so the current delimited continuation is only up to the delimiter. So we have only '3 +'.
And '- 1' is out of the context. So its not its not included in the delimited continuation
Ok, So here are some examples.
Identify the delimited continuations and their types.
OK, for the first one, well, the current computation is 2X3, so the current continuation is add 3X4,
but that does not include 5X, because
it is outside the delimiter and its type is
given for the value for the whole which is
the integer, and then we will get back some integer
as a result.
So for the second one, the computation is
2 equals 3 and then the continuation is up
to the delimiter, so it
is this entire "if "expression,  but it excludes adding the string "world".
And the type of it is, well given that boolean for the predicate value we will get back string.
I think this is it, OK?
So now we know what the delimited continuations were.
So now we talk about how to use it and how extract the continuation, we use the shift
operator and this shift operator has this
kind of syntax and shift fun K over M and
when this expression is executed it does three things, it clears the current continuation
and then it binds that cleared continuation
to K and it executes the body M in the empty
context, so for example in this example what happens is that it first clears the current
continuation, the current continuation in
this example is 3 +, so the 3 + part is cleared,
so it goes away, and it is bind to the -- it
is bound to the variable K, so this K gets
3 +.
And then the body of the function is executed.
So that's what the shift operator does.
So it clears, bind, execute.
So this is somewhat complicated but we will see a number of examples today.
OK, so the first one: How to discard continuations:
We use this idiom, so shift fun K RON
but variable K does not occur in the body of M. So K is not used in M, so I used the underline,
so that it pretends that the variable is not
used in M, so the continuation is captured,
but because it is not used, it is just discarded and this is the same as raising an exception.
So for example, in this example, we say 3
+ and then we want to do some shift and at
this point, shift will -- sorry, shift will
clear the current continuation, which is 3 +
and then it binds it to K, and executes
its body.
So it becomes like the second line.
And because in the second line, 2 does not
mention K, so the current continuation is
just discarded, and the value reset expression becomes 2 and 2 - 1 becomes 1.
So that's how it goes.
OK, so let's replace the whole with a shift KM for some M. So how can we discard the current continuation
We want to hit some shift fun under arrow something into the whole.
So in the first first example, if we insert
that expression into the whole, then it will
capture the current continuation -- sorry,
it clears the current continuation, it binds
it to K, and then it will return the question
mark as a result of the reset expression.
So in this case that result will be multiplied
by 5, so we have to return some integer there.
So if we return 3 there, then the final answer will be 15.
In the second case, we'll -- oops, in the
second case, we clear the current continuation
which is the "if "expression, we bind it with
K but we don't use it and return something. And that something will be concatenated to the string "world".
So we have to return some strings there.
So if we return "chao" there, we will receive "chao" world.
And one point is we need the type of the context to fill in the body of the shift which appears deep in the middle
of some complex expression.
We have to think of the type of the context to type check this kind of expressions.
OK.
OK, here is some more realistic example.
The following function multiplies elements
of a list: So given the list of integers,
we want to multiply all the elements and you can write the program in a very straightforward manner.
If it is an empty list, then we just return
one, and if it's not, then we recursively
multiply the rest of the list and multiply
the first element by that.
And but because we are multiplying the numbers, if we know that there is some 0 somewhere
in the list, then we know that the result
will be 0 anyway, so the question is can we
insert the 0 closed there and avoid all of
the multiplication when we found 0.
So we want to replace that question mark with something so that then we when we see 0, then we want to avoid all the multiplication.
It is tempting to replace that question mark
with 0, so this is going one step forward,
because it avoids traversing the rest of the
list once 0 is found.
So for example, if we say times of 1, 2, 0,
4, then we recursively expand the whole, and
we reach to 0, and at this point, we see 0,
so we just return 0, avoiding to go into the
rest of the list.
So we don't have to do multiplication, 0 times 4, but we just return 0.
But still we multiply 0 times 2 times 1.
So how can we discard that part, also?
And the answer is to discard the current continuation, so rather than just returning 0, we say shift
fun K 0, so we discard the current continuation and return 0. So let's see what happens again, so if we have times of 1, 2, 0, 4, then we recursively
expand our call and we finally get to the
0, and at this point we say shift K, and so
the current continuation, which is 1X2, that
is discarded -- sorry, that is cleared bound
to K, but that K is discarded, so that part
of the multiplication is also discarded and
we return 0 back.
OK, so that's how it goes.
So using shift, you can do a kind of exception and exception handling.
OK, we have just discarded continuation, but we didn't make any use of that.
So let's use the -- let's use a continuation.
So the next one is how to extract continuations.
The idiom is shift fun K -> K and
if we say that, it captures the current continuation
and returns it so because the continuation is returned, then we can use it and we can play with it.
So for example if, we want to observe the
continuation, 3 + and - 1
then we insert shift fun K -> K into the whole and let the result be name "if," okay, and then what happens
is that we first clear the current continuation, so "3 +" and  "- 1" goes a way and then we bind it to K
and then we execute the body of the shift.
Well, because the body contains only K and
K is bound to the continuation, then that
K becomes the value of f, so afterward if apply f to say 10 then we plug that 10 into the whole and we compute 3 + 10 - 1 which is 12.
So this is how we extract the continuation and use it.
OK, here is a somewhat more advanced example.
Here is an identity function on a list.
So it just traverses over the list, but we
construct the same list as is.
So if it's empty then it's empty.
It will recursively traverse all the list,
but reconstruct the first element and the original element again
So the question is by modifying the line A
when we lead to the empty list, we capture
the current continuation at that time, and returns it and would then what does that continuation do?
So what we want to do is to replace the empty list with shift fun k -> k, and well, let's see what happens.
So we start from id of 1, 2, 3, and then we
expand the recursive goal and when we get
to the empty list, we clear the current continuation, capture the integer K, and returns it
So what we get is the continuation which conses, 3, 2, and 1 in that order.
So let's name it, append 123.
So the append 123 is the result of calling id with the 123, and it will receive the captured
continuation which captures 3, 2, 1, in that order.
So it will append the 1, 2, 3 to a given list. So if you pass in 4, 5, 6, then we will receive
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 as a list.
So that append is somewhat contrived definition of a curried append function.
So if you want to define append function, given list 1 you just call the id list 1 and then it will traverse the list 1 and
return the current continuation at the empty place and that it will be dubbing.
That will be a function that given the second one you can append the first one onto the second list.
OK, so this is the how to extract continuation.
OK, so now we move on to somewhat more complicated one.
How to reorder continuations.
Several years ago, I had a high school student, and she was -- she has done a game programming in Racket with me.
And when she created that game she maintained a list of characters, a list of objects in the game.
And in the list she treated the first element as special, the first element is a forecast
object of the game, so whenever she clicked some clickable object, she wanted that object
to be at the beginning of the list.
And so you have a list of characters, and
you click someone, and then that one goes
to the top of the list.
And this take function models that situation.
So given a list of numbers, and the number
n, and that is where she clicked, and we want
to return the given list where the nth element is moved to the front.
So for example, if you have the list of 0,
1, 2, 3, 4, and if you click the 0th element,
then that one will go to the first but it is exactly the same as the original list.
If you say 3, then 3rd element goes to the
front and if you say 5, then that was a nonclickable
object, so the original list is returned as
is.
At first sight seemly this function appears
to be very easy to write, because the original
list is almost reconstructed as is, so the return list is almost the same as the original
one, except that the designated element is moved to the top.
So we can think of this function as something
like an identity function that we just showed
you before, but some trick on it so you can move that designated element to the top of list.
However, a closer look at this reveals that
the situation is not that simple.
First, the nth element might not exist and
so if there is no nth element there, so if
there was no nth element there, then we have to do something else, so we need to distinguish
the two cases if the element was found or not, and when the when when the element is
found, we have to carry that element over, so that it you can count it afterwards.
So for example, in the second example, if you want to move the third element to the list, so you traverse
over the list to the third element, and when you see it, you keep it somewhere else, and
you have to cons the 2, 1, and 0 to the rest of the list and that kept element is consed on top of it.
So if you write the function that way it will become something like this.
So we declare our type that indicates if the designated element is found or not, and then we have
a loop function that goes over to the rest, but it returns not a list, but it returns
a pair of whether you found the element or not, and the rest of the list.
So if you encounter the empty list, well,
we didn't -- we didn't find the nth element,
so we say not found on rest of the list.
So if -- sorry.
If n decreases to the 0, it means that we
come to the nth element, so we found the element,
so we return the first element paired with the rest of the list.
And otherwise, we recursive over to the other
-- recurs over to the rest of the list and
when we get back the result, we cons the first
element to the rest of the list, keeping the
found element there.
And the take function itself will call this
loop function, and when we return and when
we get back the result, if nth element is
found, then we cons that element to the rest of the list.
OK, well, well, if you struggle with this
program, then you will be able to get to this
solution, but my point is that this solution
appears to be very complicated.
Does this complication really required?
And my answer is really no, there is a simpler
solution if we have delimited continuation construct.
So in this example, take function, just call
the loop function with a delimited context
and then loop function just traverses over
all the list, and well, for empty list, we
just return empty list and if this then branch
was not there, then in the else branch it
will just be recursive with the rest of the
list but we reconstruct the first one
so if we didn't have that then branch,
this loop function is the identity function, OK
but then if n equals 0, it means we found
the nth element, so we do something strange
there and what we do is we capture the current
continuation, and we reorder the variation.
So let's take the example there.
So we want to have the third element at the
top, So when we encounter the third element what is the current continuation?
Well, current continuation contains cons 2,
cons 1, cons 0 and at that time we capture
the current continuation into k and we reorder
it so rather than consing the first first, we apply
the apply the continuation to the rest of the list, which is 4.
So if you say k of rest, then 4 is past the
continuation and then 2, 1, 0, is consed on
top of 4. So we get 0, 1, 2, 4 and on top of it we cons the first
element 3, so that is what we wanted to do.
So we reordered the consing of the first element
with the application of the rest of the computation,
so we did the rest of the computation first
and after completing that rest of the computation,
we put the 4th element at the top and this
is exactly what we wanted to do.
And I would say that this one naturally expressed
the original problem.
OK, you might say that this take function
is rather artificial and you don't have this
kind of programs very much in practice.
But the same idea can be applied to A-normalization,
and A-normalization is one of the compiler passes
and you name -- you give a unique name to
all the subexpressions of the input, so for
example, given the A minus B minus C minus
D, we want to assign a unique name to all
of the subexpressions so for that expression
the first thing to do is b minus c, so we
name it e1, and after that we want to do e1
minus d so we name it e2 and after that we want to subtract e2 from a and we name it e3.
and like that, we want to assign unique names
to all the subexpressions of the input.
And interesting thing about this program is
that when A-normalizer encounters b minus c, which is embedded deep in the big synax tree, you have to insert
the let expression for that part at the very
beginning, so it's not -- it's not OK to insert
the let expression locally there, but we want
to insert the let expression at the very beginning
of the expression, and this situation is exactly
the same as what we saw in the take example.
So we want to reorder the traverses of the
syntax tree and insertion of the let expression.
So here's how the A-normalizer is written.
So A normal form will cause a loop function
in the delimited context and loop function
goes like that.
If it encounters the variable, well, it's
just a variable, so it returns a variable. If you see the minus expression,
then you recurs over the e1 and e2, and if
you ignore the red part and return the blue
part, then this loop function is the identity
function, it just traverses over all the list
and it reconstructs the same syntax tree.
But instead of that you do some strange thing there.
Well, what will you do?
Well, first you want to name that minus expression, so we generate a new symbol, x,
and then we reorder the variation, so the
rest of the continuation k is processed with
a generative variable x, and on top of that,
and after all the rest of the computation
finishes, we insert the let expression at
the top, so that is exactly the same as what
the other function did,
So let's say as an example, say this loop
function is given as A minus B minus C minus
D. So this is a minus function so we recurse
over the syntax tree so we have loop a and loop b minus
C minus D, and that minus thing is the blue
minus normal form normal form normal form 2 and that line is fed into G, which is the
red part.
OK?
Then loop a is just a variable, so it returns
a, and loop a minus b minus c minus d, becomes
loop minus B minus c, minus loop d,
At that one will be passed do the red part g,
and then, well again loop b minus c becomes loop of b and loop of c and then becomes both b and c,
So at that point, at that boxed part, we first
come to the point where the red g part is
executed.
And at this point, interesting thing happens.
So we generate a new symbol.
So at this point, well, in this example we
generated the new symbol e1 and then we capture
the current continuation.
Current continuation is the rest of the computation,
so all the lines except for the boxed part
and that part becomes k and then we continue
the rest of the continuation k with the newly
created variable x, which is e1, so that e1
is plugged into the boxed part and we get
the expression after in, so g of A minus g of e1
and so that boxed part is boxed with e1 and
on top of that we insert the let expression. Let e1 equal B minus C.
So that's how you insert the let expression
at the very top.
And when the computation proceeds, the next
thing that is done will be e minus D will
be passed to G, and at that point, again,
the g is executed, so a new variable is generated,
and the let expression is inserted.
And that let expression will be inserted in
the inner reset, so that it will appear next
to the let the ... let expression currently we
have.
OK.
And this technique is used in the Peter Thiemann's
paper, called cogen in six lines.
Cogen is a compiler generator and he describes a compiler generator in a very concise way consisting of only 6 lines.
So there are 6 lines it defines a compiler generator.
And three lines for variable abstraction and
application, because that is for the lambda
calculus, and six lines because we have static
and dynamic variants for each of them.
And in his paper, A-normalization via shift
and reset is crucially used to serialize execution
of expressions this technique is also known
as let insertion in partial evaluation community
OK, this is the last one.
So how to wrap continuations.
So in this case, we have this idiom, so we
captured the current continuation, k and then
we apply k to some result, in this case, "hello"
but it is wrapped in a function.
Well, because function is a value, so if we
do that, the current continuation is aborted,
so if we -- sorry, if we execute this expression,
we clear the current continuation, binds it
to k, and then we return the body, but because
that body is just a function, so that becomes
the value of the surrounding reset expression,
so we abort the current continuation, and
then the function we receive is argument from
outside the current context, so we have access
to the outside of the context.
And when we receive that, we can resume that
aborted computation afterwards, so let's see
the complete example.
So in this example, we want to concatenate
the string hello and the string world but
when we construct the string hello we say something nasty there,
at it says, well, we capture the current continuation K,
which is the red part and then we clear the
current continuation, so it becomes a second
line, and then -- OK, and then because the
body of the reset is now just a function,
so it's a value, so it becomes a value of
this reset expression, so at this point, boxed
function, we receive the unit from outside
the context, so that unit recited in the first
line, that unit resides outside the reset,
but we have access to that reset from within
the shift expression that is embedded in deep
in the expression.
So at this point, we access the unit outside
the context, and then after receiving that
unit, then we resume the current computation,
which is adding world to hello.
So we have abort access and resume patterns
here.
And this pattern can be used to write the
typed printf and the question is, please fill
in the hole so that the following program
would type check and behaves as the printf does.
So consider that reset expression as a printf
and then printf is given the string hello
and something exclamation mark and because
we have something there that corresponds to %s we receive that part as an argument to the printf expression. So world is passed afterwards
And in the second example, rather than world we will pass in the integer 8 so we want to turn that integer 8
into a string and we want to construct a
string "it's 8 o'clock" so how can we do that?
Well, we just fill in that hole with the shift
expression, using shift fun k and this k will capture
the current continuation, then abort the current
continuation there, because that box part is the value, so that boxed part will
receive the value x from outside the current
context, so that x will receive the argument
world and then we resume the current computation
with that, so we will get back the Hello World
there, and in the second example, the boxed
part will receive the argument 8, so that
x will be the integer 8, so return that
integer into string and resume the current
computation, so we'll get back 8 o'clock.
So %s is the first red expression and the
%d will be the second red expression.
Well, I showed you the print printf using
shift and reset.
But this idea was given by Olivier Danvy in 1998
and that paper shows how printf can be written in
type-safe manner in a standard functional language
without using delimited continuations or dependent types in particular.
And the trick is that it is written in continuation-passing
style and uses continuation in a nontrivial
way.
And if we deeply go into that paper, you will
come up with the idea that that is very close
to what I showed you today with shift and
reset.
But in 1998, I think it was a great discovery
that the standard functional language without
dependent types can actually support the printf
in type safe manner and this was printf, but
it can be generalized to state monad.
So state monad will allow you to write put
and get function and put function will restore
a value into a mutable store and get will
receive a value from there, so that kind of
mutation can be realized without any side
effects.
So for example in this example, assume that
we have a sequential execution semicolon. So if we say put 3 then value of store will become 3
And after that if we say get, then that get
will receive the value 3 and after that we
put 4, so the value of the store becomes 4
and afterwards get becomes 4 and the final
get will be also 4, so it's 4 times 4 plus
4 plus 3, so that is 11.
How can we implement these kind of things?
Well, the idea is that the context higher
order and pass the mutable cell, the value
of the mutable cell outside of the context,
and this is just as we did for the printf.
So we write something like that: So in the
expression part, we write put and get and
those kind of expressions, and we pass the
value of the cell at the argument to the context.
So context becomes higher order and we pass
0 outside.
So -- and then we can write the put and get
function like that kind of expression using shift.
So for example, if we say that within the
context, we say get of get, you need somewhere
in the expression.
Then that get expression will execute the
shift expression, so we clear the current
continuation, bind it to k, and then return
the function from v, kvv, so it becomes a
second line, and then this from v, this fun
v, the abstraction, so that becomes the value
of the reset, and it then it has the access
to the 0 outside the context, so we receive
that 0 from outside, and then at k 00, we resume
the suspended computation there.
at that point the value of get becomes 0. This is the first 0 applied to k. And the second 0 is the new value of the cell.
And you can write the put in a similar manner.
And this state monad is the kind of thing
is actually generalized to any monads, and
Filinski showed that any monads can be represented
in direct style using shift and reset.
And this paper is quite involved, and it is
not very easy to read through, but the good
news is that this paper contains a complete
code in Standard ML.
So if you can dive into the standard ML code
then you can understand the essence of the
idea without reading any of the text of the
paper.
OK, so I hope that I could somehow convey
to you how I think about delimited continuations,
and how I program with it in a day to day
programming.
It's quite simple, but it's quite expressive.
And here now I want to talk about the future
of the shift and reset, and my point is that
the current proof assistants do not allow
exception or shift or reset.
So if you write a proof of a theorem, and
if there is an exceptional case, then you
have to, case analysis if that exception happens
or not.
In our -- in other words, you have to write
the proof monadic style.
But if we can use shift and reset in the theorem proving then
We don't have to write the monadic proofs,
but we can just throw exceptions, and do
all that kind of expressive programming in
theorem proof.
So I want to help that.
But the question is, theorem prover is based
on Curry-Howard isomorphism and if you want
to use shift and reset to provide the curry-Howard
isomorphism for shift and reset, well, I don't
know, so we have to answer that. And before that what is the type of shift expression and what is the logical meaning of that?
Well, Curry-Howard isomorphism says that
if the typability of programs in functional
language corresponds one to one to the derivability
of logical formula in intuitionistic logic,
and if you write the type system and the derivation
system then and compare them, then you see
that those two are exactly the same.
If we ignore the blue part, the red part coincides
one to one.
So that's the Curry-Howard isomorphism.
And the point here is that function type B -> A  is identified with the logical implication  B implies A. So that is a crucial part but then
what is the type of shift?
Whenever we talk about the type of shift,
we have to take the type of the context into
account.
So if we have shift, then its type is affected
by the type of its context, so for pure expression,
that does not have any shift expression, well,
it can appear in any context, but if you use
shift, then that expression can appear only
in certain restricted context.
So for example put and get function cannot appear only in the higher order context.
So the type of shift is affected by the type of the context.
And in general, a function type of shift will
-- function type in the system where we have
shift and reset, it becomes like A arrow B
added with C and D and this type corresponds
to the function type from A to B, but the
type of the context changes from C to D. Well,
context of types can change if you use shift.
I didn't talk about that, but that happens.
And for pure expression, we say the answer
Type C and D is always the same and polymorphic,
so if we can safely ignore using the polymorphic
argument. And we can identify that with the implication A -> B
But for the impure case we have to deal with C and D, the type of context anyway and what does this mean logically?
So in logic we have implication from something
to something and we will never think about
the type of context there.
So what does it mean?
And one way -- one interesting work on that
direction is done by Griffin, and he said
that call/cc, call with continuation, which is a variant of shift, it has the type alpha to beta to alpha to
alpha and that is a classic type and so it's
not intuitionistic.
And that was an interesting result but of course it does not take the answer type into account because call/cc is undelimited continuation construct
So it takes undelimitted contention and it
doesn't have any answer type, and the type
of the context.
But if you think about the shift, then shift
moves around a part of the computation,
and well, sorry, if we think about shift,
then we need to think about answer types,
anyway, and the type of the context, anyway.
And if we think about what it does, well,
shift moves around a part of the computation,
but logically we have a typing -- we have
a derivation for some formula, and we cut and
paste the proofs to construct another proof,
and that is what's happening in the logical world.
So would that be the meaning of the arrow-type
extended with the type of the context?
I don't know.
But it seems that we need to think something
about that if we want actually to introduce
shift and reset into theorem proving and my
current conjecture is that shift is intuitionistic,
and it means that even if we use shift, we
cannot construct a term having a classic type.
But that's -- that's not proved yet, and well
-- well, I think that's an interesting thing to explore.
OK.
So today I talked about shift and reset and
my point is that shift and resets are quite
simple, but they're very expressive and there
is a type system for shift and reset, but
its relationship to logic is not known.
You could -- you could ask a question like
that.
Well, we can always turn a program with shift
and reset into a program without using shift
and reset by CPS transformation.
If you do a CPS transformation, then you can
always transform the program in shift and
reset to the program without.
So then do you really need shift and reset?
Can we live without that?
And my question -- my answer is, well, definitely
we need it.
Well, in -- long time ago, when the higher-order
functions were introduced, I think the people
must have asked, do we need higher-order functions?
They're expensive, they are complicated.
And we can always emulate them using Clojures,
why do we need higher-order functions but
today it provides us with a higher level of
abstraction and way of thinking and going further
and in that same thing, I think that having
shift and reset as a basic language construct
has an implication into the more sophisticated
way of thinking in general.
OK, so that's my talk.
Well, you can use -- well, I have developed
a system called OchaCaml, which is a shift/reset extended Caml-like
So you can use shift and reset there, and there are a lot of other languages that you can use shift
and reset
So happy programming with shift and reset.
[applause]