My last name is pronounced la-gwes.
I don't expect you to remember that.
I do love either the brackets or the non breaking
space in bibtech.
I get cited as goues,cl a lot, which makes
my poor, late grandfather roll over in his
grave, just too bad.
As intimated, my research is in software engineering,
I'm a professor, and I noticed, trolling through
the archives of Papers We Love, that there
is sort of a tragic underrepresentation of
software engineering research.
And I don't know if that's because of, or
in spite of, kind of the overlap between academia
and industry that this kind of gathering represents,
but hopefully we can rectify it a little bit.
In particular, I care about software quality,
so how can we build and maintain and improve
and assure real software, the software that
we use and that we're all writing every day.
And I actually do work in this area.
I know that is counter a little bit of the
ethos of the event to talk about my work and
I'm sorry about that, the talk I gave that
caused the invitation to happen was actually
sort about similar stuff and I thought I could
make it up to you by having a bit more insight
of the progression of the field and maybe
some stories that never made it to print and
so that you will forgive me.
Before I get to particular approaches, I want
to start by laying out the problem domain,
so what is it that all of these approaches
are targeting?
Note that I started with three papers.
We'll see if we get to three.
We'll definitely get to two, but the third
I'll speed up or something but I'm going to
set up the problem domain of telling you a
story and it is in fact a true story of why
I went to grad school.
So once upon a time, I was young.
This is me young.
Young Claire I graduated from college and
I got a job as a software engineer.
I. I worked in a company that had an existing
product.
And that means that it did a lot of stuff.
Right it had features.
We sold it to people.
They used it.
It had a regression test suite that ran overnight.
It's a piece of software, right?
In this organization every developer had to
go on bug duty every six weeks.
There was at least one input, one regression
test, one bug report from a customer or developer
that was causing the software to do something
weird and it was our job to film it.
So the bug that sent me back to grad school
was from a customer.
[laughter]
And a Ukrainian customer which is important,
a Ukrainian customer has a lot of data in
Ukrainian which is written in Cyrillic character
set.
And something went weird in our handling of
64-bit Ukrainian unicode.
So if there's one nice thing that can be said
about this bug is it's actually pretty easy
to describe at a high enough level that you
can understand the story and also easy to
produce because all you had to do was give
the appliance the data and watch the fire
garbage out, right.
You know, actually just describing it and
reproducing it was pretty simple.
This was the fundamental problem in source-level
automatic defect repair or patch generation,
we have a program and it's doing some stuff
correctly.
It's real world program that somebody is working
on right now, it's PowerPoint or whatever.
It has to be doing at least one thing incorrectly.
This is true true of all software.
Bugs are an enormous problem.
In the wild we might find a bug in any number
of ways but in research practice in this area
we're using test cases right now to witness
correct versus incorrect behavior so when
I say it's doing something wrong I mean there's
a test case that it was failing but we could
tell if it was passing.
My job as an engineer was to take that input,
learn something about the program and create
a small number of changes, that when applied
to the input program produced something very,
very similar that did all the same things,
but with that bug corrected.
So in the goal in automatic program repair
is to develop techniques that can produce
those patches automatically, and freeing developers
like me from the burden of three days of Ukrainian
unicode.
I'm telling you this story, because I think
that there's a slightly different perspective
that we're taking in this kind of work than
you might have encountered if you're.
They're doing really cool and important stuff
in addressing whole classes of defects, right?
Can we make it so that we never have a buffer
overflow again, can we prevent hijacking attacks
it's not at all the kind of approach that
we're taking in the software engineering community
when this comes to fixing bugs automatically.
There is a bug, it is bad, and I want it fixed.
I couldn't tell my boss, I'm sorry, I only
fix buffer overflows and this doesn't look
like one, right?
I said I've got a bug report and I want it
fixed.
So this area of research has had quite a bit
of attention in the last five to ten years
especially and there's a wide variety between
the different approaches that have been proposed,
but from 30,000 feet they are all basically
the same.
They follow all the same three steps to try
and patch a bug and in fact they're very similar
to the steps that a human developer takes,
as well, so step one is localize the bug,
and you might do a little bit of analysis
at that point, either static or dynamic to
understand the bug, right, to come up with
a way to fix it, then any technique will have
some set of strategies that it takes to create
fixed possibilities, right?
Templates or edits templates or something
like that, that they will recombine or instantiate
which they will then try to validate to find
one that does the trick.
I said from 30,000 feet everything is the
same.
Step 3, validating candidate patches, right
now I'm I'm hoping this is making the people
who develop testing in the audience uncomfortable,
because it should be.
We're going to come back to this.
The first step is very, very similar between
all techniques that try and fix patches automatically.
Bug localization or fault localization is
an area of research analysis in its own right.
So it punts to the existing literature on
this and reuses techniques that have been
proposed by others.
If you have not been exposed to this kind
of work before it's not that important that
you understand the particulars.
I can give up the intuition by calling back
to those of us who fix bugs.
When I faced down that Ukrainian bug I'm going
to have an honesty moment with you as the
audience and tell you what's the first thing
that I did.
I applied that first analysis that any of
us ever learned, right?
I put in a bunch of printfs.
This is more or less what spectrum based fault
localization techniques are doing, except
automatically and significantly better math.
They see what's execute and then they do some
computation to figure out which pieces of
the program are most likely to be associated
with the bug.
So it's nice because it gives you pieces of
prax and like a numerical ranking or score
indicating bugginess and we just do that.
Because we can only solve one problem at a
time and they are working on it.
Which is good.
So the real variation here is actually in
the second bullet where we come up with different
ways to try and change the program.
From 10,000 feet, I said at from 30,000 feet
they're all the same.
From 10,000 feet the techniques in this space
split into two conceptual threats and the
first two papers I listed are a prototypical
approach to each of those threats which is
why I picked them.
The first set of techniques are what we call
heuristic.
We've got some kind of typically syntactic
templates that will generate a program, we'll
generate a whole bunch of possibilities and
see if they work.
Some of these are randomized but they can
be deterministic, point is they don't use
any kind of symbolic reasoning.
The symbolic reasoning is what's done in the
second sept set of techniques.
>> So that I picked the first two papers.
This has been kind of the thread for the last
five to ten years, these two, never the two
shall meet, right, this vast divide, but lately
and I confirmed this intuition, I've had this
intuition that they're coming back together,
that we're getting a little bit of the best
of both worlds, I'm confirmed that in both
the semantic and heuristic communities that
I'm not insane on that observation, so the
third paper, which we may or may not get to,
is beginning to bring those two threads together.
But let's start with the heuristic and semantic
techniques I want to tell you about.
So the first technique is called GenProg.
We continue to debate what the name that we
came up with means.
One of these days it will be settled.
It uses evolutionary computation to fix bugs,
so the one-sentence summary is that it's conducting
a biased random search for edits at a sin
text level of a program to fix a bug without
breaking anything else.
So it's using randomness, right?
Now, the search space of possible patches
for a particular bug is infinite.
So the real goal here is to manage that search
space and traverse it in a way that's tractable,
right?
And random search can be good for that kind
of problem.
Now, if you want to search for something randomly,
you actually have a whole bunch of tolts available
to ut.
That's just the application of evolutionary
algorithms to program source code.
This is one of those algorithms that people
get really religious about.
You either love it or you hate it.
I've had people yell at me in public.
It really upsets people.
But the thing about genetic programming is
it's just a kind of a reasonable strategy
to take in this problem because we treat programs
as tree, and the literature on genetic programming
has a lot of understanding of how to manipulate
programs as trees and tree-based mutation
and so on.
So it's imperfect for a number of reasons
and I might highlight those later but we're
just using it because its assumptions fit
the problem domain.
Not because I'm religious on this one way
or another.
So you can yell at me if you want but it's
going to have no impact on my behavior.
Hasn't yet.
Program test cases, we need the passing test
cases because we want to make sure we don't
break anything.
Evolutionary computation is a population based
approach so that means it generates a number
of solutions to the problem at hand and then
it iteratively refines and improves that population
looking for a variant that actually solves
the problem.
So each candidate is evaluated for its fitness,
to see how suitable it is, how likely it is
to reproduce and make it to the next generation,
in this context again, how many tests does
the patch program pass, the good ones are
maintained for continued evolution in recombination.
The really bad ones, like the ones that move
variable out of scope for example, that don't
compile, are discarded.
The nice thing about manipulating a program
at this level is you'll see that we never
make a program that doesn't compile for syntax
reasons but we may move a label to a place
where it has a redundant label for example,
at which point -- there are actually ways
to make GCC complain that aren't just syntax,
you preclude most of them.
So the particulars as they fit in this framework
are that GenProg is manipulating and
uses that genetic programming to traverse
the space of statement-level edits that reuse
code from within the same program to try and
fix the bug.
So to spare you more text I'll just show you
what I mean.
Here's a program.
It's not the same program as was in the paper.
It happens to be shorter and fits bare on
a slide.
It is an implement of spoiler alert, it has
a bug.
In particular, if you give it A being 0, it
will forever and we can show you.
And when you get bigger numbers, but if we
give it that first number being zero, it will
print out the right answer and then it will
loop forever and the reason it's looping forever
is because if you subtract 0 from 3 forever,
B will never change.
This is easy to fix, right?
It's helpful to illustrate what we're trying
to do with GenProg.
So I'll show you what I mean.
It's actually the first bug we ever fixed
with GenProg, also.
I might have a quality requirement on my computation
of greatest deviser now you may think
I'm nuts for this, but I will point out that
the original implementation of make node computed
the greatest common divisor between two numbers
to figure out the -- Katz did, as well, so
I'm not completely bonkers, but really the
reason I use this is because it fits better
on the slide.
So the program internally looks something
like this.
In the granularity level at which.
It won't try and modify individual variables,
but it will be moving statements around at
roughly this level of granularity.
And we do that because it reduces the number
of possible edits, making that search space
a little bit more tractable while still be
expressive.
We use local fault generation.
This further reduces the search space and
biases it towards the code that's most likely
to be buggy.
So I've colored the red blocks here.
The green ones we're never going and try and
change because the failing test case never
executes them, so why bother.
So I had some drama with myself when preparing
this talk because a key consideration when
you're applying search to a new domain like
this is how you represent candidate solutions.
What is the thing in this box?
In the paper that I gave you, which I picked
because I think it tells a nice complete story
and it's kind of accessible to a broader technical
audience, each one of these individuals was
a modified version of the input program.
So we were evolving a buggy version of a program
into a fixed version of itself which is sort
of evocative and poetic and it fits the analogy
and it totally doesn't scale.
Because you're keeping around something like
50 copies of the PHP interpreter, which is
sort of a silly thing to do.
So I thought I'd just tell you how we're doing
it now, because a lot of the underlying assumptions
are still the same and then I'm not lying
to you.
If it sounds different from what we said in
the paper, it's because it is.
In the intervening years we've changed this
representation is what I'm trying to tell
you such that the it has roughly the same
expressive power, it happens to be more efficient
than have every individual be an evolved program.
But everything else is it more or less the
same.
A patch is just a series of statement-level
edits, so we can delete a statement, swap
it with something else, or we can append.
If we're replacing code or inserting new code
we're taking that code from somewhere else
in the same program.
This leverages the fact that's been observed
in empirical practice that although developers
do make mistakes, otherwise there would be
no point in this talk, for the most part they
do things correctly.
There is so if I forgot a null check I probably
didn't do it everywhere just maybe in that
one little node.
So
to mutate individual or just make a new one,
you just add enough random edits to a given
patch and to combine them you take edits from
one packet and combine them together.
So we want to start by picking a random location
guided by the fault localization, so if we
get really lucky, let's say we picked this
printf.
We just need some code now to insert.
I took away the colors because the fault localization
weights may not be usefully informative on
picking correct code, right, just the incorrect
code and this is a problem that's sort of
started calling fixed localization, it's totally
100% unsolved.
In GenProg right now we basically pick it
at random, uniformly.
I don't think anyone has a definitive solution,
but if we imagine we get super lucky and pick
that return statement, the individual variant
now is just one edit, insert return off printf
on line 3 and to evaluate it we apply that
patch to the original program.
We get a great abstract syntax tree.
We can compile it out and run it on the test
case.
And see if it works, which it does, because
I got lucky and it's my talk and that's how
we do that.
I will get into results into a minute, because
it's a nice story, but I need to show you
that we can patch things.
Before I do that, I actually want to introduce
the second technique that I really want to
talk about in some detail so you can appreciate
the contrast between semantic and heuristic
approaches.
The second paper is about about a technique
called Angelix it's an iteration in the semantic
body of work on program repair.
I totally fan girl this work.
I'm a little bit embarrassing about it.
Hopefully I will be able to tell you why,
so have if you haven't read it I'm sure you
all did, you can read it or you can read it
again and appreciate it.
So within this same framework we're doing
the same thing, Angelix is also the most important
thing is Angelix is local identifying the
bug.
And just the right-hand side of assignments
and conditions I'll show you what I mean but
first I want to shout out to Abhik.
He's the main PI in this work.
This made my life really easier because animating
in many slides is really frankly tedious so
in addition to being a really awesome scientist
he's also a really nice guy who made my life
easier so cheers to him.
That said, this is some source code that I
don't want you to understand because it doesn't
matter.
What matters is line 4 is wrong.
Angelix is
so we can use test cases, we have some test
cases to localize to particular expressions
that are most likely associated with the fault
and in particular, the existing work can identify
this line as faulty pretty easily.
so that's the line that we want to try and
fix.
There are two major things that Angelix does
to fix that.
It's going to say, whatever bias it's being
assigned to is wrong.
So let's figure out what it should be instead:
So the name Angelix comes from the idea of
this Angelix value.
The value that would make a given test case
pass if the expression had that value when
it was executed.
This value was set arbitrarily.
That's the word that is often used in the
literature, and we just mean symbolically.
So you can solve for symbolic value, right,
if you say, OK, instead of bias gets down,
bias gets X.
Let's solve for X and that's basically what
they do.
A set of conditions that controlled a particular
execution, in terms of that symbolic value.
So you start by executing the test concretely
and at the point that the execution depends
on the symbolic value, you can collect the
...
I'll show you the intuition on a single expression
and a single test case.
One thing that makes Angelix awesome is it
can reason over multiple things at the same
time.
I'll just show you one because it's easier.
So if we set bias to let's say alpha and we
worry about one test case, which we're doing
here, we're going to start executing the code
on this test case, so for the first three
lines nothing changes from the concrete execution,
because it can just be executed concretely
because everything has a concrete value.
But when we get to line 4, now all of a sudden
we've entered the symbolic world.
Bias doesn't have a concrete value.
It has an arbitrary value.
The condition on line 3 concretely evaluated
to true.
So now we keep executing but now we're in
a symbolic world and so when we get to line
6, bias doesn't have a concrete value right
now, right?
Bias is just alpha.
We don't know what alpha is.
We don't have any constraints on alpha that
tells us that it's greater than other equal
to or less than down.
So this could be true and on line 7.
We return 1.
And if we return 1 on line 7 it's because
bias is equal to arbitrary value.
It hasn't been changed.
Moreover, because we know what the expected
output should be, we know that this corresponds
to a passing execution.
And that's useful because we can remember
it.
But again, we don't know if that evaluation
on line 6 was going to evaluate to true.
So what if it department?
That means that we're actually advancing to
line 8 instead.
There's this other fork that execution could
take and in that case we know bias has to
be equal or less than 110.
But we also know that returning 1 here is
wrong.
So this execution is incorrect.
If you ever read any paper that uses symbolic
execution for anything, it probably has this
tree in it.
There's always this tree of execution, and
that's what symbolic execution is computing
that full set of paths that could happen.
Loops are a different story that you can ask
me about at the break.
So why do we do that?
We did that because instead of bias just being
a number, a symbolic value or a number, right
if we could set to a mathematical function,
let's call it F and that has access to all
the variables, like inhibit, up_sep and down_sep,.
We can collect all of the constraints over
that function and concatenate them together.
Now all we need is a function that satisfies
those constraints.
So where are we going to get it?
That's kind of the next question.
We use that guided symbolic execution to get
the constraints.
Now Step 2 is to solve those constraints.
We want to concatenate so that we don't just
pass one, we pass all of them.
You have a bunch of options.
They happened to use something called oracle
guided component based program to size.
It takes me about an hour lecture in my grad
school so I'm not going to do it in detail.
I will just give you the intuition, so the
idea is that we have a fixed set of functions
or operators, so maybe plus-minus-multiply.
Maybe we have a couple more shall, but we
just have a fixed set of operators and those
are the components and we're going to synthesize
code, we're going to construct our query to
an SMT solver in a very particular way that
is a loud to use those operators and it needs
to combine them in a way that satisfies the
constraints imposed by the test cases that's
the oracle-guided part.
So in this example this kind of synthesis
can totally happen it.
We return a function that looks like this.
It turns out that that is the correct answer,
which is cool.
The way that we encode that synthesis problem
is is you should read the paper two years
before it because it explains it super-duper
well.
Now, Claire, you might be wondering why did
they talk a lot about forests.
You have not used the word forests, nor have
you.
Remember in our example, I said I was going
to focus on a single expression and a single
test case.
We can actually do this for multiple expressions.
And then we're just collecting paths that
such different expressions with symbolic values.
So here's one angelic path, right?
And we know that that path is the test case.
But if we go to your left, we just go through
E1, E2, that won't pass the test case so we
don't have to worry about it, etc.
You get the point.
The point of the whole forest thing is that
we can collect these paths and combine them
all into one forest of angelic paths and then
combine all of them for the purposes of synthesis.
The neat part is that the size of this forest
is independent of the size of the program.
It's only related to the number of expressions
that you're considering as symbolic at a time.
So this is an instance in which we've modified
reasoning, so that it's only reasoning about
the increment that we're working on.
We only care about the change in the behavior,
and not the behavior of the entire program,
which means that we've taken synthesis something
that historically can only apply to very small
programs and made it be useful in the context
of a very large program and this idea about
reasoning about just the size of the increment
and not the entire program is one of the key
things that has allowed this technique, as
well as heuristic techniques to scale to programs
of nontrivial size.
It appears basically in all kinds of places
in program repair and this may seem kind of
intuitive now.
But it's one of those innovations that just
seems really obvious I think in retrospect
that the time wasn't.
Angelix very slightly different goals but
very similar underlying mechanics, except
that the constraints it had to solve basically
had to do the whole function which is why
it totally didn't scale and this one does,
which is why I think it's so awesome.
There are many more besides the two that I've
told you but I can give you a flavor for the
kinds of problems that we're concerned with
and how we evaluate them and show you some
comparison.
There are three major issues in program repair,
three major problems we're trying to solve.
The first is scalability, I've kind of hinted
at this.
The second is output quality, which is that
we want to make patches that are good.
This is a major problem, I will come back
to it because it has no suitable definition
yet and the third is we want to make a whole
bunch of different kinds of patches for different
kinds of bugs and different kinds of programs.
Like I hinted at at the beginning, I couldn't
tell my boss, I only fix buffer overflows,
I had to fix every kind of bug that came my
way.
And this is the first place where I think
you can imagine the differences between what
the techniques can do.
Something like GenProg operating at the state
level as compared to Angelix.
Now, there is overlaps in the types of bugs
they can fix, but you can still, I think just
even looking at the level of representation
tells you that there has to be some kind of
difference in expressive power.
Semantic techniques also tend to be limited
in the power of their underlying symbolic
reasoning p eng nines, so if a symbolic execution
engine can't handle it, semantic techniques
can't either.
So
as those techniques get better, the repair
techniques built on them also get better.
OK, so the first evaluations of program repair
focused on both of these two issues: Scalability
and expressive power.
And I want to stop just for a second on scalability.
Because for a long time, this was the problem.
As I hinted at with semantic techniques, synthesis
doesn't work.
>> So I think we forgot, in the intervening
years how hard this was to do it scalably.
So scalability was the dominant concern for
a long time and why we ignored output quality
for so long.
Spoiler alert.
I'm going to show you a table full of bugs
and programs that I don't want you to try
to read.
I will tell you what's happening.
OK.
The first half of this table consists of bugs
in programs that appeared in the first paper
I gave you on GenProg.
The back half has a bunch of more programs,
bigger and better programs than appeared subsequently.
The approach here to evaluate places things
like bug track and bug databases and try to
see if GenProg could fix them.
The whole point is that GenProg could fix
them in about under 7 minutes on average which
was super cool.
We fixed them, yay.
>> I'm picking on myself, but I'm picking
on everyone else, too, because this is what
we did for a long time.
But it never really satisfied anyone.
I give talks like that with tables like that,
and inevitably after the talk someone from
the back of the room would come up to me and
say something like, OK, that was super-cute.
That part was either implied or actually said,
but you know, what if I actually, I'm a real
human who works on real code, what if I gave
you the last 100 bugs my developers had to
deal with, how many could GenProg actually
fix?
Which is a really good question because maybe
I just showed up the only 18 bugs that GenProg
was capable of fixing, right?
I don't think I realized how much confession
I was going to do in this talk.
But it's true.
I want to tell but the dataset really, really
quickly, just to give you a more complete
picture of the way we've been evaluating this
and the kinds of numbers that GenProg puts
up, but also because subsequent papers in
this space often use the same scenarios that
we constructed in that dataset for the purposes
of comparative evaluation so if you read the
Angelix paper, you'll notice that they relied
on some unknown dataset that was cited somewhere
in the bibliography, which you probably didn't
read, because why would you, to understand
where those bugs came from, you need to understand
the drama of my life.
So we just wanted a real set of important
bugs that was indicative in some way and we
just want to get like the last 100 bugs or
whatever in a bunch of open source programs.
This was actually just pre-GitHub.
Which means we were actually trolling source
boards a lot.
And now they look at me like I'm nuts.
Most of the projects we studied actually and
most of the projects you'll see in the next
table have moved to GitHub since, but that's
where we were.
We were on source forage and we went back
in time through source control looking for
commits where test case behavior changed and
that gave us about 105 bugs.
It got up to 185 that we tried to fix.
We're about to show you another table I don't
want you to read.
These numbers are a little bit old but we
took this historical approach and we showed
that under controlled circumstances, GenProg
fixes about half the bugs you throw at it
and it does in a reasonable period of time.
We did that so that we could measure how much
it actually cost and show that those costs
were human competitive.
Which was the point of that evaluation.
But you should recognize the names of some
of these programs.
Things like the PHP interpreter, which is
amazingly well tested which I think is funny.
Wireshark, right?
You've heard of that.
Wireshark.
It turns out compilers can be easy to test
so it can be easy to find bugs in.
But these are real programs, they have up
to 7 million lines of code in them manned
we showed that we can fix bugs in them.
That dataset is what appears in Angelix.
This is one of those charts where they're
comparing Angelix to another technique called
SPR and also GenProg and so this graph is
just showing you what they call repair ability.
So how many of the bugs in each program set
they can fix.
I don't really like this graph, because it's
normalizing the number of defects in each
program, so there's way more PHP bugs for
example than GMP bugs.
But you know, what they're telling you is
that Angelix can fix a whole bunch of bugs
better than other techniques can.
And that's where those scenarios came from
and you're like why, Wireshark?
The answer is I could find bugs in them and
did it in 2011.
And this is one of the reasons I love this
paper.
They synthesized a patch for Heartbleed.
I also love that bugs have logos now, because
it makes slides easier to make.
They're like, hey, we fixed all these bugs,
the patches are of higher quality and also,
let's synthesize a patch for a previously
unrepaired.
If you stared at it for a bit, you can convince
yourself that it's functionally equivalent.
It's really cool.
Anyway, moving on.
So back to making strong statements.
Scalability is basically solved.
Heuristic techniques have been will for a
long time.
Other techniques in that space have been able
to operate them for a long time.
Angelix takes semantic techniques up to that
level.
It's not fully automated you have to do some
work to make it fit nicely with it.
And expressive power we're still fixing a
variety of bugs.
I think this is an open challenge we're not
as worried about it these days.
The thing we are worried about is pair quality.
This problem isn't unique from all repair.
Humans also write garbage we just want to
know if a patch is good, no matter where it
comes from.
It's also not a new problem and in fact it's
something that our concern which goes back
to the start of our work in program repair,
and I have a bunch of really hilarious stories
that go wrong when you start randomly changing
like the Python interpreter.
[laughter]
But something that I think is more informative
for this discussion actually goes back to
the second bug we ever tried to fix with GenProg
so I'm going to tell you about it.
The second bug was in a 6,000-line very bare
bones web server.
Called noel HTTP D. Somebody forgot to check
that a user provided input was greater than
0.
Before calling malic with it.
The so now what we need is a bunch of passing
test cases and we can try out our prototype
and see if we can fix our bug.
So what does a user do?
Feeling pretty good.
Audience participation time.
What happened?
We have a bug in post, we have a bunch of
get requests, we want to patch some test cases.
Of course that's what happened.
It actually happened really quickly.
[laughter]
Yeah.
So we felt stupid, naturally and we added
a non-crashing POST test case.
Took a little bit longer than just deleting
POST did, but you know, whatever.
But the point -- it illustrates the point
that when your test case is your objective
function, your test rate quality really matters.
Now I'm willing to fall on my sword at this
point and claim that a patch that deletes
posts is better than a patch that does nothing,
because at least I can get static content,
right?
But I'm not going to lie to you and pretend
that that's as good as like fixing POST, right?
I get into this argument with people all the
time, right, and all sorts of options are
put forward but there's no principled answer
in the research literature that I know of
that actually answers it.
So one possibility is that we want our patches
to be understandable by humans, although I
will point out that I had no problem understanding
the POST-deleting patch, right?
That wasn't the issue.
One thing that's been put forward and you
may have seen this in the Angelix paper is
we might say a patch that doesn't delete is
good, and I can't just get past goto fail
in this one.
That is really bad bug that you fix by deleting
a line so I don't want to say that a patch
can't delete, because deletion is sometimes
OK.
But humans are often wrong and how close does
it have stob, anyway, I'm totally comfortable
with their Heartbleed patch even though it
wasn't the same.
We might say it has to address the cause and
not the symptom which I think is getting closer,
I'm telling you this story because it informs
actually the evaluation which takes place
in the third paper which I may or may not
get in detail because the idea of how do we
actually assess the quality of the patches
that come out of this is all over the literature
as we try to develop patches.
One proposal that we've put out is to measure
quality based on degree to which results generalize
to a second set of tests.
So in machine learning when you evaluate a
model, you test it on a separate set of data
than you trained it on to assess overfitting.
So if you look at program repair this way,
the tests that are used to build the repair
are training tests.
And then you can have a second set of tests
to assess correctness.
We could then use data to evaluate the degree
to evaluate the degree to which one makes
patches to the other.
Right?
It would be super cool if it weren't totally
impossible.
It's totally impossible because it requires
two patch test suite and we don't even have
one.
Even for PHP.
So it's sort of a problem when it comes to
evaluation.
We did come up with a dataset that sort of
gets at this.
I have a friend who's a professor at UC Davis
and they have an intro programming class where
students can submit multiple responses to
super programming assignments to a git server
where they run the test cases and tell the
students.
So now we have multiple buggy versions of
multiple programs and because the assignments
are small, we can use this actually to assess
the degree to which one technique makes better
patches than the other and we did that.
There's a whole paper on that.
I'll spare you.
The short version is both tools produced patches
that overfit to the training set.
If they didn't.
Both of these bars would be all the way to
100 all the time.
It's a little bit synthetic because the programs
are small, but at least we have a lot of them,
I guess and I'm telling you so you can understand
the evaluation we do in the third paper.
Fun fact before we get there, though, the
tools actually did as well as the freshmen
did.
But students have brains, so I felt pretty
good about this.
I really did.
[laughter]
I'm an optimist.
It's worth mentioning that this is not unique
to heuristic techniques.
We looked at how Angelix does on this dataset
and the dataset that we call this intro class.
They also overfit.
Angelix was looking at functionality and deletion
in their quality assessment.
They found that Angelix actually does a much
better job of this on the patches they looked
at.
So one more thing worth mentioning on Angelix,
I actually think part of this problem was
easy to fix because one observation we had
was that what it's doing is synthesizing overly
constructed conditions on if checks.
So they are never do an e less than or equal:
That said, this is kind of sad, right?
I've just spent 40 minutes telling you hey
we're going to fix bugs in your programs by
using test cases and I told you to be skeptical
at the test cases thing at the beginning and
I assume you were, but like still I was telling
you a happy story and maybe it's actually
really a sad story.
But I am an optimist.
I think it's not ha sad story in that we have
a bunch of options, so option one is to develop
techniques that are more likely to generalize,
so now we have this one idea how to assess
at least experimentally.
We can use it to guide the construction of
new techniques, so I'm going to give you a
35-second summary of what happens in that
third paper.
That third paper starts to combine heuristic
and semantic techniques with this goal in
mind.
In general the way we want to try and do this
is by challenging our assumptions basically.
I'm going to pause for a second just as a
scientist and admit to you again I'm being
very confessional, and admit to you that I've
made a lot of assumptions in my work today
and they've all been wrong.
One of them is an it's assumption shared by
many, many techniques and that patches are
like kittens and smaller is better.
The idea is that patches should be short,
right, and short patches are more likely to
not do bad things.
Angelix encodes this explicitly in its encoding
in the problem space, it wants to make small
changes.
It's built on a technique that that's all
it was trying to do.
Everyone thinks this is true.
The idea that's being pursued in that third
paper is that what if instead of trying to
make small changes, if we replaced a whole
function that was written by a person we might
be able to capture the whole logic.
So the principle here is to use human-written
code to fix bugs at a higher granularity level
and that that might lead to better-quality
repairs.
So we're using symbolic reasoning to search
for code at that higher granularity level.
Symbolic reasoning to search to semantic reasoning,
generate and validate plus semantic and the
story comes full circle.
I'd tell you more about that but I'm running
out of time and I'm already going fast.
The point is the patches are of much higher
quality.
Win, which is good.
The problem is that we're back to having a
scalability problem, right?
This is only on those small programs.
So we're going back around in circles.
And such is science.
Oh, well.
So I actually don't think that we are in a
sad place, right?
I think that's not the place we're in.
I think we're in a happy place.
I also really like this kitten and I wanted
to show her to you, because she's cute.
The other option for how we might address
this problem is to understand and reason about
the circumstances under which perfection is
not required.
I'll tell you a really quick story about some
more results from 2012 from another paper.
Done these case studies on these patches to
see what effect they had practically speaking.
And what we did was took a bunch of servers,
null HTTP D and light TPD and we took patches
to these servers and this patch was bad.
We couldn't find a patch that didn't turn
off functionality automatically.
So what we did is we ran these programs with
indicative workloads taken from a day of requests
to an academic department's website, we patched
them and then we looked at how many of the
requests were lost POST patch as an indication
of how many indicate users would be affected
by this patch.
And the upshot.
Look apartment the last line of the table
you shouldn't read is that it totally didn't
matter.
Like we turned off something that PHP previously
did in string manipulation and nobody noticed
and not just because PHP is ridiculous, because
it is, but because bugs often happen in corner
cases.
Bugs happen in undertested functionality that
people don't use as much.
Because if people used it, they would have
noticed the bug sooner and it wouldn't be
there.
So the reason I think this is sort of a viable
option is to try and understand sort of the
user's needs.
The developer intention.
The common cases.
When is it OK to turn off functionality?
I don't want to punt and say deletion is OK,
but I think deletion is OK sometimes.
And it's sort of a good example of why I think
software engineering is worth studying.
Something I felt that was interesting that
Marius started with in the last talk is saying
algorithms and computer systems absent their
human users can't study them that way.
The reason I like software engineering is
it's got the human involved and thinking about
the user context and the developer intention
can help us understand what we actually need
our systems to do for us and when they are
at an acceptable level of quality.
So I will summarize, I told you a story about
myself in youth and I did that to motivate
a high level picture.
I told but GenProg, it uses randomness to
do it.
I told you about Angelix, one of my favorite
papers of all time -- I'm not lying -- which
uses symbolic reasoning to do it.
These two are indicative of techniques in
two broad classes of program repair.
So if you read papers they probably fall into
one of these two categories.
Told you about a big dataset that we use today
evaluate all of these techniques and then
I told you how tragic the quality problem
is.
And if any of you have an idea of what a good
patch is.
I spend a lot of time asking when I meet software
engineers, come tell me, because I really
want to know and then I put a picture of a
kitten because I'm a Millennial and I cannot
help myself.
And also she's cute.
So that was a lightning-fast introduction.
I many at 49 minutes and 34 seconds and they
told me 50, so I'm feeling pretty good about
myself.
And I think we have time for a few questions.
So fire away.
[applause]
>> Super-excellent talk, so I think this was
really interesting and I was wondering, I
had a comment on your last question on your
is deleting OK, I work at Twitter and I actually
decided to delete 60,000 lines of code and
that was actually a big win he so deleting
is great and I think it would be actually
interesting and I don't know if there's work
on analyze on what is unused because especially
in distributed systems they tend to take down
the codebase.
>> I don't mean to interrupt you, but this
is a principle that I think is beginning to
be explored in the security program: So you're
making me feel better with your question.
>> No, I think it's actually a really difficult
problem in industry when you get these large
codebases and I worked in the game industry
for a while, too and there was literally this
unknown block of code and no one would delete
it because we were all too scared.
But what I also thought was super interesting
especially in the distributive correctness
space, this is all like local single program
by defining invariants.
Is there any work in that?
>> So yes, actually and I should have caveated
the whole talk with there is work in sort
of the PSL [inaudible] community.
So if we have contracts, for example, let's
say we're writing a project in a language
called Eiffel.
So there is I think some promising directions
we can take in learning invariants and using
those
to inference.
The trick is just getting them.
So if I could convince you all to start specifying
your code, we could make it much better for
you.
You just like need to do it.
So yeah, I think there are some promising
approach.
People are more likely to specify their code
than they were H and there have been advances
in invariant learning and an inference to
try and learn those invariants to and I think
that's another important step because you
can inform all kinds of reasoning then to
fix bugs.
>> I have a question.
Are there semantics that you like existing
or not that are amenable to program repair
or systems to avoid or designs to avoid.
>> So that's a really good question.
And my opinion on this has changed within
the last six months, which makes it tricky
to answer.
My answer used to be that I don't have a strong
reason to believe that one language is any
better than the other.
We have actually tried GenProg at multiple
levels of abstraction.
It works at the assembly level, it works on
C, but I'm beginning to see as we're trying
to apply it to Java for various reasons that
the modifications that work in C don't work
nearly as well in Java, because Java's compiler
cares basically about what you do and that
means it's less mutationally rebust is the
phrase we would use.
If you think about it in Java, if you have
code after a return statement that's dead,
it won't compile.
But maybe you randomly inserted that return
statement because you're trying something
and you just had that return statement and
not the dead code, the fix would be good,
so in the framework of evolving changes, right,
maybe what we want to do is insert the return
and delete the dead code, which we know how
to do all that, right, I'm just saying that
the framework of these statement-level modifications
doesn't necessarily port directly between
languages that have stronger semantics.
Which I think just means that we need to reason
about the semantics as we think about the
modifications that are legal.
In some respect the fact that C's compiler
lets you get away with murder makes it easier
to fix, but I don't want to encourage a universe
where we're just writing everything in C,
because I don't think he is that the solution.
I think the solution really is to think about
the implications that stronger or different
semantics have for the kind of modifications
that are informed on code and use that to
inform a system that substantiates.
So the answer is no, but I think it matters.
I'm kind of language agnostic, actually.
Sorry, I should get better at shorter answers.
People ask me short questions and I just go
on forever.
So one of the questions I have is it sometimes
one of the hardest things about dealing with
a bug is writing the failing test case that
isolates it.
>> Yes.
>> Do you have any hope that you can hold
out to us on that front?
The number of software releases that actually
have failing tests on them is going to go
down, so --
>> Yeah, so I think this is a huge problem
and it's a thing that we're definitely punting
on, like, oh, yeah, you have a test case,
right and half the time by the time you get
to a test case you know what the problem is.
So I think you started answering my question,
which is these automated tested and continuous
integration frameworks add a lot of automation
to the test case.
There is a significant work in automatic test
generation to help find the defects.
And any kind of really pyramidal sis that
looks for bugs and tries to fix them.
There's this whole body of work in SE and
PL and security.
Some of that will involve changing these techniques
to take different kinds of inputs but some
of it is just an integration problem.
So I think there is hope.
I don't think we'll ever get rid of the need
of developers.
That's not the goal.
But yeah, I'm thinking a lot of that automated
tooling can just hook directly into this,
and life gets easier.
I can give you a patch and a test case for
a bug that I found automatically, that would
be a really good day for everybody.
>> One more over here.
>> Question?
>> Cool work, fantastic presentation, thanks.
>> Do you have any papers you love that look
at these kind of approaches where you don't
have reproducible failures?
Where you have maybe not even hard to find,
but still random nondeterminism.
>> So the question is asking me about nondeterministic
bugs and if there are papers I love that look
at them.
So, yeah, that is an assumption that I should
have played explicit and I don't know if we
did, is that we're assuming deterministic
failures.
There is work in reasoning about concurrency
errors and in finding them especially.
People do a fair amount of model checking.
There is a little bit of work in how to resolve
I think that work is really cool.
I don't know if it's, you know, we're not
quite there yet I think as a community in
terms of being ready for prime time.
The hardest part about those is reproducing
them, though, and a lot of times if you reproduce
it, you know, it's the exact issue which is
that as soon as you know how to make it happen,
you know how to fix it.
I think that's kind of one of the next steps
here and I'm not sure how we're going to solve
it because the real problem there is in the
testing and in the and not so much necessarily
in the fixing of it.
There's some work, I don't hate t but I -- it
doesn't get me as excited.
>> Thank you.
[applause]